<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Bellum Tartaricum, or The conquest of the great and most renowned empire of China, by the invasion of the Tartars, who in these last seven years, have wholy subdued that vast empire. Together with a map of the provinces, and chief cities of the countries, for the better understanding of the story. / Written originally in Latine by Martin Martinius, present in the country at most of the passages herein related, and now faithfully translated into English.</title>
            <title>De bello Tartarico historia. English</title>
            <author>Martini, Martino, 1614-1661.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1654</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 215 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 126 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A89620</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing M858</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E1499_2</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R208642</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99867571</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99867571</idno>
            <idno type="VID">119887</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A89620)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 119887)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 192:E1499[2])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Bellum Tartaricum, or The conquest of the great and most renowned empire of China, by the invasion of the Tartars, who in these last seven years, have wholy subdued that vast empire. Together with a map of the provinces, and chief cities of the countries, for the better understanding of the story. / Written originally in Latine by Martin Martinius, present in the country at most of the passages herein related, and now faithfully translated into English.</title>
                  <title>De bello Tartarico historia. English</title>
                  <author>Martini, Martino, 1614-1661.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[10], 240 p. : ill., maps  </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for John Crook, and are to be sold at his shop at the sign of the Ship in St. Paul's Church-yard.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1654.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>With engraved frontispiece.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Octob. 24".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Catholic Church --  China --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>China --  History --  Tatar Conquest, 1643-1644 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>China --  History --  Qing dynasty, 1644-1912 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-01</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-01</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:119887:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:119887:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>BELLUM TARTARICUM,</hi> OR THE CONQUEST OF The Great and moſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nowned Empire of CHINA, By the Invaſion of the TARTARS, who in theſe laſt ſeven years, have wholy ſubdued that vaſt Empire.</p>
            <p>Together with a Map of the Provinces, and chief Cities of the Countries, for the better underſtanding of the Story.</p>
            <p>Written Originally in LATINE by <hi>Martin Martinius,</hi> preſent in the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try at moſt of the paſſages herein related, and now faithfully Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlated into Engliſh.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>John Crook,</hi> and are to be Sold at his Shop at the Sign of the Ship in St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Church-yard. 1654.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="illustration">
            <pb facs="tcp:119887:2"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>portrait of the Tartar emperor Thienmingus (Tianming)</figDesc>
                  <head>The Liuely Effigies of Theinmingus y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> preſent Emperour of the Western Tartars, who hath Lately ouerrun and Poſsest himſelfe allmost of the whole Empire of China.</head>
               </figure>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:119887:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:119887:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:119887:3"/>
            <head>TO THE READER.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Whereas in the courſe of this inſuing Hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry there occurs frequent men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the chief Provin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces and Cities in <hi>China;</hi> which have either been aſſaulted and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended, ſubdued or deſtroyed, by the ſeverall Armies, aſwell from North to South, as from Eaſt to Weſt; leaſt the pleaſure and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light of this Hiſtory, ſhould be any way diminiſhed by the fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent re-encounter of harſh and
<pb facs="tcp:119887:4"/> barbarous names of Countries, and Towns unknown to the <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ropean</hi> Reader, whilſt his atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion follows the victorious Army. I thought it good to prefix a little Geographical table of the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries, and chief Cities, which might ſerve as a guide to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct the eye of the underſtanding, in the purſuit of the mentioned victories. I confeſs it is not ſo exact as the rigour of Geography exacts, but yet it is ſuch an one, as was drawn by the hands of their learned Philoſophers, and may well give us a ſufficient no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of all the places mentioned.</p>
            <p>As for more exquiſit, and rare Maps both univerſal and parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular, as well of the Countries, as of the Cities, and of all the rari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties they contain, together with the exact knowledge of their Longitudes and Latitudes, and of
<pb facs="tcp:119887:4"/> all that does belong either to A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtronomy or Geography relati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to them; with what may be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected from Natural or Humane Hiſtory, I reſerve all theſe rari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties and curioſities to my <hi>Atlas of China</hi> which I am compoſing; taken from their own antient re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cords ever ſince the time of <hi>Noah;</hi> all which I have with incredible pains, and induſtry both gathered up together, and tranſported with me to <hi>Europe.</hi> I will not there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore for the preſent deflower that worth of its greateſt beauty, by an unſeaſonable expoſition of it to the Readers view; but expect till it grow to that perfection, as I hope will raviſh the unſatiable appetits of this our curious Age.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="map">
            <pb facs="tcp:119887:5"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>map of the Chinese empire</figDesc>
                  <head>SITVS PROVINCIARVM IMPERII SINICI M.DC.LIV.</head>
                  <p>Occidens</p>
                  <p>Septentrio</p>
                  <p>Oriens</p>
                  <p>Auster</p>
                  <p>
                     <list>
                        <item>TANYV TARTARORVM REGNVM</item>
                        <item>NIVLHAN</item>
                        <item>Yupi</item>
                        <item>NIVCHE TARTARIA ORIENTALIS</item>
                        <item>Crocous fluv.</item>
                        <item>XENSI</item>
                        <item>Sigan</item>
                        <item>Hanchung</item>
                        <item>XANSI</item>
                        <item>Taitung</item>
                        <item>Taiyuen</item>
                        <item>Pucheu</item>
                        <item>Kiangcheu</item>
                        <item>PEKING</item>
                        <item>Peking</item>
                        <item>XANTVNG</item>
                        <item>T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ncu</item>
                        <item>Cinan</item>
                        <item>LEAOTVNG</item>
                        <item>Xu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                              <desc>••</desc>
                           </gap>ing</item>
                        <item>Quang<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ing</item>
                        <item>Tuocun</item>
                        <item>Legoyang</item>
                        <item>Caiyuen</item>
                        <item>Xanghai</item>
                        <item>Taoyuan</item>
                        <item>COREA</item>
                        <item>Kingki</item>
                        <item>GIAPON</item>
                        <item>HONAN</item>
                        <item>Caifung</item>
                        <item>SVCHVEN</item>
                        <item>Chingtu</item>
                        <item>Mahu lacus</item>
                        <item>HVQVANG</item>
                        <item>Kiang fluv Filius Mar</item>
                        <item>Tungting lacus</item>
                        <item>Vnchang</item>
                        <item>NANKING</item>
                        <item>Yangchai</item>
                        <item>Hoigan</item>
                        <item>Nanking</item>
                        <item>Poyang lacus</item>
                        <item>CHEKIANG</item>
                        <item>Ta<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> lacus</item>
                        <item>Sungtiang</item>
                        <item>Hangche<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </item>
                        <item>Cientang flu.</item>
                        <item>KIANGSI</item>
                        <item>Nanchang</item>
                        <item>Kiucheu</item>
                        <item>Canchou</item>
                        <item>FOKIEN</item>
                        <item>Kin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>oa</item>
                        <item>Ve<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>cheu</item>
                        <item>Kienning</item>
                        <item>Fochen</item>
                        <item>Cheuxan</item>
                        <item>IVNNAN</item>
                        <item>Iunnan</item>
                        <item>QVEICHEV</item>
                        <item>Queicheu</item>
                        <item>QVANGSI</item>
                        <item>Queilin</item>
                        <item>QVANGTVNG</item>
                        <item>Nankiung</item>
                        <item>Chaoking</item>
                        <item>Quangcheu</item>
                        <item>Hainun</item>
                        <item>Macao</item>
                     </list>
                  </p>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:119887:6"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:119887:6"/>
            <head>BELLUM TARTARICUM, <hi>OR</hi> The Hiſtory of the Warrs of the <hi>Tartars</hi> in <hi>China</hi> &amp;c.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE moſt antient Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of <hi>Tartars</hi> in <hi>Aſia,</hi> which was the Parent of many Nations, had been an Enemy of the Empire of <hi>China</hi>
               <note place="margin">The <hi>Tar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tars</hi> were antient E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies to <hi>China.</hi>
               </note> above Four Thouſand years: during which time, as they had many ſharp Warrs with thoſe of <hi>China,</hi> in which they were ſomtimes conquered, ſo alſo more often they remained Conquerers of the Provinces of that Nation.</p>
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:119887:7"/>
            <p>I call that Nation <hi>Tartars,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Who are the <hi>Tar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>s.</hi>
               </note> which inhabiting the Northern parts, behind that famous Wall which ſtretching out above 300. <hi>German</hi> Leagues from Eaſt to Weſt, hath ever ſerved for a Rampart to hinder their irrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons into the ſaid Empire.</p>
            <p>This Country the <hi>Chineſes</hi> ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving a defect of the letter R. an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiently called <hi>Tata:</hi> comprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding under this name as well the Oriental <hi>Tartars,</hi> hitherto unknown to us in <hi>Europe,</hi> as the Occidental, containing the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinces, <hi>Sumahania, Tanyu, Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uche, Niulhan,</hi> and the like, from the leſſer <hi>Tartary,</hi> and Kingdom of <hi>Caſcor,</hi> to the Oriental Sea a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove <hi>Japony,</hi> where they are ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parated by the Streight of <hi>Ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an,</hi> from <hi>Oviora</hi> in <hi>America;</hi> if yet it be a Streight and not a Continent.</p>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:119887:7"/>
            <p>But it is not my intention to write all the Warrs which have paſſed betwixt them; but only of ſuch as have happned in our me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory, and in my preſence; All the reſt ſhall appear at large in my Abridgement of the Hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of <hi>China.</hi> And that we may proceed with more Order, it will be neceſſary to reflect, how and from whence thoſe Trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles had their begining.</p>
            <p>It is therefore firſt to be known,<note place="margin">The <hi>Tar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tars</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quered <hi>Chi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>na</hi> hereto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore.</note> that the antient Weſtern <hi>Tartars</hi> (of whom <hi>Paulus Vene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus,</hi> and <hi>Ayton</hi> make mention under the names of <hi>Cataye</hi> and <hi>Maningin</hi>) waged war againſt <hi>China</hi> after they had ſubdued al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt all <hi>Aſia</hi> to their Power; and this before the times of great <hi>Tamberlain,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Tamber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lain</hi> never tooke <hi>Chi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na.</hi>
               </note> who never reigned in <hi>China</hi> as ſome have falſly
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:119887:8"/> writ; for he floriſhed about the year MCCCCVI; in which time <hi>Taichangus,</hi> Emperour of <hi>China,</hi> and the ſecond of the <hi>Tai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mingian</hi> Family (the <hi>Tartars</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing before beaten out of his Kingdome) governed peaceably all the Provinces included with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the compaſs of that Vaſte Wall which before I mentio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned.</p>
            <p>But the War which <hi>Paulus Venetus</hi> toucheth, betwixt the <hi>Chineſes</hi> and <hi>Tartars</hi> began in the year MCCVI. as their Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtory and Chronology teſtify, which laſting 77. years, at laſt in the year MCCLXXVIII. having totally conquered all that potent Empire, they ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinguiſhed the Imperial Family of the <hi>Sungas,</hi> and erected a new Regal Family, which they called <hi>Juena;</hi> of which <hi>Tarta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rian</hi>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:119887:8"/> Race nine Emperors by de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcent,<note place="margin">The <hi>Tar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tars</hi> Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ours of <hi>China.</hi>
               </note> governed in the Kingdom of <hi>China</hi> for the ſpace of LXX<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> years in Peace and Quietneſs; and about the end of that War, came <hi>Paulus Venetus</hi> into <hi>Chi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na</hi> with the <hi>Tartars,</hi> as appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth by his Writings.</p>
            <p>In this tract of time, the <hi>Tar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tars</hi> forgetting their antient Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gour of Mind and warlike Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits, which the pleaſures and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lices of that Country had quai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led and tamed, being alſo weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by ſo long a Peace, became of a ſweeter temper, and recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved a deep Tincture of the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture and Diſpoſition of the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives of <hi>China.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Whereupon a contemptible perſon (who was ſervant to one of thoſe deputed to offer Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice to their Idolls) called <hi>Hugh,</hi> preſumed to rebell againſt them.</p>
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:119887:9"/>
            <p>This man commiſerating the condition of his enſlaved Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, and alſo touched with the ambition of Reigning, firſt acted the part of a Thief, or High-way man; and being of a Generous Nature, bold, and as quick at hand as in wit; wanted neither Courage, nor Art, nor Compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions, nor Fortune, to gather ſuch a multitude as in ſhort time made up the vaſt body of an Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my; whereupon depoſing the perſon of a Thief, he became a General, and with a bold at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt preſumed to ſet upon the <hi>Tartars,</hi> and having waged ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Warrs againſt them, obtain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed many ſingular Victories; ſo as in the year 1368. he finally drove them out of the Kingdom of <hi>China,</hi> receiving for ſo memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable an action, the whole Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire of <hi>China</hi> as a worthy reward of his Heroical Actions.</p>
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:119887:9"/>
            <p>It was he firſt erected the Impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rial Family of the <hi>Taiminges,</hi> and being he was the firſt Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour of that Race, ſtiled him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf by the name of <hi>Hunguus;</hi> which ſignifies as much as, <hi>The famous Warriour.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>After ſuch an illuſtrious Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, it was no wonder if all the Provinces ſubmitted to him, both as to one that was a Native of their Country, and alſo becauſe they looked on him as a man who had redeemed them from Thraldome: for it is the Nature of the people of <hi>China</hi> to love and eſteem their own, as much as they hate and vilify Stran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers.</p>
            <p>Wherefore he firſt placed his Court at <hi>Nanking</hi> neer to the bank of that great River of <hi>Ki<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ang,</hi> which the <hi>Chineſes,</hi> in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of the huge Mountains of
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:119887:10"/> water which it diſcharges into the Ocean, call the <hi>Son of the Sea:</hi> And having ſpeedily order<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; and eſtabliſhed that Empire, fearing no Inſurrections from theſe new redeemed Creatures, he was not contented to have chaſed the <hi>Tartars</hi> out of <hi>China,</hi> but he made an irruption into <hi>Tartary</hi> it ſelf, and ſo followed the point of his Victory, as that he routed them ſeveral times, waſted all their Territories, and finally brought the Oriental <hi>Tartars</hi> to ſuch ſtreights, as he forced them to lay down their Arms, to pay Tribute, and even begge an Ignominious Peace. This Storm of War fell chiefly on the <hi>Tartars</hi> of the Province of <hi>Niuche,</hi> whither the <hi>Tartars</hi> of <hi>China</hi> being expelled were retired.</p>
            <p>And thoſe <hi>Tartars</hi> every year,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:119887:10"/> either as Subjects or Friends, came into <hi>China</hi> by the Province of <hi>Leaotung</hi> to traffick with the Inhabitants; For, being brought to poverty and miſery, they thought no more of making war againſt <hi>China.</hi> The Merchan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſe they brought were ſeveral, as the root cal'd <hi>Ginſem,</hi> ſo much eſteemed amongſt the <hi>Chine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes,</hi> and all ſorts of pretious skins, as thoſe of <hi>Caſtor, Martais</hi> &amp; <hi>Zi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellens;</hi> and alſo Horſe-hair, of which the <hi>Chineſes</hi> make their Nets, and the men, though mad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, uſe it in tying up their hair, as the handſomeſt dreſs they can appear in. But thoſe <hi>Tartars</hi> multiplyed ſo faſt, as they grew quickly into ſeven Governments which they called <hi>Hordes,</hi> as much as to ſay into ſeven Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips, and theſe fighting one a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt another, at length about
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:119887:11"/> the year of Chriſt MDL. came to erect a Kingdom, which they called the Kingdome of <hi>Niuche.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus ſtood <hi>China</hi> in relation to the Eaſtern <hi>Tartars;</hi> but to the Weſtern <hi>Tartars</hi> they payed Tribute masked under the Title of Preſents, that they might de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt from War;</p>
            <p>For the <hi>Chineſes</hi> eſteem it ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry unhanſom to make war a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt any, if by any other means their Country can be conſerved in Peace and quietneſs, being taught this by their Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phers.</p>
            <p>But in the mean time, being over jealous of the Enemies to their antient riches,<note place="margin">A great Garriſon upon the Wall a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the <hi>Tartars.</hi>
               </note> they never left that great Wall, which ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tends from Eaſt to Weſt, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a Million of <hi>Sorelgers</hi> to guard it.</p>
            <p>Therefore this Kingdom of
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:119887:11"/> 
               <hi>China</hi> being thus eſtabliſhed in the <hi>Taimingian</hi> Family,<note place="margin">A long Peace in <hi>China.</hi>
               </note> enjoyed a conſtant Peace and quietneſs for CCL. years, and whilſt the ſeven Lords or Governors made Civil wars, that renowned Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour of <hi>China,</hi> known by the name of <hi>Vanley</hi> being the thir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teenth Emperour of <hi>Taiminges</hi> Family, governed happily the Kingdom of <hi>China</hi> from the year 1573. to the year 1620. with as much Prudence as Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice and Equity.</p>
            <p>But in this time the <hi>Tartars</hi> of <hi>Niuche</hi> had ſo multiplied and ſpred themſelves,<note place="margin">The <hi>Tar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tars</hi> think of inva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding <hi>Chi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na.</hi>
               </note> as that being incorporated into a Kingdome, they became daily more formi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dable to <hi>China:</hi> And therefore the Governors of the bordering Countries, conſulted privatly a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt themſelves how they might curb and reſtrain theſe
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:119887:12"/> people within their limits: For their Governors have ſo much Power and Authority, that al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though they live as Slaves to their Prince, yet when there is queſtion of a Common and pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick good, they govern abſolute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and uncontroulably; unleſs by ſome higher Powers their Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders be reſtrained.</p>
            <p>Firſt therefore the Prefects or Governors,<note place="margin">The firſt cauſe of the <hi>Tarta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rian</hi> war.</note> did abuſe the Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chant's <hi>Tartars</hi> of <hi>Niuche</hi> when they came into <hi>Leaotung,</hi> which is a Province confines next to them.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond cauſe.</note>Then again when the King of <hi>Niuche</hi> would have married his Daughter to another King of the <hi>Tartars,</hi> they hindred this mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage by repreſenting ſome pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended reaſons of State.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The third cauſe.</note>And finally when the King of <hi>Niuche</hi> ſuſpected nothing from
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:119887:12"/> them he conceived his friends, they took him by deceit, and kil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led him perfidiouſly.</p>
            <p>Wherefore to revenge theſe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juries,<note place="margin">The firſt irruption of the <hi>Tar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tars</hi> into <hi>China.</hi>
               </note> the Kings Son gathered a ſtrong Army, &amp; taking his time, found means to get over the great Wall I mentioned; and the great River being frozen, he preſently ſet upon the great City <hi>Kaiyven,</hi> (or as others call it <hi>Taxun</hi>) which lies upon the Confines of <hi>Tartary,</hi> which he took in the year MDCXVI.</p>
            <p>From this City he writ a Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter in <hi>Tartarian</hi> Characters to the Emperour of <hi>China,</hi> which though writ in Barbarian Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racters,<note place="margin">The <hi>Tar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tars</hi> Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtation againſt <hi>China.</hi>
               </note> yet contained nothing barbarous. By this Letter which he ſent by one of their <hi>Indian</hi> Prieſts (whom they call <hi>Lama</hi>) in a very humble and ſubmiſſive manner he declared to him, that
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:119887:13"/> he had invaded his Country to revenge the injuries he had received from the Governors of the neighbouring Provin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces. But yet that he was rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to reſtore the City he had taken, and depoſe his Arms, if his Complaints might be heard, and ſatisfaction given him. The Emperour of <hi>China,</hi> called <hi>Van<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ley,</hi> having received this Letter, though otherwaies of an eminent wiſdom, and of as great experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, yet being now broken with Age, in this buſineſs ſeems to have proceeded with leſs Pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence than that which accompa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied the former Actions of his life; For, thinking it not to be a buſineſs of that moment as it de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved to be treated before him in his own Court, he remitted the buſineſs to the chief Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nors and Commanders. And
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:119887:13"/> theſe men puffed up with their u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſual pride, thought it not ſit ſo much as to give an anſwer to the <hi>Barbarian</hi> King, but reſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed it very highly that any durſt be ſo bold as to complain to the Emperor of any injury receiv'd.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Tartarian</hi> King, ſeeing they vouchſafed no anſwer to his juſt Demands,<note place="margin">The bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barous and ſuperſtiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Vow of the <hi>Tar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarian</hi> King</note> turning his anger into rage, vowed to celebrate his Fathers Funerals with the lives of two hundred Thouſand of the Inhabitants of <hi>China.</hi> For it is the cuſtom of the <hi>Tartars</hi> when any man of quality dyeth, to caſt into that fire which conſumes the dead Corps, as many Servants, Women, and Horſes with Bows and Arrows, as may fit to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend and ſerve them in the next life: Though now ſince they conquered <hi>China,</hi> they have left off this barbarous cuſtome, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:119887:14"/> reprehended and corrected for it by the <hi>Chineſes</hi> themſelves. After this ſuperſtitious Vow, ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vancing his revenging Arms, he beſieged <hi>Leaotung</hi>
               <note place="margin">The chiefe City of <hi>Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aoyang</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſieged and taken.</note> (which was the chief City of the Province of <hi>Leaoyang</hi>) with 50000 men. But the City was defended by exceeding many men, who ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally were all armed with muſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quets: The <hi>Tartars</hi> had nothing but their Scymetars, with Bows and Arrows, which they diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge with ſtrange dexterity &amp; Art. But becauſe they chiefly feared the muſquet bullets, they reſolved by a Stratagem to make that unknown Inſtrument leſs hurtfull to them than their Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies did imagin.<note place="margin">A Strata<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gem a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt muſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>quets.</note> For the <hi>Tarta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rian</hi> King commanded ſuch as made the firſt onſet, to carry a thick hard board for their Shield, which was as good to them as a
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:119887:14"/> wooden Wall; theſe men were ſeconded by other Companies who carried Ladders to climb up the Walls; and the Horſe came up in the Rear. In this manner he ſet upon the City in four quarters, and received the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge of their Muſquets againſt his Wooden wall; Then in a mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment the ſcaling ladders being applied, before they could charge again, they were upon the Walls and enterd the City; for ſuch is the quickneſs and nimbleneſs of the <hi>Tartars</hi> (in which they excel all Nations, and in which alſo they place their chief art) that in a trice, they either prevail in their Deſigns, or retire: and the little skill the <hi>Chineſes</hi> had in the uſe of Muſquets, was no ſmall hinderance to the War. For the <hi>Tartars</hi> quickneſs and nimblenes not giving them time to charge
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:119887:15"/> again, being aſtoniſhed with the ſuddain inundation of armed men, they preſently fled which way ſoever they could; but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing purſued by the ſwift <hi>Tartari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an</hi> Horſe, moſt of them periſhed in the taking of this great City. This City being taken, the <hi>Tartar</hi> like a Torrent over-run many others of leſs note,<note place="margin">Many o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties taken.</note> but amongſt others, he took that noble City <hi>Evamg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning,</hi> and over-runing moſt ſpee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily the whole Country of <hi>Leao<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tung,</hi> he entred the Province of <hi>Pekin,</hi> and coming within ſeven Leagues of the very Imperial Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, He durſt not advance, fearing the Enemy might compas or ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>round him, becauſe he heard that a world of men came in to help their diſtreſſed Prince. But the <hi>Tartar</hi> ſtruck ſuch a terrour into the hearts of all the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries he had paſſed, as both Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dier
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:119887:15"/> and Citizen leaving their Houſes left the empty walls to the <hi>Tartarians</hi> poſſeſſion, knowing the <hi>Tartar</hi> to have that cuſtom and practice to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy and put all to fire and ſword that did reſiſt, and only pillage the Cities that ſubmitted,<note place="margin">How the <hi>Tartars</hi> u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed their conquered Towns.</note> leaving the Citizens alive, and under a milder Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment. By which means ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving collected a world of Riches he returned to <hi>Leaotung</hi> victori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous. And becauſe his Southſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers had perſwaded him that the ſtanding of the old Walls were unfortunate, he beat them down, and compaſſed them about with new, fortifying them with new Munitions, and there proclamed himſelf Emperour of <hi>China:</hi>
               <note place="margin">The <hi>Tar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tar</hi> calls himſelf Emperour of <hi>China, An.</hi> 1618.</note> For although as yet he had taken no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of <hi>China,</hi> but only the skirts of the Eaſtern Country of
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:119887:16"/> the Province of <hi>Leaotung,</hi> yet in his hopes and aſpiring thoughts he had devoured the whole King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom: wherefore he was called in the <hi>China</hi> language <hi>Theien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mingus</hi> in the third year of his Reign, which was in that of one thouſand ſix hundred and eigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teen.</p>
            <p>In this year ſome in authority about the Emperour <hi>Vanley,</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded the baniſhment of the Prieſts, who did then preach the Chriſtian Religion to that Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; But the Emperour (who in his heart loved Chriſtianity, and thoſe particularly that firſt plan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted that Religion amongſt them) gave no ear for a long while to their Demands; But at length overcome by the importunity of a chief Commander, who had e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver been a ſore Enemy to Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Religion, and was called
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:119887:16"/> 
               <hi>Xinchio,</hi> it was ordeined and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clamed that all thoſe <hi>Fathers</hi> that did propagate Chriſtian Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion ſhould be baniſhed the Kingdom. Upon which ſome of them were ſecretly concealed in ſeveral Provinces by ſome Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Governours,<note place="margin">God puni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed <hi>China</hi> for their perſecuti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians.</note> others being taken were carried in great Cages to <hi>Macao,</hi> where being ſhut up day and night, ſuffered extremely, whilſt others alſo be-being whipt out of the Country, rejoyced to ſuffer ſomthing for his ſake whoſe name they bore; and that which added more af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fliction to all theſe miſeries, was the Emperour <hi>Vanley</hi>'s Prohibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to all his to profeſs Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Religion. But upon this oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion the Chriſtians of <hi>China</hi> (who from the horrid wilder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of Infidelity, had been brought to the pleaſant Paſtures
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:119887:17"/> of Chriſtianity) gave illuſtrious examples of their Faith &amp; Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtancy; but the longer Narration of this glorious perſecution is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved for another place. I only touch it here, to admire the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Providence of God, who raiſed ſo ſharp War againſt <hi>Chi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na,</hi> when they neglected Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Peace; and permited at the ſame time, theſe <hi>Tartars</hi> to take ſo deep a root in this Empire of <hi>China,</hi> as afterward grew to that height, as both to extirpate the Royal Family of the <hi>Taiminges,</hi> together with the Kingdom, at the very ſame time they went about utterly to deſtroy all Chriſtiani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty. But it happened in this, as or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinarily it doth; for by this very perſecution, Chriſtian Religion grew to that height and great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, that the Church glories to behold, and unleſs God vouch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſafe
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:119887:17"/> to lend a potent helping hand, the vaſt Kingdome of <hi>Chi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na</hi> is utterly overthrown.</p>
            <p>In the mean time the <hi>Chineſes</hi> were very ſolicitous to expell this Enemy from the bowells of their Country, and firſt they ſelected very chief and eminent men for Commanders and Governours; then they gathered an Army of ſix hundred thouſand choiſe Sol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers. The King of <hi>Corea</hi> alſo ſent to the Emperour of <hi>China,</hi> twelve thouſand; with this po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent Army therefore they went out in the begining of <hi>March</hi> MDCXIX. to give Battail to the Enemy. The <hi>Tartars</hi> reſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved to meet them with an undan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted courage; and for a good while the event and victory was very doubtfull; but in the end the Army of <hi>China</hi> was wholly routed, and their chief Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manders,
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:119887:18"/> with fifty thouſand men were all ſlain: The <hi>Tartars</hi> according to their cuſtome, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecute the victory with all quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and diligence; for the ſame day they took and ſacked two Cities which they burned. After this, they over-run that whole Country, and came to the very Walls of <hi>Pekin,</hi> the Emperours Court; but durſt not venture to beſiege it, becauſe they knew (beſides the infinite number of Canons it contained) there was lodged fourſcore thouſand Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers in it.</p>
            <p>But the <hi>Chineſes</hi> confeſs that there was ſuch a fear and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſternation in the City, that the King thought to have left that City and gone into the Southern parts of the Kingdom, which he had effectually performed, had not ſome Commanders ſugge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:119887:18"/> that his flight would give courage to the Victorious, and breed trouble and confuſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in the whole Empire, being that to fly is nothing elfs but to yield up the Land to the Enemy. Nay more, they ſay the diſorders were ſuch in the City, that if the <hi>Tartar</hi> had come on, he infallibly had made himſelf Maſter of it. But the Enemy was more greedy of Prey, and therefore like a Lightening they over-run all, ſpoiling and burning all Towns and Cities, and killing and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroying an immenſe company of <hi>Chineſes</hi> in a moſt cruell man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner,<note place="margin">The <hi>Tar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tars</hi> return with great Riches.</note> and leaving all theſe places diſmantled and without Gariſons, laden with infinite Riches, they returned victorious to <hi>Leaotung,</hi> where they had their firſt foot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</p>
            <p>After theſe things had paſſed,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:119887:19"/> that renouned emperour of <hi>Chi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na</hi> call'd <hi>Vanley</hi> died,<note place="margin">The Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour <hi>Vanle<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> dies <hi>Taichangus</hi> ſucceeds and dyes.</note> and left his Son <hi>Taichangus</hi> to ſucceed him; who begun to gather a new Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my againſt the <hi>Tartars;</hi> but after four moneths reign he alſo died.</p>
            <p>To him ſucceeded <hi>Theinkius,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Theinkius</hi> is choſen.</note> who as ſoon as he aſſumed the Crown ſent an Embaſſadour, with many magnificent Preſents, and worthy of the <hi>China</hi> Monar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chy, to the King of <hi>Corea;</hi> The end of this Embaſſage was to thank him for the Auxiliary for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces ſent to his Grandfather, as alſo to comfort him for the loſs he had received in the late ſervice of <hi>China,</hi> and finally to ſolicite and preſſe for further ſuccours; For it ſeems thoſe of <hi>Corea,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Thoſe of <hi>Corea</hi> more valiant than the <hi>Chineſes.</hi>
               </note> as they are nearer to <hi>Ja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pony,</hi> ſo they participate more of that warlike Spirit and Forti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude, than thoſe of <hi>China</hi> doe.</p>
            <pb n="27" facs="tcp:119887:19"/>
            <p>Beſides, that he might more ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectually divert the imminent danger of his Kingdoms ruin,<note place="margin">New pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parations againſt the <hi>Tartars.</hi>
               </note> he leavied new Forces throughout all the Kingdom, which he ſent into the Country of <hi>Leaotung,</hi> to hinder the irruption of the <hi>Tar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tars</hi> any further into the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try; And for their better ſupply with neceſſary Proviſion, he maintained a great Navy in the Haven of <hi>Thiencin</hi> to carry Corn and other neceſſaries for their maintenance. This Port of <hi>Thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>encin</hi>
               <note place="margin">The Port of <hi>Thien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cin</hi> very commodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous.</note> is a Station to which an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>credible number of ſhips reſort, both by Sea and River, from all parts of <hi>China.</hi> So as by this means, by a very ſhort and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendious way, they were eaſily provided with all neceſſaries. For all the whole Country of <hi>Leaotung</hi> is almoſt invironed with the Sea, and the furtheſt
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:119887:20"/> part is but two daies diſtant by wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter from this Port of <hi>Thiencin;</hi> but by land far more time is neceſſary.</p>
            <p>Amongſt other Commanders which came with ſuccours to their Prince,<note place="margin">The vali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ant <hi>Ama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zon</hi> of <hi>Chi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na.</hi>
               </note> there was one <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roick</hi> Lady, whom we may well call the <hi>Amazon</hi> or <hi>Pentheſile<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an</hi> of <hi>China.</hi> She brought along with her three thouſand, from the remote Province of <hi>Suchuen carrying all</hi> not only Maſculine minds, but mens habits alſo, and aſſumed Titles more becoming men than women. This noble and generous Lady, gave many rare proofs of her courage and valour, not only againſt theſe <hi>Tartars,</hi> but alſo againſt the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bells which afterwards riſs a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt their Lord and Emperour. But now ſhe came in this War to ſupply her Sons place, whom ſhe left at home in his own King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome,
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:119887:20"/> as being yet a Child, and not able to perform that Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage and Duty to which he was obliged. For in the mountains of the Country of <hi>Suchuen</hi> there is a King, not ſubject to him of <hi>China,</hi> but an abſolute Prince; yet ſo as he receives the Honor and Title of a King from the Emperour of <hi>China;</hi> after which Inveſtiture, his Subjects only o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bey him and pay Tribute; But becauſe they ſurpaſs all others in Valour and Courage, therefore they are uſed by the Kings of <hi>China</hi> in warlick Affairs.</p>
            <p>By occaſion of this war the two noble Chriſtian Doctors,<note place="margin">The firſt invention of the Chriſtians to advance Chriſtia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity.</note> 
               <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Michael,</hi> found means to perſwade the Emperour to demand of the <hi>Portugeſes</hi> of <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cao,</hi> ſome greater Pieces, and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo ſome Gunnes and Gunners; hoping by this means alſo to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtore
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:119887:21"/> the baniſhed Fathers of Chriſtianity, as alſo the Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on it ſelf. And their Propoſition took effect, for both the one and the other were ſent for, and the Fathers publickly admitted a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>again, and many new Souldiers of <hi>Portugal</hi> came to help the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my.</p>
            <p>But God did moſt abundant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly recompence this favour done to Chriſtianity; For before the <hi>Portugeſe</hi> arrived, his Army had caſt the <hi>Tartars</hi> out of the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try of <hi>Leaotung,</hi> by means of the Inhabitants of that Country, who being much exaſperated by the <hi>Tartarians</hi> cruelty,<note place="margin">The <hi>Tar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tars</hi> are caſt out.</note> opened their City Gates as ſoon as the King of <hi>China</hi>'s Army appeared, and riſing againſt their Gariſon, gave entrance to the Army. In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſomuch as they recovered the Metropolitan Town of <hi>Leaotung;</hi>
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:119887:21"/> For the King of <hi>Tartary</hi> being diverted by other Wars at home could not come ſoon enough to relieve it: So as by this means the affairs of <hi>China</hi> began to recover Life, and Strength, and the <hi>Tar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tars</hi> ſeemed wholly reſtrained.</p>
            <p>But though Fortune ſeemed to ſhew a ſmiling face for <hi>China,</hi>
               <note place="margin">The <hi>Tar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tars</hi> make war again.</note> yet, as her cuſtome is, ſhe ſtood not long conſtant and ſtable: For the <hi>Tartarian</hi> King having diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patched his affairs in <hi>Tartary,</hi> ſent preſently ſixty thouſand Horſe to beſiege <hi>Leaoyang</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain; promiſing that himſelf in perſon would follow with greater Forces.<note place="margin">They be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeige <hi>Lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oyang,</hi> and take it</note> And this Army took that ſtrong City in the ſpace of forty hours; both par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties fighting with ſuch vigour and fierceneſs, that thirty thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand of the Gariſon were killed, and the <hi>Tartars</hi> loſt about twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:119887:22"/> thouſand of theirs. Nay the <hi>Chi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſes</hi> affirm, that they had never woon the City, had not the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernor been corrupted by great promiſes of reward, to open them one of the Gates of the Town. But be it as it will, the <hi>Tartars</hi> woon the Town; The Vice-Roy hanged himſelf for grief. But the Kings Viſitor, judging it unworthy to beſtow the Title of a King upon the <hi>Barbarian,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Conſtancy rewarded by the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemy.</note> In admiration and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward of his Conſtancy and Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>delity, obtained life and free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, but he knowing that accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the cuſtom of <hi>China,</hi> he was guilty of death, becauſe he had fought unluckily, more cruel to himſelf than the barbarous Enemy, hanged himſelf in his own Garters.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Tartars</hi> having taken the City, proclamed by Edict, that
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:119887:22"/> they ſhould kill none, if they would cut their hair, and uſe the <hi>Tartarians</hi> Habit.<note place="margin">The <hi>Tar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tars</hi> Habits and Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners.</note> For the <hi>Tar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tars</hi> (that I may ſay ſomething of their Manners, as my ſubject gives me occaſion) doe ſhave both the Head and Beard, reſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving only the Muſtachoes, which they extend to a great length, and in the hinder part of their heads they leave a Tuff, which being curiouſly woven and pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, they let hang down careleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly below their ſhoulders; they have a round and low Cap, which is alwaies garniſhed round with ſome pretious skin three fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers broad, of <hi>Caſtor,</hi> or <hi>Zibellin,</hi> and ſerveth to defend their Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, Ears, and Foreheads from colds and other Tempeſts. That which appears above the skin being covered over either with curious red ſilke, or elſe with
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:119887:23"/> black and purple horſe-hair, which they die and dreſs moſt curiouſly; ſo as their appurte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances being handſomely joy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned together, makes the capp both commodious and handſom. Their Garments are long Robes falling down to the very foot, but their ſleeves are not ſo wide and large as the <hi>Chineſes</hi> uſe; but rather ſuch as are uſed in <hi>Polony,</hi> &amp; <hi>Hungary,</hi> only with this diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence, that they faſhion the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tremity of the Sleeve, ever like a Horſe his Hoof. At their Gir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle there hangs on either ſide two Handkerchiefes to wipe their face and hands; beſides, there hangs a Knife for all ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary uſes, with two Purſes, in which they carry <hi>Tobacco,</hi> or ſuch like Commodities. On their Left ſide they hang their Scymiters, but ſo as the point goes before,
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:119887:23"/> and the handle behind, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore when they fight they draw it out with the right hand behind them without holding the Scab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bard with the other. They ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome were Shoes, and uſe no Spurrs to their Boots, which they make either of Silk, or of Horſe-skin very neatly dreſt; but they often uſe fair Pattins, which they make three Fingers high. In riding they uſe Stir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rups, but their Saddles are both lower and broader than ours; Their faces are comely, and commonly broad as thoſe of <hi>China</hi> alſo have; their colour is white, but their Noſe is not ſo flat, nor their eyes ſo little, as the <hi>Chineſes</hi> are; They ſpeak lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle, and ride penſively. In the reſt of their manners they reſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble our <hi>Tartars</hi> of <hi>Europe,</hi> though they be nothing ſo barbarous.
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:119887:24"/> They rejoice to ſee Strangers; They no way like the grimneſs and ſoureneſs of the <hi>Chines</hi> gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vity, and therefore in their firſt aboads they appear more human.</p>
            <p>Having thus briefly deſcribed their Manners, we reſume our former diſcourſe, and return to the victorious <hi>Tartars</hi> in the Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty they had takens; In which, find<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing many rich and wealthy Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants of other Provinces, they publiſhed a Licence that they might depart with their Goods, and withall commanded them ſpeedily to voyd the City; Who preſently obeying the Order, carried away all their Goods and Riches,<note place="margin">The <hi>Tar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tars</hi> perfi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diouſnes.</note> little ſuſpecting the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fideous treachery of the <hi>Tartars;</hi> For they had not gone three miles from the Town, but being ſet upon by the <hi>Tartars,</hi> they were plundred of their Goods,
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:119887:24"/> and loſt all their lives; which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing done, they returned into the fearfull City, laden with Riches, the Citizens trembling, leſt they might happily experience the like perfidiouſnes.</p>
            <p>But the <hi>Tartar</hi> conſidering at how dear a rate he had bought the maſtering of that City, and fearing alſo to find the like pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſion and preparation in other Cities, they durſt not make any further attempt; for they knew well that the Emperour had not only fortified all the antient pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, but erected alſo new muni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titions, in the ſtraights of many hard and rude paſſages.</p>
            <p>And amongſt all other ſtrong holds, that of <hi>Xanghai,</hi> ſituated in the Iſland of <hi>Cu,</hi> was moſt emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent, containing a vaſt number of men in the Garriſon, to reſiſt the further progreſſe of the <hi>Tartari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an</hi>
               <pb n="38" facs="tcp:119887:25"/> Forces. But that which moſt of all repreſſed the <hi>Tartars,</hi> was the great valour of the incompa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Commander <hi>Maovenlun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gus,</hi> who having with his great Fleet taken an Iſland neer <hi>Corea</hi> in the mouth of the River <hi>Yalo,</hi>
               <note place="margin">The vali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anteſt Comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of <hi>Chi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na.</hi>
               </note> vexed much their Army in the Rear, and was victorious in ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral Skirmiſhes againſt them; ſo that the <hi>Tartars</hi> bent all their care and thoughts againſt this their Enemy. This renowned perſon was born in the Province of <hi>Evangtung,</hi> where being near the <hi>Portugeſe</hi> of <hi>Macao,</hi> he had much perfected himſelf in the art of war, and he brought with him many great peices of Artil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lerie, which he had recovered from the Shipwrack of a <hi>Holland</hi> Ship, upon the Coaſts of that Territorie. And becauſe the Emperour of <hi>China</hi> had declared
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:119887:25"/> the City of <hi>Ninguyven</hi> to be the chief in place of <hi>Leaoyang</hi> (where alſo he had placed a new Vice-Roy, and his Royal Viſitor) therefore <hi>Maovenlungus</hi> placed the beſt part of his Artillarie up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Walls of this City.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Tartars</hi> therefore acted nothing till the year 16<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>5<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and becauſe they reſolved to beſiege the new Metropolitan City of <hi>Ninguyven,</hi> they firſt reſolved to trie <hi>Maovenlungus</hi> his fidelitie;<note place="margin">The faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulnes of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manders in <hi>China.</hi>
               </note> offering him half of the Empire of <hi>China</hi> if he would help them to gain it; But that noble Soul of his, proved as faithfull as valiant, by rejecting thoſe Demands with indignation; and came pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently with his Forces to ſuccour the City <hi>Ninguyven</hi> which they beſieged; by which means,<note place="margin">The over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throw of the <hi>Tar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tars.</hi>
               </note> the <hi>Tartars</hi> having loſt ten thouſand men, were put to the flight; and
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:119887:26"/> among the reſt, the King of <hi>Tar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary</hi>'s own Sonn was killed. Wherefore being furious with anger, they paſſed the frozen Sea, and invaded the Iſland <hi>Thaoyven,</hi> where they killed ten thouſand that kept Garriſons there, toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with all the Inhabitants; and by this one Act,<note place="margin">Their Cruelty.</note> having reven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged their former diſcomfiture, they returned into <hi>Tartary,</hi> not with a reſolution to ſit ſtill, but with an intention to return with greater Forces; By which re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraint, all things remained quiet till the year 1627. in which the Emperour <hi>Thienkius</hi> dyed in the flow'r of his age, and with him the whole Empire of <hi>China</hi> ſeemed to fall to ruin and deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction;<note place="margin">The Kings of <hi>China,</hi> and <hi>Tarta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry</hi> both di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed.</note> and in the ſame year, the King of the <hi>Tartars,</hi> who had cruelly murdered many men, himſelf augmented the number of the dead.</p>
            <pb n="41" facs="tcp:119887:26"/>
            <p>After <hi>Thinkius,</hi> in the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire of <hi>China,</hi> ſucceeded that un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happy Emperour <hi>Zungchinius,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Zungchini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nius</hi> cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour of <hi>China.</hi>
               </note> brother to the former, of whom more hereafter. And after <hi>Thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enmingus</hi> King of <hi>Tartary,</hi> ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded <hi>Thienzungus</hi> his Son,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Thienzun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gus</hi> more milde than his Prede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſors.</note> who changed the manner of his Fathers Government, and by good Counſel began to govern the <hi>Chineſes</hi> in a curteous and ſweet manner; but though he lived not long, yet he ſerved for a good example for his Sonn to Conquer <hi>China</hi> more by Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vilitie and Humanitie, than by force of Arms.</p>
            <p>In this year, great <hi>Maoven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lungus</hi> Soldiers being inſolent by want of action,<note place="margin">The Sol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers Inſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lencies ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſperat the Country of <hi>Corea.</hi>
               </note> grew very troubleſom and offenſive by their Rapines and Diſorders to the <hi>Coreans,</hi> who were friends &amp; Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies; and particularly they much
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:119887:27"/> exaſperated the Province of <hi>Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enkin,</hi> inſomuch that ſome of the Inhabitants of that place, moved with indignation of ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral paſſages, ſecretly treated with the <hi>Tartarian</hi> King to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vade the <hi>Chineſes</hi> Army, in the habit and attire of the Inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitants of <hi>Corea,</hi> from whom they could expect no Treaſon, being leaguerd with them in friendſhip and amitie: promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing moreover their beſt aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance to effect this miſchief, to him that was a Traitour both to Country, King, and the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour of <hi>China.</hi> But this Counſel pleaſed the <hi>Tartar,</hi> and therefore he ſent a Vice-Roy with a potent Army,<note place="margin">The <hi>Tar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tars</hi> are brought into <hi>Corea.</hi>
               </note> to which the <hi>Coreans</hi> ſhewed the waies, and guided them through all the paſſages; who falling upon the <hi>Chineſes</hi> Armie (which ſuſpecting no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing,
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:119887:27"/> was divided, and many ſtragling up and down the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trie) made a huge Carnage a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt them. But when <hi>Mao<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venlungus</hi> percieved they were <hi>Tartars,</hi> he preſently made head, and gathered a Body of an Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie together, and vigorouſly op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed all thoſe ſharp aſſaults. But yet at length he was forced to yield the Field; and therefore leaving a Regiment or two to hold the Enemie in action whilſt his Army retreated, he fled to his Ships, and to the Iſland which he had Fortified. The <hi>Tartars</hi> were vexed and grieved, both to ſee their victory ſo bloo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, and alſo that <hi>Maovenlungus,</hi> whom they chiefly aimed at, had eſcaped with moſt of his Army; and therefore enraged with An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, they fell upon the <hi>Corean</hi> Traitors, and killed every man;
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:119887:28"/> which action the King of <hi>Tartary</hi> much condemned; and then turn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their wrath to the four Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thern Provinces, which border upon <hi>Tartary,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Corea</hi> wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted.</note> they waſted and deſtroyed them all in a moment.</p>
            <p>In the mean time the King of <hi>Corea</hi> gathered an Army to reſiſt the <hi>Tartars;</hi> and <hi>Maovenlungus</hi> alſo, having recruited his Forces, came into <hi>Corea</hi> to revenge the received loſs. The victorious <hi>Tartars</hi> were come within ſeven Leagues of the principalleſt City of all <hi>Corea.</hi> But finding the King to have taken the Straights and Paſſages of the Mountains which lead unto it, they deſperat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly reſolved to force their paſſage. The Battel was hardly begun, but <hi>Maovenlungus,</hi> after a long march, falls in upon their rear: and the <hi>Tartars</hi> finding them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves encompaſſed before and
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:119887:28"/> behind, nor any means to eſcape but by dint of Sword, fought moſt deſperatelie, ſuſtaining the ſhock of two Armies; And ſuch a Battel was fought, as <hi>China</hi> ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſaw; for, (it is ſtrange to write, yet very true) of the three Armies, none was victorious, but all in a manner deſtroyed.<note place="margin">The Fight and ſlaugh<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter of 3 Armies.</note> Of the <hi>Tartarian</hi> Armie fifty thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand were found wanting; The <hi>Corean</hi> Armie loſt ſeventy thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand; and few or none eſcaped of the <hi>Chineſes</hi> Armie; For their Quarter being moſt commodious for the <hi>Tartars</hi> flight, they there made their moſt vigorous Char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, and ſo forced their way to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards their own Countrie. So as none of them all gained the field, or could proſecute the courſe of a Victorie. Yet the King of <hi>Corea</hi> made a ſhift to rallie ſo many to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether again, as to take poſſeſſion
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:119887:29"/> of thoſe his Countries which the <hi>Tartarians</hi> by their flight had left deſolate. But the <hi>Tartars</hi> after all the loſſes, ceaſed not to make frequent inrodes into the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try of <hi>Leaotung,</hi>
               <note place="margin">The Ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtern part of <hi>Leoa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tung</hi> is un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the <hi>Tartar.</hi>
               </note> and took all the Oriental part of it. From thence they made incurſions into the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther part, and carried away great Preys and Booties; But they were alwaies ſo beaten, and ſo defea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, as they could never fix a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant habitation. For by this time were arrived ſeven excellent Gunners from the <hi>Portugeſe</hi> quarters,<note place="margin">The <hi>Por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tugeſe</hi> ſend ſuccour.</note> which both by them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, and by teaching the <hi>Chi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſes,</hi> advanced infinitly the King of <hi>China</hi> his Affairs; eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially where that Chriſtian Vice-Roy, called <hi>Sun Ignatius,</hi> Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mander in chief, of whoſe affairs we ſhall ſay ſomthing hereafter</p>
            <p>In this conjuncture of affairs,
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:119887:29"/> the Emperour <hi>Zungchinius</hi> ſent a new Commander called <hi>Yvenus</hi> into <hi>Leaotung,</hi>
               <note place="margin">A crafty Comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of the <hi>China</hi> Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my.</note> with a new Armie and full power to conclude a Peace with the <hi>Tartars,</hi> if they would admit it: For the diſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders of the times had cauſed ſo many needy perſons, Theevs, and Cut-throats, that the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour grew more anxious how to ſuppreſs this great domeſtick E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemie, which ſeemed to aim at the Kingdoms ruin, than he was of the <hi>Tartarian</hi> Forces. This <hi>Yvenus</hi> was a crafty and ſubtill wit, moſt eloquent both in ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and writing; who by politick diſcourſes, drawn from the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of this war, had wrought ſo much, not only upon the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours mind, but alſo upon all the Councill, that they eſteemed what he concluded as a Law to be obſerved: Wherefore the
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:119887:30"/> 
               <hi>Chineſes</hi> put all their confidence in him; nor had they been fruſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted of their hopes, had not this wicked man been more wedded to his own intereſt, and love of Riches, than to the publick good, &amp; fidelitie to his Prince: For firſt he received of the <hi>Tartars</hi> a vaſt Summe of gold; which wrought ſo much upon him, as that ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving invited to a Banquet that moſt Valorous and Faithfull Champion <hi>Maovenlungus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Maoven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lungus</hi> poi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoned.</note> whom the <hi>Tartars</hi> only feared, he there poiſoned that great Comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der.</p>
            <p>After this he made a moſt ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nominious and ſhamefull Peace with the <hi>Tartars,</hi> condeſcending to all that thoſe that fed him with Riches, could deſire; But when the Emperour had peruſed the Treatie, he preſently found his Plenipotentiarian had ſold
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:119887:30"/> him, and therefore refuſed to ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifie or confirm the Articles. What ſhould <hi>Yvenus</hi> act in this exigent? That he might force the Emperour to admit them, he peſwaded the <hi>Tartars,</hi> in the year 1630. to enter <hi>China</hi> by another Country than that which was committed to his charge, promiſing them for his part, he would no way hinder their progreſſe by his Army. The <hi>Tartars</hi> knew that his ava<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rice had ſo potent an Aſcendent over him, as that they need to fear no hurt from him; and upon that Confidence admitted of his Counſell. Wherefore being ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure from all aſſaults from any Enemie behind them, they en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered the Province of <hi>Peking,</hi> and beſieged the Kings Court:<note place="margin">The Kings Court be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſieged.</note> Inſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much that his Councel perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded him to leave the Imperial
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:119887:31"/> City, and retire to the Southern Provinces; but he proteſted he would rather die, than quit the Northern quarters; and not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſo, but he forbid any to depart the Court, or Town beſieged. In the mean time the <hi>Tartars</hi> make many fierce affaults, and as often were valiantly beaten back with great loſs and Carnage. <hi>Yvenus</hi> was called to reſiſt the <hi>Tartars,</hi> for as yet his Traiterous Complots were not diſcovered. And leſt he ſhould diſcover his Treaſon, he comes with his Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie neer the very Walls, which were of ſo vaſt an extent, as both the <hi>Chineſe</hi> and <hi>Tartars</hi> Armie might perfectly be diſcerned, though betwixt them there was a great Intervall. But though <hi>Y<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venus</hi> was under the Emperours eye, yet he acted little; for his only aim was to return home la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:119887:31"/> with Riches, he never deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted to perſwade the Emperour to admit his conditions of Peace. So that the Emperour finding him evidently to be a Traitor, diſcloſing his intention to none of his Councell nor Governors, ſends to invite him to a pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vat Councel of war, giving alſo order that he ſhould be admitted into the Citie by the Walls, leſt if any Gate ſhould be open, the <hi>Tartar</hi> being ſo neer might preſs in upon them; but indeed he or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered the buſineſs in this man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, leſt he ſhould bring his Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie into the City with him. <hi>Yve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus</hi> therfore knowing he had ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny chief men about the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours perſon, who were both his favourites and friends, and that none of them gave him the leaſt ſign of any diſtaſt the Emperor might conceive againſt him, he
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:119887:32"/> boldly and ſecurely preſented himſelf at Court; and as ſoon as he appeared, he was preſently arreſted, and after ſome few queſtions, the Emperour com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded him to be kil'd.<note place="margin">The perfi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dious Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral kil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led.</note> The <hi>Tar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tars</hi> hearing of his death (before the <hi>China</hi> Armie had a new Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral aſſigned) ranſack all the Country round about, and after they had made excurſions to the next bordering Province of <hi>Xan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tung,</hi>
               <note place="margin">The <hi>Tar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tars</hi> for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage all the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try of <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king</hi> and depart.</note> richly laden with all man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of Spoiles, they returned to their firſt reſidence in <hi>Leaotung.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And from theſe times till the year 1636. the event of their Warrs was very various; but in general we obſerve, that the <hi>Tar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tars</hi> could never fix a foot in <hi>Chi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na,</hi>
               <note place="margin">The King of <hi>Tartary</hi> dies; ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeds.</note> but they were preſently bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten out again. In this ſame year <hi>Thienzungus,</hi> King of the <hi>Tar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tars</hi> died, after whom, ſucceeded
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:119887:32"/> his Son <hi>Zungteus,</hi> father to him that now governs <hi>China,</hi> of whom we now muſt begin to Treat.</p>
            <p>This Prince before his Reign expreſſed much judgement in ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verall Occurrences,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Zungteus</hi> the new King of <hi>Tartary,</hi> prudent &amp; milde.</note> ſurpaſſing all the Kings of <hi>Tartary</hi> in Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manity, and obliging curteſie: For when he was young, he was ſent by his Father into <hi>China;</hi> where he lived ſecretly, and learned the <hi>China</hi>'s Manners, Doctrine and Language; and when he came to be Emperour of <hi>China,</hi> he changed, and far ſurpaſſed all the Examples of his Predeceſſors: For having obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, that their too hard and cruel uſage of the <hi>Chineſes,</hi> had been the principal obſtacle of their ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vancement, to the end he might conquer that Empire he ſo much thirſted after, as well by love as
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:119887:33"/> by Arms, he curteouſly enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained and cheriſhed all thoſe of <hi>China</hi> which came unto him,<note place="margin">Mildeneſs and Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleneſs to be uſed in Conquer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</note> u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing all Priſoners with great ſweetnes, and invited them either to ſubmit freely to his Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, or take their courſe with full freedom. The fame of his humanity was ſpred far and neer; which induced many Commanders and chief Officers to fly unto him; by whoſe means and help, he became Emperour of that ſpacious and floriſhing Country. For experience ſhews us, that Love and Humanity doe work more upon mens hearts, in conquering and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerving Kingdomes, than Arms; and cruelty of the Conquerors hath loſt that, which ſtrength of Arms had happily ſubdued. Wherefore when the <hi>Chineſes</hi> came to underſtand that the King
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:119887:33"/> of <hi>Tartary</hi> did not only afford them a Sanctuary, but a favoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Haven, many great perſons flying the Indignation of the King of <hi>China,</hi> ſheltered them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves under the <hi>Tartars</hi> prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction. For in reſpect of the <hi>Chi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na</hi>'s Avarice and perfidiouſneſs, it's a neceſſary but a moſt inhu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Maxim,<note place="margin">A barba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple of the <hi>Chine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes.</hi>
               </note> that thoſe Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers periſh, who have managed the Kingdomes Affairs with leſs ſucceſs. For they eaſily are brought to believe, that ſuch un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happy events, do not proceed ſo much from the frown of a ſcorn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Goddeſs called Fortune, as it doth from the perfidy and negligence of the Commanders. So as if any fought unhappily, or if he loſt the Country commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to his charge, if any Sedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion or Rebellion happened, the Governors hardly ever eſcaped
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:119887:34"/> alive. Seeing therefore they found ſo much Humanity in the <hi>Tartar,</hi> and ſo much Inhumanity in the Emperor, they rather choſe to fly to the former.</p>
            <p>By this occaſion give me leave to relate what happened to that incomparable Commander (re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nouned both for Fidelity and Fortitude) called <hi>Ignatius.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ignatius</hi> the chief Comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of the Chriſtians unjuſtly killed.</note> This Heroick mind preferd his fideli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie to his Prince, before his life, before the <hi>Tartarian</hi>'s protecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, yea even before the ſtrength of his formidable Army; and choſe rather, with his unparallel'd Fidelity, to ſubmit his head to a Block by an unjuſt ſentence, than to abandon his Country, or once accuſe the leaſt default in his So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vereign's judgment,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ignatius</hi> his fidelity.</note> though pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vented, by very unjuſt impreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons: He might perchance have ſwayed the Sovereign Scepter of
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:119887:34"/> 
               <hi>China,</hi> if he would have hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kened to his Souldiers, but he rather choſe to die gloriouſly, than to be branded with the name of a Traitor in poſterity.</p>
            <p>This man therefore after he had gained ſeveral Victories a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the <hi>Tartars,</hi> and recover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed many Cities from their poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, ſo as he hoped ſhortly who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to extirpate them out of <hi>Chi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na,</hi> His Souldiers being long without pay, ſeditiouſly plun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred and pillaged a Town which had ever been faithfull to the K. <hi>Ignatius</hi> by ſeveral petitions and Remonſtrances to the Emperour, had declared his wants of mony, and their want of Pay; but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he fed not thoſe venal ſouls that managed the buſineſs with mony and preſents, they alwaies ſuppreſſed his humble addreſſes for relief. Beſides, this man be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:119887:35"/> a very pious Chriſtian, he did nothing in his government,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ignatius</hi> his Piety.</note> but what was conform to Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon and Juſtice; which was the cauſe he incurred the hatred of all the antient Prefects; who uſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally receiving Bribes from the conteſting parties, demanded fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour of <hi>Ignatius</hi> for their Cli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ents. But it was in vain to inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cede for any, unleſs the juſtneſs of the cauſe did alſo ballance their Petitions. And theſe men attributing this proceeding, not to vertue, but to his Pride, think<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing themſelves undervalued by him, dealt under-hand with the Prefects in the Court, to ſtop the Armies pay, that ſo they might deſtroy this innocent man. More<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>over, he was envied the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ders in the very Court, becauſe he came to this eminent dignitie by his own valour and induſtrie;
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:119887:35"/> which they imagined was only to be given to Doctors, and <hi>Ignati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us</hi> was but a Batchelor; as if the moſt learned muſt needs be alſo the moſt valorous. In this conjun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture of affairs, the Souldiers not contented with the ſeditious pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lage, ſeeing the moſt imminent danger hanging over their moſt eſteemed and beloved Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, by reaſon of their folly, they go about to perſwade him to make himſelf King of that Country, nay more, to take the whole Empire to himſelf, as a thing due to his Proweſs and Merits; promiſing their whole ſtrength to effect the buſineſs; and alſo to extirpate thoſe men about the Emperour, that aimed more to compaſs their malicious ends, than to promote the general affairs of the Empire: But <hi>Igna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius,</hi> by pious admonitions, ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:119887:36"/> them off from further vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence, made them obedient and quiet, commanded all to ſtand faithfull to the Emperour of <hi>Chi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na,</hi> and puniſhed the chief of that fedition.</p>
            <p>This Supreme act of fidelity deſerved a better eſteem and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptance, than that which was framed by the Emperour and his Court: who ſlighting this his allegeance, ſent another Vice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>Roy in his place, and comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded him to appear in Court: He then perceived they aimed at his life; and the Souldiers ſuſpected the buſineſs; and therefore, mad with anger, they all jointly roſe in Arms for hm, ſwearing they would live and die with him, and that he ſhould not preſent him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe at Court. <hi>It is our duty</hi> (ſay they) <hi>to conſerve thy life, which haſt been ſo carefull of ours; and
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:119887:36"/> we have ſtrength and courage e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough to reſiſt all the force of thy perfidious Enemies.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But <hi>Ignatius</hi> was deaf to al theſe allurements,<note place="margin">He chuſes rather to die, thatn either to reign, or to ſerve the <hi>Tar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tars.</hi>
               </note> and ſtudied by all means to ſweeten their exulcera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted minds; alwaies inculcating to them to the true and loyall to their Sovereigns ſervice: chuſing rather to water that ungratefull Soil of his native Country with the ſtreams of his Blood, than either to ſpill his Enemies blood by the force and pow'r of his Souldiers, or retire to the <hi>Tarta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rian</hi> king, which offered him ſo fair preferments. But many of his Captains fell off to the <hi>Tar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tars;</hi> following, in this, not his example, but that of many o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, whom they ſaw eminently promoted amongſt the <hi>Tartars.</hi> Some of thoſe that then fled from the Emperour, are now
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:119887:37"/> chief Commanders under the <hi>Tartarian</hi> King, in their <hi>Chi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na</hi> Empire; ſome alſo have ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained the dignity of Princes, or Riolets in ſeveral Countries, for the reward of their Valour and faithfull ſervice againſt <hi>China. So efficacious is that wedge which is made of the ſame wood.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But although hitherto theſe <hi>Tartarian</hi> Warrs had cauſed great troubles and tempeſts in the <hi>China</hi> Empire, yet all things now ſeemed calmed and pacified, ſo as they ſeemed ſecure from any fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther danger; for the Weſtern part of <hi>Leaotung</hi> was ſtrongly forti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied, and there was a great Army in the Iſland of <hi>Cu,</hi> and the bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering quarters, which hindered the <hi>Tartars</hi> of the Eaſtern part of the Countrie, which they po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſed, from further paſſage. But now the chiefeſt danger was
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:119887:37"/> from the Traitors and Theeves which were in the very Bowells of the Country,<note place="margin">The Theeves in <hi>China,</hi> a chief occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of its overthrow.</note> who finally de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed it; and gave it up in Prey to the <hi>Tartars.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I touched ſomthing of their Commotions before, now we muſt treat a little more largely of their proceedings, that the Reader may ſee how the <hi>Tartars</hi> came to ſubdue and conquer <hi>Chi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The firſt Combination of theſe Rovers appeared in the remote Country of <hi>Suchuen,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Severall Theeves.</note> who having pillaged divers Cities, and em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boldened by proſperous ſucceſs, ventured to beſiege the chief Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of that Country call'd <hi>Cingtu,</hi> which they had infallibly taken, if that valiant Amazon, whom I mentioned before, had not come to relieve it with her Army; but by her valour they were beaten
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:119887:38"/> off with great loſs,<note place="margin">They are defeated, but not v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed.</note> and not being wholly extinguiſhed, they retired into the mou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tains to recruit their Forces. Theſe were ſeconded by a like Race of people in the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince of <hi>Queicheu,</hi> who took oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion of riſing by reaſon of an unjuſt Sentence paſſed in a Sute betwixt two Grandees of that Country; and one of theſe great perſons being offended with the Governors. Theſe roving com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panions, firſt kill'd all the Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates which had pronounced that unjuſt Sentence; &amp; then they defeated the ViceRoy his Army; yet afterwards he routed them a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain with a new Army, but could not extinguiſh them. Beſides theſe,<note place="margin">Famin augments the Theevs</note> the Famin increaſing in the Northern quarters in the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries of <hi>Xenſi</hi> &amp; <hi>Xantung,</hi> by reaſon of a great inundation of Locuſts which devoured all, there riſe up
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:119887:38"/> by this occaſion, many looſe fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>owes which lived by Rapin. Theſe men at firſt were few in number, and ſmall in ſtrength, and only preying in little places, they preſently fled to the Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains; but finding they got both Meat and Riches, with little la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour and leſs coſt, they quickly got Companions to reinforce them; This Sedition being much augmented by the Emperour <hi>Zungchinius</hi> his notable avarice,<note place="margin">And the Emperour his avarice</note> who ſo exhauſted the people by Impoſts and Taxes, as if it had been a year of the golden Age. The Prefects of the Provinces, not being able preſently to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs the inſolency of thoſe peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, they daily increaſed in cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage and ſtrength; Inſomuch as in ſeveral Countries they had eight very conſiderable Armies. They choſe the ſtrongeſt and va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lianteſt
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:119887:39"/> men amongſt them for their Commanders; and theſe perſons being grown rich and potent by preying, depoſed now the perſon of the Ringleader of Theeves,<note place="margin">The Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manders aſpire to the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire.</note> and aſpired to no leſs than to the Empire of <hi>China.</hi> And at firſt they fought one againſt another, every one laying hold one what he could: But at length things were brought to that paſs, that two of the Commanders be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing only left alive, theſe two pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vailed with the ſouldiers of thoſe that were killed, to follow their Enſignes and Fortune; and they knowing well that if they were taken by the Emperors Officers, they could not eſcape a moſt cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain death, eaſily reſolved to ſhelter themſelves under the Arms of theſe two victorious perſons.<note place="margin">The names of the chief Felons.</note> The name of one of theſe chief Brigands was <hi>Licungzus,</hi> the
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:119887:39"/> ſecond was called <hi>Changhien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chungus,</hi> two notorious bold roguiſh fellows, who leſt they ſhould deſtroy one anothers for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunes by their ambitious emula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, they ſeparated themſelves far from one another, reſolving both to perſue their proſperous fortunes. <hi>Licungzus</hi> therefore poſſeſſed himſelf of the Northern parts of <hi>Xenſi</hi> and <hi>Honan;</hi> and the other tyranniſed the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries of <hi>Suchuen</hi> and <hi>Huquang.</hi> But that we may not interrupt our diſcourſe, by delivering the Acts of both theſe together, we will firſt treat of <hi>Licungzus</hi> his feats, being it was he was the cauſe of the <hi>Tartars</hi> coming to the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire (which he himſelf might have poſſeſſed, if his proceedings had been moderate and human) and of the other we ſhall ſpeak hereafter. Therefore in the year
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:119887:40"/> 1641. theſe pilferers having got immenſe riches in the Province <hi>Xenſi,</hi> made an irruption, in a vaſt body, into that delicious ſweet Provincs of <hi>Honan,</hi>
               <note place="margin">They vex ſeveral Provinces.</note> and went ſtrait to the chief City cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>Caifung,</hi> which they beſieg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. There was in that place a ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry great and ſtrong Gariſon, who by the benefit of artillerie moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed upon hand-wheeling Chars, forced them to quit the ſiege; then they fell upon all the neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bouring Cities, Plundring, ſpoil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and burning all they could maſter. Having horded up ſtore of proviſion of Corn, and aug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented their Army by a compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of Raſcally Vagabonds and loytering fellows,<note place="margin">They be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiege the noble Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty <hi>Caifung.</hi>
               </note> they returned again to beſiege the Metropolitan City; but deſpairing to take it by Force or aſſaults, they reſolved to ruin it by a long Siege, that
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:119887:40"/> they might enjoy the immenſe Riches of that noble City; and though this Town be three great Leagues in circumference, yet they rounded it ſo by their lines, as nothing could enter the City; this drave them to ſome ſtraits, for although the Purveyer for victualls had brought in good ſtore of proviſion in the two moneths ſpace in which they were abſent, yet becauſe that Province which uſed to be moſt plentifull, was lean in Corn, they could not make ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient proviſion for ſix moneths ſiege, for ſuch an infinite multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude of people as were retired within the Walls; Yet it held out moſt obſtinately for the ſpace of ſix moneths, in which time though they were brought to hard ſhifts, yet hoping alwaies for ſuccour from their Emperor,
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:119887:41"/> they would never ſubmit to any conditions. I dare not relate to what an exceſſe this Famin came too, but it ſeems it ſurpaſſed the Famin of <hi>Hieruſalem;</hi>
               <note place="margin">An un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heard of Famin.</note> a pound of Rice was worth a pound of Silver, &amp; a pound of any old rot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten skin was ſold at ten Crowns; dead mens fleſh was ſold publike<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in the Shambles as Hogs fleſh, and it was held an act of Piety to expoſe the dead in the Streets for others to feed on, who ſhortly were to be food for others; but I will paſs over, &amp; conceal yet more horrible things than I have rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted. This City lies towards the South ſide of that vaſt &amp; precipi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate River which the <hi>Chineſes</hi> call <hi>Hoang,</hi> becauſe the Streams al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies appear of a yellowiſh ſaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fron colour; &amp; becauſe the River is higher than the plain levell downs, of a Leagues diſtance from
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:119887:41"/> the Town, they built upon the Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſide, a long &amp; ſtrong Bulwark of great ſquare ſtones, to prevent all inundations. The Emperours Army, after long expectation, came to relieve the Town, and advanced as far as theſe Bul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warks, and having conſidered the ſituation of the Country and Enemies Camp, it was thought the fitteſt and eaſieſt way to raiſe the ſiege without giving battail, to let in the water upon the Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies Army, by ſome breaches made in that long Wall or Bul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wark. It was in <hi>Autumn</hi> when they took this reſolution, and the River, by reaſon of extraordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry rains, was ſwoln bigger than ever before; and they making the Sluces, or Inlets, too great, and the Breackes too wide, gave way to ſuch an Ocean of water as it overrun the
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:119887:42"/> Walls of the Town (which were very ſtately and high) involving not only many of the Enemies in its ruin and deſtruction,<note place="margin">The City of <hi>Caifung</hi> is drowned</note> but alſo 300000.. men, and the Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty it ſelf periſhed in thoſe floods of water. So the antient City, which heretofore had been ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nored by the Emperor's Reſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, appeared no more a place of pleaſure, but a vaſt Pool or Lake for Monſters of the waters to inhabit; for the houſes of the Town were not over-run with water, but alſo beaten down; and alſo the Church of the Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, together with their Prieſt, who was one of the Society of Jeſus; it was well known he might have ſaved himſelf, but being there were many Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans periſhed, he willingly choſe to die with thoſe he had gained. The deſtruction of this City
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:119887:42"/> happened the ninth of <hi>Oct.</hi> 1642. about which time this famous Conductor of Theeves took the name of King,<note place="margin">The Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral of the Theeves<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> takes the Title of a King.</note> with an addition of <hi>Xunvang,</hi> which ſounds as much as <hi>Proſperous,</hi> and ſo was ſtiled <hi>Licungzus the proſperous;</hi> and having in a manner taken all the Country of <hi>Honan</hi> into his Dominion, he returned into the Province of <hi>Xenſi,</hi>
               <note place="margin">He takes the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try of <hi>Xen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſi.</hi>
               </note> and wonn it wholy to his ſubjection. When he came to <hi>Sigan,</hi> which is the Metropolitan of <hi>Xenſi,</hi> he found ſome reſiſtance from the Garri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, but he took it in three daies, and for a reward and encourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to his Souldiers, he gave it to them to pillage alſo for three daies ſpace; and then he gather<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed up all the Corn of the whole Province, as well to keep all the Country in their duty to him, as alſo to leave no Forrage for the
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:119887:43"/> Emperours Army. And now thinking himſelf ſecure of the whole Empire, he took the name of Emperour upon him,<note place="margin">Calls him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour.</note> and ſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the Family wherein he thought to eſtabliſh this Dignity, <hi>Thienxunam,</hi> as much as to ſay, <hi>Obedient to Heaven;</hi> By which Title he perſwaded the Souldi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers and the People, that it was by the diſpoſall of the Heavens that he ſhould reign, that he might deliver the people from the Emperours Avarice, and extirpate thoſe wicked Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours that ſo much vexed the people, and deliver them from all their perfidious Plots. For he knew well, that this Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Title would be very accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table to them of <hi>China,</hi> who be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve that Kingdoms and Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pires come only from Heaven, and are not gained by any Art or
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:119887:43"/> Induſtry of Man; and that his actions might carry a face corre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpondent to his illuſtrious Title, he began to uſe the People with all humility and ſweetneſs,<note place="margin">The Theeves good Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment.</note> not permitting any Souldier to wrong or iujure them; only he perſecuted all the Officers call'd Preſidents, which he could find, and all thoſe he put to death; and as for thoſe that had been Preſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents, becauſe he found them rich, he made them pay great Fines, and let them live; remit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting all Taxes in the places he ſubdued; ſeverely commanding that the Subjects ſhould be trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with all Civility and Curte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie. So as all men applauding and loving ſo ſweet and milde a Government, eaſily ſubmitted to his Power and Dominion; but where the Governours uſe Tyran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, there the Subject hath little
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:119887:44"/> care of Fidelity. There were in the City two Prieſts which ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved the Chriſtians, that were Jeſuits, and ſuffered much in the ſaccage of the City; but being afterwards known for Strangers, they were uſed with all humani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty.</p>
            <p>In the mean time a third cauſe of this Empires ruin grew up in the Court;<note place="margin">The Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord was another cauſe of the ruin of <hi>China.</hi>
               </note> which was hatched in the Emperour <hi>Thienkius</hi> his time: For that Emperour exalted an Eunuch called <hi>Gueio,</hi> to ſuch a height and power, as he gave the abſolute Power and ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veraign Command into his hands, and paſſed ſo far as allway to ſtile him by the name of Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. This extravagant power cauſed much Envy, Diſsention, and the banding one againſt ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther amongſt the Governours, Preſidents, Commanders, and
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:119887:44"/> Counſellours: and the Eunuch alſo added much to incenſe the flame, by his indiſcreet uſage of the favour he poſſeſſed; for if a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny man had touched him, either in word or writing, or expreſſed leſs reſpect unto him in conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation, or behaviour, or did not flatter the baſe fellow, he would preſently give order to put him to death, though he were a very eminent perſon; or at leaſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grade him from all Office or Dignity. By which means he ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſperated many, and amongſt the reſt he offended the Prince <hi>Zunchinius,</hi> who now, by the death of his Brother without iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſue, was come to be Emperour of <hi>China.</hi> This Emperour knew that the Eunuch had moved Heaven and Earth to hinder his coming to the Crown; but ſeeing he could not effect that, at leaſt
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:119887:45"/> he maintained a ſeditious faction againſt the great ones; which finally proved the deſtruction of the Eſtate; For theſe men band<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in two factions, ſtudied more how to deſtroy one another, than to advance the publique good; yet both parties pretended the ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral good, but both neglected it; Every party endeavouring to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toll and exalt his own Creatures into places of truſt and power: All which when <hi>Zunchinius</hi> the Emperour went about to redreſſe, he exaſperated the minds of many of the Commanders againſt him; for as ſoon as he came to the Crown he cruelly perſecuted all that favoured the Eunuch, and in fine killed this very Eunuch which had been his Predeceſſors Favou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rite, together with many more of his kind; of which Tragedy I will only relate the Cataſtrophe. The
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:119887:45"/> Emperour <hi>Zungchinius</hi> reſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving to deſtroy both the Eunuch and all his power, ſent him an order to go viſit the Tombs of his Anceſtors, to conſider if any of thoſe antient Monuments wanted reparation: the Eunuch could not refuſe ſo honorable an imployment, which ſeemed ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther an addition to all his honours; but he had not gone far upon his journey, but there was preſented to him (from the Emperour) a Box of ſilver gilt, with a Halter of Silk folded up in it; by which he un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood he was to hang himſelf by the Emperors order: which he could not refuſe, being that kind of death (amongſt the <hi>Chineſes</hi>) is counted honourable, when it is accompanied with ſuch formali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties. But by this occaſion the Emperour raiſed new Factions and more Traitors, which held
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:119887:46"/> ſecret correſpondence with the Theeves Army. Hence it came to paſs, that no Army was ſent to oppoſe them, or if any went they did no manner of action, being alwaies hindered by the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mulation of others; nay it hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened often, that when they might have taken great advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tages, yet the occaſion was neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected, leſt the Commanders ſhould increaſe their Power and Credit, by their Victories, with the Emperour. Theſe Diſſenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and Emulations happened ſo ſeaſonably to the Roving Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my of Theeves, as that to <hi>come, to ſee, and conquer,</hi> was to them one and the ſelf-ſame thing, as I ſhall declare unto you.</p>
            <p>Whileſt theſe tranſactions paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed in the Court,<note place="margin">The Theevs take the Province of <hi>Xenſi.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Licungzus</hi> Conductor of the Theeves, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving ſetled all things in the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:119887:46"/> of <hi>Xenſi,</hi> paſſed to the Eaſt; and coming to the famous great River of <hi>Croceus,</hi> finding on body to defend it, he paſſed over with as much facility, as it might have been maintained with eaſe, if there had been placed but a handfull of Souldiers. For this River runns with a violent rapid courſe, and with as vaſt a Sea of waters from Weſt to Eaſt; but being there was no man to defend it, they paſſing it eaſily, preſently ſeizd upon the chief and richeſt Citie in all thoſe quarters, called <hi>Kaiangcheu,</hi> which is ſituated neer the South bankſide of that River, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing carried on with a ſtrong gale of Fortune, he ſeized upon all other Cities, every one deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring either to free themſelves from further vexation, or blindly and fondly ſubmitting them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:119887:47"/> to any new change of Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment. For we commonly delight in varieties and novelties, and hoping for better, we find worſe. Only the City of <hi>Thaiy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven</hi> made ſome reſiſtance, but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing preſently ſubdued, was fined with great vaſt ſummes of mony for their temerity. The Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour <hi>Zungchinius</hi> hearing the Theeves had paſſed the River <hi>Croceus,</hi> and were advanced to the very Confines of <hi>Xenſi</hi> (which borders upon the Province where he had placed his Throne &amp; Roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all Seat) he ſent an Army under the Lord Marſhal of <hi>China,</hi> to hold them at leaſt in play, if he could not overthrow them; But this Army did juſt nothing, nay moſt of the Souldiers ran to the Thieving party, in ſo much as the Lord Marſhal himſelf, cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>Colaus Lius,</hi> ſeeing Affairs
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:119887:47"/> grew ſo deſperate, Hang'd him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf for fear of further ſhame and diſhonour.<note place="margin">The Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour of <hi>China</hi> is troubled.</note> The Emperour hearing of the ill ſucceſs of his Affairs, began to think of lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving the Northern parts, where his Royal City of <hi>Peking</hi> is ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuated, and to paſs to <hi>Nankuing</hi> which is far more Southward; but he was diſſwaded from this intended courſe as well by his loyal, as diſloyal Subjects: by theſe, that they might give him up more ſpeedily into the ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies hands, before their trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chery was diſcovered; and by the others, leſt his flight might trouble the Kingdom more, and diſcourage all his Subjects from giving their beſt aſſiſtance; for they thought the City impreg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable, being fortified with ſo ſtrong a Garriſon; nor did they doubt that the Kings preſence
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:119887:48"/> would draw the forces of the whole Kingdom to him. And their Counſel had been good, if the Court had been purged of Traytors.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The Stra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tagem of the Theef.</note>In the mean time the Theeves Conductor, who was no leſs quick and nimble in execution, than witty in invention, ſowing a Fox his tayl to the Lions skin, cauſed many of his Souldiers in a diſguiſed habit to creep into that Princely City, and gave them mony to trade in trifling ware, till he aſſaulted the Wals with the body of his Army, for then they had order to raiſe ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, and tumult in the City; and conſidering they were a Company of deſperate Fellons, &amp; of a very low &amp; baſe fortune, it is ſtupendious to think how they could keep ſo profound ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crecy in a matter of ſo high con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cernment:
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:119887:48"/> But to this mine, which was prepared in the bow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>els of the City, he held a ſecret train of Intelligence, with the Lieutenant of the City, who ſeeing the Emperours Affairs deſperate, is ſaid to have dealt with the Conductor of theſe Bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gants about giving up the City unto their power; But, however it was, theſe Pilferers came in a ſhort time to beſiege the Royal City of <hi>Peking.</hi> There was in that City a vaſt Garriſon, and as great a quantity of Artillery; but on the Quarters upon which the enemy made there aſſault, there was none charged with Bullets, but only with Powder.</p>
            <p>Wherefore being ſecure from any annoy from that ſide,<note place="margin">The Roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al City of <hi>Peking</hi> is taken.</note> in the year MDCXLIV. before the riſing of the Sun, they entred the Metropolitan City of all
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:119887:49"/> 
               <hi>China</hi> by one of the Gates which was opened to them; nor was there any long reſiſtance made, even by thoſe that were faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful to their Prince; for the Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers of the Theef, which lay lurking in the City, made ſuch a tumult and confuſion, as none knew whom to oppoſe, in which reſpect they made a great ſlaugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, ſo as <hi>Licungzus</hi> in this Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bylonian confuſion, marched victorious through the City, till he came to the very Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours Pallace, where though he found ſome reſiſtance from the faithfulleſt Eunuchs, yet not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding he preſently entred that famous and renowned Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lace; And that which exceeds all admiration, the enemy had paſſed the firſt Wall, and Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cinct, and yet the Emperour be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing alive, knew nothing of ſo
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:119887:49"/> ſtrange a paſſage; for the Trai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terous Eunuchs, which were of moſt Authority, fearing he might eſcape by flight, deferd to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moniſh him of his own danger, or of the taking of the City, till they ſaw he could not poſſibly evade: Who hearing this dole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful news, he firſt demanded if he could get away by any means; but when he heard that all paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſages were be ſet, he is ſaid to have left a Letter writ with his own Blood, in which he bitterly expreſſed to all poſterity,<note place="margin">The Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving kild his Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter hanged himſelf.</note> the infidelity and perfidiouſneſs of his Commanders, and the inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cency of his poor Subjects; conjuring <hi>Licungzus,</hi> that ſeeing the Heavens had caſt the Scep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter into his hands, he would, for his ſake, take revenge of ſuch per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidious Creatures. After this reflecting he had a Daughter
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:119887:50"/> Marriageable, who falling into the villains hands might receive ſome affronts, he called for a Sword, and beheaded her with his own hands in the place; then going down into an Orchard, making a Rope of his Garter, he hung himſelf upon a Prune tree. Thus that unfortunate Emperour put a period, as well to that Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire, which had flouriſhed ſo long with much ſplendor, ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, and pleaſure, as to his Il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luſtrious Family of <hi>Taimingus,</hi> by finiſhing his life upon ſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temptible a Tree, and in ſuch an infamous manner: To all which circumſtances, I adde one more, that as the Empire was erected by a Theef, ſo it was extingui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed by another; for although, others were choſen to ſucceed him, as we ſhall relate hereafter, yet becauſe they held a ſmall
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:119887:50"/> parcel of the Empire, they are not numbred amongſt the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perours. His example was fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed by the Queen, and by the Lord Marſhall, who is call'd in their language <hi>Colaus,</hi> together with other faithfull Eunuchs; So as thoſe pleaſant Trees which ſerved heretofore for their Sports and pleaſures, now be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came the horrid and ſureſt In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruments of their death. And this cruell butchering of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves paſſed not only in the Court, but alſo in the City, where many made themſelves away either by hanging, or drowning by leaping into Lakes; For it is held by this Nation to be the higheſt point of fidelity to die with their Prince, rather than to live and be ſubject to another.</p>
            <p>Whileſt theſe things were
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:119887:51"/> acting, <hi>Licungzus</hi> enters the Pallace victorious, and aſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding up to the Chair of State, ſate himſelf down in that Impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rial Throne; but it is recorded, that in executing this firſt Act of Royalty, he ſat ſo reſtleſly and unquietly, yea ſo tottering<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, as if even then that Royal Chair would foretel the ſhort durance of his felicity.<note place="margin">The Theefs Tyranny and cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elty.</note> The next day after, he commanded the body of the dead Emperour to be cut into ſmall pieces, accuſing him of oppreſſion and cruelty a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt his Subjects; As if he, being a villanous Traitour, and a Theef, after the ſaccaging and burning ſo many Provinces, and ſhedding ſuch an Ocean of blood, had been of a better diſpoſition. So we often condemn others, when we do worſe our ſelves, and remark, yea, augment, the
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:119887:51"/> leaſt faults of others, when we either take no notice, or diminiſh our own. This Emperour <hi>Zung<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chinius</hi> was Father of three Sons, of which the eldeſt could never be found, though all imagina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble means was uſed for his diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covery; ſome think he found means to fly away; others think he periſhed by leaping with o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers into the Lake; the two o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers being yet little Children, were by the Tyrants command beheaded three days after; his barbarous humour not ſparing even innocent blood: Which diſpoſition he made ſhortly ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear, when caſting of that veil of Piety and Humanity, with which he had for ſome time char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med the people, he commanded all the Principal Magiſtrates to be apprehended, of which he murdered many with cruel tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments,
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:119887:52"/> others he fined deeply, and reſerved the Imperial Palace for his own aboad. He filled that moſt noble and rich City with ranſacking Souldiers, and gave it up to their prey and plunder; where they committed ſuch exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crable things, as are both too long, and not fit to be related. But by this his horrid cruelty, and Tyranny, he loſt that Empire which he might have preſerved by curteſie and humanity.</p>
            <p>Amongſt the other impriſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Magiſtrates, there was one a venerable perſon called <hi>Us,</hi> whoſe Son <hi>Uſangueius</hi> governed the whole Army of <hi>China,</hi> in the Confines of <hi>Leaotung,</hi> againſt the <hi>Tartars.</hi> The Tyrant <hi>Licungzus</hi> threatned this old man with a moſt cruell death, if by his pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal power over his Son, he did not reduce him with his
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:119887:52"/> whole Army, to ſubjection and obedience to his power, promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing alſo great Rewards and Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours to them both, if by his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therly power (which they hold ſacred) he did prevail for his ſubmiſſion. Wherefore the poor old man writ to his Son this en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuing Letter.</p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <p>It is well known that the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vens, Earth, and Fate can cauſe theſe ſtrange viciſſitudes of For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune which we behold; know my Son, that the Emperour <hi>Zunchi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nius</hi> and the whole family of <hi>Tai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mingus</hi> are periſhed. The Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vens have caſt it upon <hi>Licungzus;</hi> we muſt obſerve the times, and by making a vertue of neceſsity, avoid his Tyranny, and experience his li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berality; he promiſeth to thee a Royal dignity if with thy Army thou ſubmit to his Dominion, and acknowledge him as Emperour:
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:119887:53"/> my life depends upon thy anſwer; conſider what thou oweſt to him that gave thy life.</p>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>To this Letter his Son <hi>Uſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gueius</hi> returned this ſhort anſwer.
<floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <p>He that is not faithfull to his So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vereign, will never be faithfull to me: and if you forget your duty and fidelity to our Emperour, no man will blame me if I forget my duty and obedience to ſuch a fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. I will rather dye than ſerve a Theef.</p>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </p>
            <p>And preſently after the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patch of this Letter, he ſent an Embaſſador to the King of <hi>Tar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary,</hi>
               <note place="margin">The <hi>Tar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tars</hi> called into <hi>China</hi> againſt the Theeves.</note> deſiring his help and force to ſubdue this Uſurper of the Empire; and knowing that the <hi>Tartars</hi> abound in men, but want women, he promiſed to ſend him ſome ſtore; and preſented him with ſeveral curious Silks, and ſent him great ſtore of Sil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:119887:53"/> and Gold. The <hi>Tartarian</hi> King neglected not this good oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion, but preſently marched with foureſcore thouſand men, which were in Garriſon in <hi>Leao<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tung,</hi> to meet General <hi>Uſangueius,</hi> to whom he expreſſed himſelf in theſe words. <hi>To the end to make our Victory undoubted, I counſell you to cauſe all your Army to be clad like</hi> Tartars, <hi>for ſo the Theef will think us all</hi> Tartars, <hi>ſeeing I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not call greater Forces out of my Kingdom ſo ſoon as is required.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Uſangueius,</hi> thirſting nothing but revenge, admitted all con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions, little thinking (as the <hi>Chineſes</hi> ſay) that he brought in <hi>Tygers</hi> to drive out Dogs. <hi>Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cungzus</hi> hearing the march of the Tartars together with <hi>Uſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gueius,</hi>
               <note place="margin">The Theeves fly from the <hi>Tar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tars.</hi>
               </note> knowing himſelf not able to reſiſt, quitted the Court and Palace as eaſily as he had taken
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:119887:54"/> it: but he carried with him all the rich ſpoyls of the Court, and marched away into the Province of <hi>Xenſi,</hi> where he eſtabliſhed his Court in the noble City of <hi>Singan,</hi> which heretofore had been the ſeat of the Emperours. It is accounted that for eight days ſpace by the four Palace Gates, there was nothing ſeen but a continual ſucceſſion of Coa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches,<note place="margin">They car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry away the Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures of the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lace.</note> Horſes, Camels, and Por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters carrying away the pretiouſeſt treaſures, though they left alſo much, becauſe the enemy ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proached. Thus the immenſe Riches of Gold and Silver, which the Emperours of the <hi>Taminge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an</hi> Family had at leaſure hoorded up, in the ſpace of two hundred and fourſcore years, were in a moment diſperſed. But although they fled very ſpeedily, yet they could not avoid the ſwift Tar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarian
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:119887:54"/> Horſes, for overtaking their Luggage, and the Rear of the Army, they Pillaged and vexed them for eight days; but yet they either could not, or would not paſs the River <hi>Croceus,</hi> that ſo they might ſpeedily return to amuſe the trembling hearts of the Territory of <hi>Peking.</hi> The <hi>Tartars</hi> return therefore victorious and rich into the Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty <hi>Peking,</hi> and there being admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by the <hi>Chineſes,</hi> they gave them the Empire. VVhere it is to be obſerved, that although <hi>Zung<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teus,</hi> the <hi>Tartarian</hi> King,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Zungteus</hi> King of the <hi>Tar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tars</hi> dyes.</note> dying at the firſt entrance into <hi>China,</hi> did not obtain that noble Empire he ſo much thirſted after; yet he gave thoſe Inſtructions, of the manner of conquering it, to his Councel, that they never deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted till they obtained it. This Prince dying, declared his Son
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:119887:55"/> of ſix years old, his Succeſſor; commanding all his own Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren to manage the Childs Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs with all fidelity and circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpection, making his eldeſt bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther his Tutor; and all thoſe bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, being Uncles to the Child, by a ſtupendious Union, and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver to be parallel'd in any ambi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious Nation, exalted this Infant to the poſſeſſion of the Empire.</p>
            <p>Theſe things being thus paſſed, <hi>Uſangueius,</hi>
               <note place="margin">The <hi>Tar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tars</hi> refuſe to depart <hi>China.</hi>
               </note> ſeeing the Thief ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pelled, began to think of creating a new Emperour, one of the <hi>Tai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minga</hi>'s Family, who was a Prince not far diſtant: But being mindful of his promiſes made to the <hi>Tar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tars</hi> he offers them their rewards; he highly extols their Fortitude and Fidelity in the Kingdomes quarrel; and finally, deſires them now to depart the Countrey qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>etly, and to entertain a ſtrict alli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:119887:55"/> and friendſhip with them, ſeing they had abundantly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venged all former injuries. To this demand the <hi>Tartars</hi> returned a long premeditated anſwer, but far contrary to what <hi>Uſangueius</hi> expected, which they delivered in theſe tearms.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>We do not think it yet a fit time to leave you &amp; this Empire, unleſs ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving heard our Reaſons, you ſhould ſtill perſiſt in your demand; for we conſider, that many of the Theeves are ſtill extant, and ſeem rather diſperſed than extinguiſhed; and we hear that their great Conductor</hi> Licungzus, <hi>hath fixed his Impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rial Seat in</hi> Sigan, <hi>the Metro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>politan of the Province of</hi> Xenſi; <hi>by which means he ſtill poſſeſſeth the richeſt and moſt populous Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinces, which are ſtil under his Dominion. If we depart, worſe is to be feared will follow; He feared
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:119887:56"/> us</hi> Tartars, <hi>when he hears we are gone, having now time to recruit his Forces, he will doubtleſs make new Invaſions, and perchance we ſhall not be able to ſend new Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cors: We therefore reſolve to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecute the Victory, and quite ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinguiſh thoſe Vagabonds, that ſo you may deliver the Empire to your deſigned King, in full peace and tranquillity. Be not ſolicitous of paying our promiſed Rewards, for they are as ſafe in yours as in our own hands.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Their Craft and Deceit.</note> 
               <hi>That which we now deſire to execute, is, that which preſſeth moſt, and ſeems to us to require no delay, that you, with part of your Army and part of ours, march ſpeedily againſt</hi> Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cungzus, <hi>and we with the reſt, take our march towards the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince of</hi> Xantung, <hi>to extirpate thoſe Theeves that have ſetled there; By this means the peace of
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:119887:56"/> the Kingdome will be firmly eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Uſanguieus</hi> either did not un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand the Stratagem, or if he did, he condeſcended not to ir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritate an Army in the Bowells of the Kingdome.</p>
            <p>Before the <hi>Tartars</hi> (which were called) entred <hi>China,</hi> they ſent into their own and other Kingdomes to raiſe as many men as poſſibly they could, to the end they might conquer the Empire after they had acquitted them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves of their promiſed aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance againſt the Theeves. But theſe Succours, not being arrived to reinforce them, therefore they thought it beſt to uſe no force, but gain time by fair words and new projects.<note place="margin">A great company of <hi>Tartars</hi> enter <hi>Chi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na.</hi>
               </note> But whilſt this buſineſs was contriving, there came an immenſe company of <hi>Tartars</hi> into the Empire; not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly from the Kingdomes of <hi>Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uche,</hi>
               <pb n="102" facs="tcp:119887:57"/> and <hi>Niulham,</hi> but alſo from the old Occidental <hi>Tartary,</hi> and from a Countrey called <hi>Yupi,</hi> which is more Oriental, and lyes above the elevation of <hi>Japony.</hi> This people is called <hi>Yupi</hi> by reaſon they make their Coats of defence, or Breaſt plates, of fiſhes skin, which grow in a manner impregnable. Nay which is more, I ſaw very many who were come as far as the River <hi>Volga;</hi> which people theſe <hi>Tar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tars</hi> call <hi>Alga-Tartars,</hi> and I find they have a Notion of <hi>Muſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covy,</hi> and <hi>Polony,</hi> but they are far more barbarous than the Ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ental <hi>Tartars</hi> be; with theſe aux<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iliary Forces, came in the infant King of ſix years old, Son to the late deceaſed King of <hi>Tartary,</hi> and when theſe were joyned with the body of the Army,<note place="margin">The <hi>Tar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tars</hi> ceiſe upon the Empire of <hi>China.</hi>
               </note> then they publikely proclamed their right to the Empire, and openly
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:119887:57"/> declared their concealed intenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; and proclamed this child of ſix years old, Emperour of <hi>Chi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na,</hi> by the name of <hi>Xunchi,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Xunchi</hi> is crowned the firſt Emperour of the <hi>Tar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tars.</hi>
               </note> and the new erected Imperial Family they ſtiled by the name of <hi>Tai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing.</hi> The Child of ſix years old took poſſeſſion of the anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent Throne of his Forefathers, with a great gravity and Majeſty, from whence he delivered this judicious Speech to the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manders and to his Army.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>It is your ſtrength and pow'r more than my felicity (my dear and ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerous Uncles, &amp; you the reſt of my noble Commanders) which ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ports my weakneſs, and makes me ſo undantedly aſcend and poſſeſs this Imperial Throne. This my Conſtancy, and this Chairs ſtabili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, I hope, is as happy a ſign of my future proſperity, as its tottering proved unfortunate to the Thief</hi> Licungzus <hi>his Tyrannie. You ſee
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:119887:58"/> my firſt ſtep to the Empire; but I know your valour to be ſuch, that I look not only upon the Kingdome of</hi> China <hi>as my own, but conceive the Empire of the World not only by me poſſeſſed, but alſo eſtabliſhed. The rewards due to ſuch incom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parable Vetues, ſhall be no other than the riches of the Empire, and Royal dignities; proceed there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore valiantly and ſtoutly.</hi> The whole Court was aſtoniſhed to hear a Child of ſix years old ſpeak ſo much ſenſe, and hence they concluded that fate or Heaven had elected him for King; But yet, the young Prince did aſſume his eldeſt Uncle, as his Tutor and Father, the ſame day he was admitted to the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire: and therefore the <hi>Tartars</hi> in their language, called him <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mahan,</hi> as much as to ſay, the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther King; which very thing,
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:119887:58"/> the <hi>China</hi>'s expreſs by the word <hi>Amavang.</hi>
               <note place="margin">The fide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity of the Kings Tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor called <hi>Amavan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gus.</hi>
               </note> To this man there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he remitted all the Conduct of his Wars, and to him it is, the <hi>Tartars</hi> owe all their great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and Dominion: for as he excelled in Counſel and pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, ſo alſo he was as eminent in fortitude and fidelity; and withall by the ſtrength and force of his reaſons and Counſels did raviſh the wiſeſt men amongſt the <hi>Chineſes,</hi> and his Juſtice and humanity did wholy enthrall and enchant the popularity. To all which I adde thoſe fugitive Magiſtrates, who, as I related heretofore, had fled too the <hi>Tar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tars</hi> to avoid the Emperours indignation, did not a little pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mote their cauſe; for theſe men, ſometimes by word and exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, did ſeduce the hearts of the Subjects, and ſometimes ſugge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:119887:59"/> dangerous, but political Counſels to the <hi>Tartars,</hi> againſt their own Country; but by both theſe means advanced them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to high and eminent dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nities amongſt the <hi>Tartars.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The ſame day ſome Bands of Souldiers were diſpatched, with order to proclame <hi>Uſangueius</hi> a Tributary King to this new en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtalled Emperour, which they performed with great magnifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cence, adding to his name (as u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſually they do) the Sirname of <hi>Pingſi,</hi> which ſounds as much as <hi>Pacifier of the Weſtern world:</hi> in which quarters they eſtabliſhed his Kingdom in the Capital Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty in the Province of <hi>Xenſi.</hi> This Prince conſidering that he could expect no more honoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Dignity from the lawful Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſour to the Empire of <hi>China,</hi> and that the <hi>Tartars</hi> were come
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:119887:59"/> into the Empire, in ſo vaſt a num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, that he could never hope to Conquer them, found means to diſpence with his hitherto uncor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted fidelity, admitting the dignity, and ſubmitting to the Emperour; and ſo he that had hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to waged VVar for <hi>China</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Theeves,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Uſangueius</hi> forced to ſerve the <hi>Tartars.</hi>
               </note> now was forced to march againſt <hi>China</hi> to ſubdue its Provinces to the <hi>Tartarian</hi> Empire. And as he was a Great Commander, ſo alſo by the help of the <hi>Tar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tars</hi> he quickly drove out the Theeves from his little King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of <hi>Xenſi,</hi> where to this day he reigneth in the Metropolitan City of <hi>Sigan.</hi> But by theſe ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours the <hi>Tartars</hi> removed him from the practice of Arms, who remaining Armed, might have proved a dangerous enemy.</p>
            <p>It was hitherto never known
<pb n="198" facs="tcp:119887:60"/> what became of <hi>Licunzus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">It is not known what be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ame of <hi>Licungzus.</hi>
               </note> ſome think he was killed by <hi>Uſanguei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us</hi> in the fight, though he never appeared more, neither dead; nor alive, after this fight, in which all his forces were diſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pated, or cut off. And with the ſame facility the <hi>Tartars</hi> ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dued the Provinces of <hi>Peking</hi> and <hi>Xantung,</hi> where they im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menſly augmented their Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, by the acceſs of the <hi>China</hi>'s Souldiers and Commanders which ſubmitted to them; for the <hi>Tartarians</hi> admitted all, even the Conquered, to their Army if they did cut their Hair, and wear their habits, after the <hi>Tar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarian</hi> faſhion: for in this Pun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tillio of Habit and Hair they were ſo rigorous, as they pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clamed it high Treaſon in all that did forbear it. VVhich Law, did many times endanger
<pb n="601" facs="tcp:119887:60"/> them, and diſturb the whole frame of their Affairs: For the <hi>Chineſes</hi> both grieved, and fought more valiantly for their Hair and Habit, than for their Kingdom and Emperour; So as many times they choſe rather to dye, or loſe there heads, than obey the <hi>Tartars</hi> in theſe Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies; of which I could relate many examples, unleſs in this relation I had reſolved to be brief. But all theſe little rubs, did not hinder, but that in leſs than the ſpace of a year,<note place="margin">The <hi>Tar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tars</hi> ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>due ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinces.</note> (not coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting <hi>Leaotung</hi>) they had con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quered <hi>Peking, Xanſi, Xenſi,</hi> and <hi>Xantung,</hi> which are the four vaſt Northern Provinces of <hi>China.</hi> In all which they chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged nothing in their Political manner of Government; nay, they permitted the uſual cuſtom of the Philoſophers of <hi>China</hi>
               <pb n="110" facs="tcp:119887:61"/> to govern the Towns and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinces; they left alſo the ſame Examens as were uſed for the approving of learned men; for by this prudent Counſel they wrought this effect, that having given the places of honour and truſt to men of their own Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,<note place="margin">They changed no Laws of the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</note> they found they ſurpaſſed the very <hi>Tartars</hi> in fidelity to them; yet they kept the <hi>Militia</hi> in their own hands, and the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering therof, &amp; yet they ſtick'd not to admit even to theſe Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, ſuch of the Country as were faithful to them; ſo as in the Royal City they retained ſtill the ſame Orders and degrees of Prefects, together with the ſix high Tribunals, as they were eſtabliſhed in the former Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perours time: but ſo, as they were now compounded of <hi>Chi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſes</hi> and <hi>Tartars.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="111" facs="tcp:119887:61"/>
            <p>In the mean time the news of the Emperours danger came to the Southern parts of <hi>China,</hi> and the Prefects of every City gathering together very great forces marched towards the Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of <hi>Peking;</hi> but in their march they received the ſad news of the Emperours death, and the taking of <hi>Peking,</hi> they therefore ſpeedily called back their For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and alſo all their Ships, which yearly uſed to carry Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſions to the Emperours Courts; a little after this, they received the news how the <hi>Tartar</hi> was inveſted in the Kingdom and proclamed Emperour. I was then my ſelf in the great City <hi>Nanquin,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Hung<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quangus</hi> Crowned Emperour in <hi>Han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quin.</hi>
               </note> where I beheld a ſtrange conſternation in the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſion in all things; till at length having recollected themſelves, the Prefects reſolved to chooſe
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:119887:62"/> an Emperour of the Family of the <hi>Taiminges</hi> whom they cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>Hungquangus.</hi> This man came flying from the Theeves of the Province of <hi>Honan,</hi> and being he was Nephew to that famous Emperour <hi>Vanley,</hi> and Coſen Germain to <hi>Zungchinius</hi> the laſt deceaſed Emperour, they Crowned him with great pomp and oſtentation, hoping for bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter fortune under his Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. As ſoon as this Prince was choſen he ſent an Embaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage to the <hi>Tartars,</hi> begging Peace, rather than demanding it; for he offered them all the Northern Provinces which they had taken, if they would joyn in amity with him. But the <hi>Tartars</hi> well underſtood the Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licy of theſe Prefects and Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſellours; which was only to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muſe them with a Peace, whilſt
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:119887:62"/> they could reſume their ſtrength and force;<note place="margin">The <hi>Tar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tars</hi> admit no Peac<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> And therefore the returned anſwer, that they would not receive as a gift, that which they had conquered by force of Arms; but ſeeing they had cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen a new Emperour, they migh do well to defend him; but as for them, they were reſolved to have all or nothing.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Xunchini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as</hi> his Son appears at <hi>Nankuing.</hi>
               </note> This Legacy comming to nothing, whilſt both parties prepare to take the Field, appears at <hi>Nankuing</hi> a young man, who gave himſelf out to be the eldeſt Son to the late deceaſed Emperour <hi>Zun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chinius;</hi> and he gave no ſmall evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dences of this truth and Clame; nay, he was acknowledged by many of the Eunuchs. But the new elected Emperour <hi>Hunquan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gus,</hi> being ſtrongly touched by the ambition of reigning, would never acknowledge him, nor
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:119887:63"/> admit him; but commanded him to be impriſoned, and killed as an Impoſtor, though many of the Prefects enraged to hear of this order, hindered the exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution of the ſentence.<note place="margin">He cauſes troubles in <hi>China.</hi>
               </note> But by this accident, things grew into a ſedition, and the diſpute was ſo high, that it gave occaſion to the <hi>Tartars</hi> to take to the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince and City of <hi>Nankuing;</hi> ſome of the Prefects winking at it, if not enticing them under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hand to this exploit. The <hi>Tar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tars,</hi> vigilant to lay hold of all advantages, hearing of theſe e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mulations and diviſions, preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly march out into the Territory of the City of <hi>Hoaigan,</hi> and comming to the Eaſt ſide of the River <hi>Croceus,</hi> they paſs over ſpeedily by the help of their Boats; on the other ſide of this River ſtood the Army of <hi>Chi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na,</hi>
               <pb n="115" facs="tcp:119887:63"/> which was ſo numerous, as if they had but caſt off their ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſhoos; they had erected ſuch a Rampart againſt the <hi>Tartars,</hi> as all the Horſe would hardly have ſurmounted it. But it is the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution and valour in War, carries the Trophies, not the number of men: for hardly had the <hi>Tartars</hi> ſet foot in their Boats, but the <hi>Chineſes</hi> ran all away, as Sheep uſe to do when they ſee the Wolf,<note place="margin">The flight of the <hi>Che<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſes.</hi>
               </note> leaving the whole ſhore unfenced to their landing. The <hi>Tartars</hi> having paſſed the River, finding no enemy to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt, enter the moſt noble City of <hi>Nankuing,</hi> and in a trice make themſelves Maſter of all the North part of the Country, which lyes upon the great River of <hi>Kiang,</hi> which is ſo vaſt, as it is worthily called the Son of the Sea; where it deſerves particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:119887:64"/> to be noted as a rare thing in the Warfare of the <hi>Tartars,</hi> that before they enter into any Country, they chuſe and name both the Governours, and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panies, with all the Officers ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary for all the Cities and pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces which they aym to take; ſo as in a moment they run like a lightning, and no ſooner they poſſeſs it but it is fortified, ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, and defended. There was one City in theſe Quarters which made a generous reſiſtance to all their re-iterated aſſaults, called <hi>Yangcheu,</hi>
               <note place="margin">The City <hi>Yangcheu</hi> reſiſting the <hi>Tartar</hi> is taken and burnt.</note> where the <hi>Tartars</hi> loſt the Son of a little Royalet. This City was defended by that faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Imperial Champion called <hi>Zuuis Colaus,</hi> but though he had a mighty Garriſon, yet he was at length forced to yield, and the whole City was ſacked, and both Citizen and Souldier put
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:119887:64"/> to the Sword; and leaſt the multitude of the dead Carca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, ſhould corrupt the Air, and ingender the Plague, they laid them all upon the tops of the Horſes, and ſetting fire both to the City and Suburbs brought all to aſhes, and to a total deſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation.</p>
            <p>By this progreſs the Forces of the <hi>Tartars</hi> much entreaſed,<note place="margin">The <hi>Tar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tars</hi> take ſeveral places.</note> for the Governours of many places, and ſeveral Regiments came to ſubmit to his Dominion. To all which he commonly continued the ſame Commands and Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces they were eſtabliſhed in be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, and advanced many of them to higher dignity; and ſo by this humanity with which he trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted all that came flying to him, and by the cruelty he uſed to thoſe that reſolved to make re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtance to the Force of his
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:119887:65"/> Arms, he gained this, that moſt men reſolved to partake of his ſweet treaty, rather than of his cruelty; ſo he eaſily conque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red all that which lyes on the North ſide of that River, which I named before the Son of the Sea. This River being a <hi>Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi> Leage in breadth, and ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing from the Weſt of <hi>China,</hi> holds its courſe to the Eaſt, and divides the Kingdom into Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thern and Southern Quarters; it alſo divides the Country of <hi>Nankuing</hi> in the very middle; though <hi>Nankuing</hi> the Metropo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litan and Royal City be placed in the Southern part. To Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter this great City, they were to paſs this River. They ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered therefore together many Ships, to Conquer this new Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perial ſeat, and alſo the new ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led Emperour. The Fleet of
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:119887:65"/> 
               <hi>China</hi> commanded by the moſt generous and faithful Admiral called <hi>Hoangchoangus,</hi> lay to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the other ſide of this Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver. Here the Admiral fought ſo gallantly and reſolutely that he skowred all <hi>China,</hi> and made it appear to the world that the <hi>Tartars</hi> were not invincible; Till at length one of his own Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manders called <hi>Thienus</hi> born in the City of <hi>Leaotung,</hi> being corrupted by the <hi>Tartars,</hi> ſhot him with an Arrow to death: which Arrow fixed the uncon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant wheel of <hi>Chinas</hi> fortune, and loſt the whole Empire. But the Traytor, not contented with this perfidious Act, began him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf to run away, and by his example draw all the reſt to imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate this Ignominious Action. His impudence paſſed yet to a higher ſtrain, for comming to
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:119887:66"/> the Imperial City, and finding the Emperour preparing to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tire, he joyned himſelf with him, as a faithful friend participating of his adverſity; till he heard the <hi>Tartars</hi> (who paſſing the River followed the Kings flight with all imaginable diligence) were come near him,<note place="margin">The Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour <hi>Hunquan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gus</hi> is ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken and killed.</note> and then he took the Emperour Priſoner, and deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered him to the <hi>Tartarian</hi> army in the year MDCXLIV. This unfortunate Prince being thus betrayed before he had reigned full one year, was ſent to <hi>Peuking,</hi> and there upon the Town Walls was hanged publickly in a Bow ſtring, which kind of death the <hi>Tartars</hi> eſteem moſt noble. The pretended Son to the Emperour <hi>Zunchinius,</hi> whether he were true or falſe, run the ſame courſe of fortune, when they had diſcovered him ſtill a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>live
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:119887:66"/> Priſon: for they did not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly put to death all thoſe which belonged to the Imperial Family of the <hi>Taiminges</hi> by Conſangui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, but after a diligent ſearch extirpated all they could find, which belonged to them even by Affinity; for it is a cuſtom in <hi>Aſia,</hi> if any one Conquer a Kingdom, to root out all belong to the Royal Family.</p>
            <p>After this they divided their Army into two parts; the one they ſent to Conquer the Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terranean Provinces of <hi>Kianſi, Huquang,</hi> and <hi>Quangtung,</hi> which are all of a marvellous extent; the other like a ſwift Torrent over-run all,<note place="margin">The <hi>Tar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tars</hi> run to the City <hi>Hangcheu.</hi>
               </note> till they came to the very VVals of the renowned and vaſt City of <hi>Hangcheu,</hi> which is the head City of the Province of <hi>Chekiang.</hi> Into this City the principal fugitives of the Army
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:119887:67"/> of <hi>China</hi> were retired; and thoſe not only of the common Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dier but many great Comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, and Prefects, where they reſolved to chooſe a new Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour called <hi>Lovangus,</hi> of the antient Family of <hi>Taimingus.</hi> But this Prince would never aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume the Title of Emperour, but contented himſelf with the Title of King; thinking his fall would be leſs, and his death not ſo bitter, as if he fell from the Throne of an Emperour: but yet to the end to animate them to fight with more vigour than they had done heretofore, he promiſed them to take that title when they had regained one Emperial City. He had not reig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned three days (a ſhorter ſpace than their perſonated Kings uſe many times to reign in their Tragedies) but the <hi>Tartars</hi> ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rive;
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:119887:67"/> Which the fugitive Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers ſeeing, and thinking by this pinch of neceſſity to force their pay from the King and City, refuſed to fight before they had received their ſalary: It was on this occaſion that King <hi>Lovan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gus</hi> his heart, not able to bear ſuch a deſolation of the Citie, of his people and Subjects, as he foreſaw,<note place="margin">King <hi>Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving as</hi> love to his Subjects.</note> gave ſuch an exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of his Humanity and Piety, as <hi>Europ</hi> never ſaw; for he mounted upon the City Walls, and calling upon his Knees to the <hi>Tartarian</hi> Captains, he beg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged the life of his Subjects. <hi>Spare not me</hi> (quoth he) <hi>I will willing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly be my Subjects victime,</hi> and having denounced this unto them, he preſently went out to the <hi>Tartars</hi> Army, where he was taken. This Illuſtrious teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of his love to his Subjects
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:119887:68"/> had not wanted a reward to Crown ſo Heroick an Action, if it met with a generous Soul like that of <hi>Alexander</hi> or of <hi>Cae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſar.</hi> VVhen they had the King Priſoner they commanded the Citizens to ſhut the Gates, and keep the VVals leaſt either their own, or the Kings Souldiers ſhould enter the City, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently they fell upon the Kings men, whom they butchered in a moſt cruel manne, but yet the water deſtroyed more then there Swords or Arrows; for many caſt themſelves headlong into the great River of <hi>Cianthang,</hi> which is a Liege brood and runs neer the City, others leaping and overcharging the Boats in the River were preſently ſunck,<note place="margin">Many of the Kings Souldiers drowned.</note> o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>others flying away, full of fear and confuſion, thruſt one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther at the River ſide into that
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:119887:68"/> unmerciful Element, and by all theſe many thouſands periſhed. The <hi>Tartars</hi> wanting boats to paſs this River, having thus ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pelled or killed the Souldiery, they returned Triumphant to the City,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Hangcheu</hi> is taken.</note> where they uſed nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther force, nor violence; by which means this noble City was conſerved, whoſe beauty, greatneſs, and riches, I hope to deſcribe elſewhere, not by hear-ſay, but by what I ſaw the three years ſpace I lived in it, and what I found when lately I came from it, into <hi>Europ.</hi> This City of <hi>Hangcheu</hi> hath an Artificial Channel or Dick to paſs by wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to the Northern parts of <hi>China;</hi> This Chanel is onely ſeparated by the high part of the way like a Cauſe way from the Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, which as I ſaid, runs on the South part of the City. The
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:119887:69"/> 
               <hi>Tartars</hi> therefore drew many Boats out of this Chanel over the Cauſeway into the River <hi>Cien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thang,</hi> and with the help of theſe Boats they paſs the River with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out reſiſtance, and found the fai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt City in all <hi>China</hi> called <hi>Xao<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king</hi> prone enough to ſubmit to their victorious Arms. This City in bigneſs yields to many others, but in cleaneſs and come<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs it ſurpaſſes all: it is ſo in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vironed with ſweet waters as a man may contemplate its beauty by rounding it in a Boat; it hath large and fair Streets paved on both ſides with white ſquare ſtones, and in the middle of them all runs a Navigable Chanel, whoſe ſides are garniſhed with the like ornament, and of the ſame ſtone there are alſo built many fair Bridges and Trium<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phant Arches, the Houſes alſo,
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:119887:69"/> which I obſerve no where elſe in <hi>China</hi>) are built of the ſame ſquare ſtone; ſo as in a word I ſaw nothing neater in all <hi>China.</hi> They took this Town without any reſiſtance, and ſo they might have done all the reſt of the Southern Towns of this Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince of <hi>Chekiang.</hi> But when they commanded all by Procla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation to cut off their Hair, then both Souldier and Citizen took up Arms, and fought more deſperately for their Hair of their Heads,<note place="margin">The <hi>Chi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſes</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend their Hair.</note> than they did for King or Kingdom, and beat the <hi>Tartars</hi> not only out of their City, but repulſt them to the River <hi>Cienthang:</hi> nay forced them to paſs the River, killing very many of them. In truth, had they paſt the River, they might have recovered the Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tropolis with the other Towns:
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:119887:70"/> But they purſued their victory no further, being ſufficiently con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tented that they had preſerved their Hair, reſiſting them only on the South ſide of the ſhore, and there fortifying themſelves. By this means the conquering Arms of the <hi>Tartars</hi> were re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed for a whole year. But the <hi>Chinois</hi> that they might have a Head, choſe <hi>Lu Regulus</hi> of the <hi>Taimingian</hi> Family for their Emperour, who would not ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept thereof, but would be only ſtiled the reſtorer of the Empire. In the mean time the <hi>Tartars</hi> had ſent for new forces out of <hi>Peking:</hi> with which they left nere a Stone unturned, that they might get over the River <hi>Cienthang:</hi> but all was in vain. The drooping Affairs, therefore of the <hi>Chinois</hi> had a breathing: nay having gathered together
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:119887:70"/> more Forces, they promiſed hemſelves greater victories. But a deſire and emulation of ruling fruſtrated all their hopes. For the Commanders, and Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidents which fled the Province of <hi>Chekian</hi> into the Country of <hi>Fokien,</hi> carried with them one of <hi>Taimingas</hi> Family called <hi>Thangus,</hi> and this man they choſe King in the Country of <hi>Fokien,</hi> which confines with <hi>Che<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kiang.</hi> This Prince pretended that the K. called <hi>Lu.</hi> ſhould yield up his right to him, both becauſe he had but a few Cities under him, and alſo, becauſe he was further removed from the Imperial race, then he was. But King <hi>Lu</hi> pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended he was Proclamed by the Army, before him, and wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted not to ſet forth his victories over the <hi>Tartars.</hi> By which two contentions, the <hi>Tartars</hi> came
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:119887:71"/> to the Crown; for theſe two Royalets, would never yield to one another, nor ſo unite their Armies as joyntly to repreſs the <hi>Tartars.</hi> Since therefore this petty King <hi>Lu</hi> had onely eight Cities under his co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mand, whoſe Contributions were not able to maintain the neceſſary pay of his Army, he never durſt ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture to paſs over the River, but endeavoured only to defend himſelf. But the <hi>Tartars</hi> ſought all means poſſibly to get over this River, yet they durſt not venture to paſs in Boats, becauſe King <hi>Lu</hi> had many Ships and good ſtore of Artillery which he had cauſed to come from Sea. But the <hi>Tartars</hi> felicity, and proſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perous fortune, overcame this difficulty: for as it happened that year being dryer then or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary, this River towards the
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:119887:71"/> South, where it runs betwixt high Mountains, which break the ebbing and flowing of the Sea, had loſt much water and of depth, and here the <hi>Tartars</hi> Horſe found it paſſable; and becauſe the rudeneſs of thoſe Mountains,<note place="margin">The <hi>Tar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tars</hi> paſs the River, and reco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver the City <hi>Xao<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king.</hi>
               </note> ſeemed a ſufficient Guard to the Country, they found no Souldiers to reſiſt; but as ſoon as the Clowns eſpied twenty of their Horſe to have paſſed the River, they preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly advertiſed the Army, and they all betook themſelves to flight. King <hi>Lu</hi> himſelf left the City <hi>Xaoking,</hi> and not daring to truſt himſelf to the Conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent, he took Ship and ſayled to the Iſland called <hi>Cheuxan,</hi> which lyes oppoſit to the City of <hi>Nim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pus;</hi> where he remains to this day ſafe, and keeps ſtill his Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gal dignity; which Iſland being
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:119887:72"/> heretofore only a retreit for Fiſhermen, and ſome Clowns, now is become a potent King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom; by reaſon that many fly from <hi>China</hi> to this King <hi>Lu,</hi> as to there ſanctuary to conſerve the liberty of their Hair.<note place="margin">The Iſland of <hi>Cheuxan</hi> becomes a Kingdom.</note> In this Iſland they are now found three<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcore and ten Cities, with a ſtrong and formidable Army, which hitherto hath contemned all the <hi>Tartarian</hi> Power and Forces, and watch for ſome hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py occaſion to advance again their Kingdom in <hi>China.</hi> But by this means, the <hi>Tartars</hi> took all the Cities and Towns of the County of <hi>Chekiang</hi> into their Dominion. One only City of <hi>Kinhoa,</hi> whoſe Preſident was aſwel a Native of the place, as alſo the Commander in Chief, and my very ſingular friend, ſuſtained the <hi>Tartars</hi> aſſaults
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:119887:72"/> for ſome months. But to the end the reſiſtance of this City ſhould not be a hinderance to the courſe of their victories, the <hi>Tartars</hi> divided their Army in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to three parts. The firſt part marched towards <hi>Kiucheu</hi> by the Mountains, the ſecond went by the City <hi>Vencheu,</hi> and the Sea ſhore,<note place="margin">The City of <hi>Kinhoa</hi> is taken and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed.</note> into the Province of <hi>Fokien;</hi> and the third obſtinate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly beſieged the City of <hi>Kinhoa.</hi> In this Siege the <hi>Tartars</hi> by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of great Guns which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually played upon them, and by the wiſe Conduct and cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage of their noble Commander, ſuffered many and great loſſes; inſomuch as he forced them to pitch their Camp further from the City; But at length they alſo brought Artillery from the chief City, by which they made ſo many breaches in the Walls
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:119887:73"/> as being in a manner diſmantled, they found entrance; and bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned and ſacked it with, all ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginable Hoſtility. The Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour blew up himſelf and all his Family with a Barrel of Gun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>powder in his own Pallace, leaſt he, or his, ſhould fall into the Enemies hands.</p>
            <p>The Province of <hi>Fokien</hi> is invironed with the bordering Countries of <hi>Quamgtung, Ki<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anſi,</hi> and <hi>Chekiang;</hi> from all which it is ſeparated by a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinual Chain of Mountains which are even in breadth of three days journey to paſs over; and withall, ſo full of ragged and ruggy Clifts, and obſcure Val<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lys, as they make the very Paths horrid, dark and obſcure at Noon day.<note place="margin">The <hi>Tar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tars</hi> take in <hi>Fok en</hi> very eaſily.</note> Inſomuch, as with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any exaggeration they may well be paralelled either to the
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:119887:73"/> Grecian Straits of <hi>Thermopolis,</hi> or to the <hi>Aſian</hi> ruggy and ſtrait paſſage of <hi>Taurus.</hi> Theſe pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces might have been eaſily de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended if they had but placed a few Clowns, to repel the Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my or overthawrted the ways by any incumbrances; but the very imagination of a <hi>Tartar</hi> was grown ſo terrible to them, as they fled at the very ſight of their Horſes; leaving therefore theſe Mountains wholy ungarni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed the <hi>Tartars</hi> found a paſſage, but ſo very painful, and full of difficulties, as they were forced to leave much of their Bagage behind them; and loſt many of their Horſes, in thoſe fearful precipices; but by this means they took the Province of <hi>Fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kien</hi> with as much eaſe, as it might have been defended, for they hardly ſpent as much time
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:119887:74"/> in taking it as a man would do to walk the extent of it. The King himſelf whom I named <hi>Lunguus</hi> (as ſignifying a Warlike Dragon) ſhewed himſelf a fearful Sheep, flying away, with a good Army of men, if that word of good, can be applyed to a nu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merous multitude that had no hearts;<note place="margin">King <hi>Lunguus</hi> ſlain.</note> but his flight ſerved him for nothing; for the <hi>Tartars</hi> following him with their ſwift and nimb<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e Horſes, ſhot all this heard of ſilly Sheep to death with Arrows. It is thought the King himſelf was involved in this Maſſacre, for he never appeared, nor was heard of after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards.</p>
            <p>Now becauſe the whole Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince ſubmitted it ſelf volunta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily unto him without any re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtance, it did not only ſuffer little from the <hi>Tartars,</hi> but he
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:119887:74"/> may chooſe and ſelect Souldi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers out of it; and having thus again recruited his Army, he made another irruption into the Country of <hi>Quamgtung;</hi> and its worth remarking, that the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Tartarian</hi> Commander who when the Army was divided as I related before, had order to ſubdue the Mediterranean Countries;<note place="margin">The Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinces of <hi>Quantung</hi> is taken.</note> this man with ſome felicity and expedition paſſing victorious through the Provinces of <hi>Huquang</hi> and <hi>Ki<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>angſi,</hi> entred alſo on one ſide of this Country of <hi>Quamgtung,</hi> whilſt the other came in by <hi>Fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kien,</hi> and becauſe the Town of <hi>Nankiung</hi> reſolved to fight it out, they conſumed it all, by fire and ſword. So the poor Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try of <hi>Quamtung</hi> oppreſſed by a double victorious Army, was quickly over-run and ſubdued.
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:119887:75"/> After the Glorious Trophies, one of theſe victorious Armies enriched with all the rarites of <hi>China,</hi> was called back to <hi>Peking,</hi> but yet they left a Garriſon in every City, aſſigning in the name of the King of <hi>Tartars</hi> both Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil and Martial Officers, for the Countries Government.</p>
            <p>The happy ſucceſs in taking the impregnable Province of <hi>Fokien,</hi> is attributed by wiſe men, (to whoſe judgement I alſo ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit) to a more remote and hid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den cauſe which I will briefly relate. There was at this time a famous and renowned Pyrat called <hi>Chinchilungus;</hi> this man was born in the Province of <hi>Fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kien,</hi> of which we are treating; he firſt ſerved the <hi>Porteguiſe</hi> in <hi>Macao;</hi> then he ſerved the Hollander in the Iſland called <hi>Formoſa,</hi>
               <note place="margin">A famous Pyrate in <hi>China.</hi>
               </note> where he was known
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:119887:75"/> to all ſtrangers by the name of <hi>Iquon.</hi> After this he became a Pyrat, but being of quick and nimble wit, he grew from this ſmall and ſlender fortune, to ſuch a height and power, as he was held either Superiour or equal to the Emperour of <hi>China;</hi> for he had the Trade of <hi>India</hi> in his hand; and he dealt with the <hi>Por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tugiſe</hi> in <hi>Macao;</hi> with the Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niards in the <hi>Phillippins,</hi> with the Hollanders in the Iſland <hi>For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſa,</hi> and new <hi>Holland;</hi> with the <hi>Japonians,</hi> and with all the Kings and Princes of the Eaſtern parts in all manner of rich com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modities. He permitted none to tranſport the Wares of <hi>China</hi> but himſelf or his, to whom he brought back the riches and the Silver of <hi>Europ</hi> and <hi>Indies;</hi> for after he once rather extorted then obtained pardon of the King
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:119887:76"/> of <hi>China</hi> for his Pyracies, he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came ſo formidable, as that he had no leſs than three thouſand Ships of which he was Lord and Maſter. Nor was he contented with this fortune, but aſpired privatly to no leſs than to the Empire; But becauſe he knew he never ſhould be accepted of the prefects &amp; people, as long as there was any of the Emperial Fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly of the <hi>Taiminges</hi> alive, he ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped by the <hi>Tartars</hi> means to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinguiſh them wholy, and after this was done, then he reſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved to diſplay his Banners and Enſigns in ſo pious a cauſe, as the driving out the common E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemy from the bowels of the Kingdom, and no doubt but un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der this pretext, they would all have followed, helped and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven adored him, as their Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our.
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:119887:76"/> It was therefore evident that he had ſecret correſpondence with the <hi>Tartars;</hi> and that he favoured them for his own pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit; And that which made the buſineſs more ſuſpicious was, that at that time when the <hi>Tartars</hi> made their irruption into <hi>Foki<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en,</hi> he was then declared Lord Marſhal of the Kingdom, and all the Generals, Commanders and Souldiers, were either of his affinity, or wholy at his Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand and Obedience. And therefore it is no wonder if he found an eaſy admittance into the Country of <hi>Fokien;</hi> of which they preſently made him King <hi>Pingnan,</hi> (as much as to ſay; <hi>Pacifier of the South</hi>) and they added many other Dignities, and Offices of truſt, that they might more ſpeciouſly illude him; for either they knew his aſpiring
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:119887:77"/> mind,<note place="margin">The <hi>Tar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tars</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive the Pyrat, and take him Priſoner by meer Art.</note> or elſe his great power and authority was ſuſpicious and formidable to them; but yet all the while the General of the <hi>Tartars</hi> remained in <hi>Fokien,</hi> they never expreſſed the leaſt diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence in him, but both with fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours, courteſies, preſents and honours, they ſtudied how further to ingage him, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed the Government of many more Provinces. He made him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf therefore ſecure of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment of all the Southern Provinces; but all happened quite contrary to his expectati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; for when this General of the <hi>Tartars,</hi> who was obſerved as a little King, was to depart to <hi>Peking,</hi> the cuſtom was for all the Officers of the Kingdom to conduct him, for ſome part of his journey to give him an ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable farewell; which laſt
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:119887:77"/> duty of Civillity, <hi>Iquon</hi> could not handſomely avoid, nor in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, had he any reaſon to be diffident of any diſtruſt in him; ſo as he left his Navy in the Port of <hi>Focheu,</hi> and accompa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied the Royolet with great ſplendor and magnificence. But when he came to take leave, and demand Licence to return; the General of the <hi>Tartars,</hi> invited him a long to <hi>Peking,</hi> where he promiſed him yet greater ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours from the Kings own per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, to reward his Merits. He endeavoured by all imaginable occaſions, to excuſe this journey, but nothing was accepted, he was forced by their kindneſs to accompany them to <hi>Peking;</hi> and ſo he was taken by Art, who by Arms ſeemed Inſupe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable. He yet lives in Priſon in <hi>Peking,</hi> becauſe his Brothers
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:119887:78"/> and Kindred hearing of his Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tivity, preſently ceaſed on the Fleet; with which they have much infeſted <hi>China,</hi> as we ſhall touch hereafter.</p>
            <p>In the mean time the other Army which had paſſed the Mediterranean Provinces of <hi>Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quang,</hi>
               <note place="margin">The <hi>Tar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tars</hi> over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thrown <hi>Quangſi.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Kianſi,</hi> and <hi>Quamgtung,</hi> invaded the Country of <hi>Quangſi.</hi> But here it was that the Arms of the <hi>Tartars</hi> which hitherto were held invincible, were ſhewed to be weak, and where they leaſt expected oppoſition, there they found the greateſt deſtruction. It happened that in this Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince of <hi>Quangſi</hi> the Vice-Roy, called <hi>Khiu Thomas,</hi> was a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian, and the chief Commander alſo of all the <hi>Militia</hi> of that Country was commanded by <hi>Ching Lucas,</hi> whoſe family for five Genetations has ſerved the
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:119887:78"/> Emperours of <hi>China,</hi> with as much conſtancy and fidelity, as they did Chriſt. Theſe two ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving gathered many together, which fled from all parts into <hi>Quangſi,</hi> after the <hi>Tartars</hi> had taken many places in the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, overthrew the <hi>Tartari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans</hi> in a ſet Battail; and paſſing into the confining Province of <hi>Quamgtung,</hi> they recovered all the Weſtern part of it. After this that they might have a head to fight for, and who might com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand and govern them in all Occurrences, and withall to draw the minds and hands of the <hi>Chineſes</hi> to the common de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence of the Country, knowing that in the City of <hi>Queilin,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Jungley</hi> made Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour of <hi>China.</hi>
               </note> which is the head City of <hi>Quang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſi,</hi> there was one of the <hi>Taimin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges</hi> Family living, who was Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phew to the Great <hi>Vanleius,</hi> they
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:119887:79"/> elected him Emperour, and cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led by the name of <hi>Jungley.</hi> This Prince fixed his Imperial ſeat in the noble City of <hi>Chatking</hi> in the Province of <hi>Quamgtung,</hi> and hitherto has fought ſeveral times with the <hi>Tartars,</hi> with good ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs. And in this Princes Court, the chief Eunuch called <hi>Pang A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chilleus,</hi> is the greateſt favourite, and a great Servant of Chriſt, whom he hath long profeſſed to ſerve both by word and deed; for to propagate Chriſtianity he has ever mantained a miſſion of Jeſuites about him, by whoſe painful endeavours many have embraced the Faith of Chriſt; And amongſt others the very Mother of this Emperour, his Wife,<note place="margin">The Heir to the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes Chriſtian.</note> and his eldeſt Son, Heir of the Empire, called <hi>Conſtantin,</hi> did all imbrace Chriſtianity. May this Man by the prayers
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:119887:79"/> of all Chriſtians prove another <hi>Conſtantine</hi> to the Empire of <hi>China.</hi> The Emperour himſelf is not averſe from Chriſtiany, but hitherto he hath deferr'd his Baptiſm, but yet he permitted his Wife to ſend a Father of the Society to do homage to the Sea Apoſtolick, as all <hi>Europe</hi> has heard. God of his goodneſs grant him that felicity, which may redound to the univerſal good of <hi>China,</hi> and Gods grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Glory.</p>
            <p>But it was not only in <hi>Quang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſi</hi> that the <hi>Chineſes</hi> began to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume their courage,<note place="margin">Theeves infeſt the Province of <hi>Fokien.</hi>
               </note> but in the Province of <hi>Fokien</hi> alſo; for no ſooner was the <hi>Tartarian</hi> Army called back to <hi>Peking,</hi> but a petty Heathen Prieſt broke out of the Mountains of <hi>Fokien,</hi> with a band of ſeditious fellows, and ſubduing the <hi>Tartarian</hi> Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſons
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:119887:80"/> he took the fair City of <hi>Kienning,</hi> and many others from their ſubjection; and others which lay lurking in the Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains following his example, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covered alſo many other Cities; about which time alſo the friends and Kindred of the Captive <hi>I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quon</hi> did extremely infeſt the Sea, and making deſcents upon the Land vexed the Province extremely about the Quarters of <hi>Siuencheu,</hi> and <hi>Changcheu.</hi> At this time the Governour of the Province of <hi>Chekiang</hi> was Vice-Roy of two Provinces, who hearing of theſe commotions came preſently by night in great haſt with all the force he could make, towards the Mountains of <hi>Fokien;</hi> for he with reaſon feared leſt they ſhould take poſſeſſion of the paſſages of thoſe places, which if they had done, the
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:119887:80"/> whole Province had been regai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned. But when this Vice-Roy called <hi>Changus,</hi> found the Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains and paſſages clear, and no oppoſition made in ſuch difficult places, he then proclamed him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf victorious, and his enemies perfidious Rebels:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Changus</hi> the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mander of the <hi>Tar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tars</hi> beſie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges <hi>Kien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning</hi> in vain.</note> wherefore comming without reſiſtance into the Country, he beſieged the City <hi>Kienning,</hi> which was de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended by <hi>Vangus.</hi> This Siege held ſome weeks, but he never could take the place by force, and therefore having loſt many of his men by aſſaults, he jud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged it beſt rather to block up the place a far of, than to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiege it ſo cloſe and neer. But yet by this, he hindred other for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces from joyning with <hi>Vangus,</hi> ſo that he was not ſtrong enough to ſally out upon them.</p>
            <p>When the noyſe of theſe com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>motions
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:119887:81"/> came to <hi>Peking,</hi>
               <note place="margin">It is at length ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken and ra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>d.</note> the Emperour preſently ſent a new ſupply to appeaſe theſe tumults; and this freſh Army comming to joyn with the other, brought the City to great ſtreights; but yet they could not win it, till at length they found means by a rare invention to tranſport their Canons over the Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains upon Porters Shoulders, by which means they diſmant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the Town, and put all what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever to the Sword, to the num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of thirty thouſand perſons, as my own friends writ unto me; and not content with this, they ſet fire on the Town, and brought it all to aſhes, by which means, the ſtately Church ere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted by the Chriſtians for the ſervice of God, was alſo conſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med by that devouring flame; yet the Prieſts that ſerved in
<pb n="151" facs="tcp:119887:81"/> that Church got out miraculouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly as <hi>Lot</hi> did out of <hi>Sodom,</hi> which name was appropriated to this City, by reaſon of that infa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous vice. This City being ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, it was no hard matter to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover the Country; for ſome fled to ſave themſelves in the Mountains, others ran to the Sea, and ſo when this new Army had pacified all, they were cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led back to <hi>Peking;</hi> where it is not amiſs to obſerve the po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licy which the <hi>Tartars</hi> uſe in the Government and ordering of their Army; they are ever cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling back ſome, and ſending out others; in which proceeding they aim at two things; firſt to keep the Countries in awe and ſubjection, by ſeeing variety of Troops continually paſſing up and down; and ſecondly to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vide for the poorer ſort of Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers;
<pb n="152" facs="tcp:119887:82"/> for the wealthy Souldier is call'd back to recreate, and eaſe labours, and the poor Souldier ſeeing his Companion grown rich, takes heart and courage to run the courſe upon hopes of the like good fortune.</p>
            <p>Yet for all theſe preventions and cautions, their Empire was not ſo eſtabliſhed, but by fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent rebellions it was often in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dangered, and particularly by one Rebellion which now I will relate, which ſhaked ſhrewdly the foundations of the new Empire. The Kingdom of <hi>China</hi> is of ſo vaſt an extent,<note place="margin">How the <hi>Tartars</hi> diſpoſe their Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſons.</note> as it is a buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of main importance, to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtribute judiciouſly the Armies, and Garriſons. Now becauſe the <hi>Tartars</hi> alone cannot ſuffice to furniſh both, they are forced to uſe the help of the <hi>Chineſes</hi> themſelves, although they have
<pb n="153" facs="tcp:119887:82"/> a ſpecial care never to leave or place either Commander or Souldier who is a Native of the ſame Country, where they ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>journ; yet this care could not exempt them from ſeveral Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, and Rebellions; yet they diſtribute and order their <hi>Mili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia,</hi> with great circumſpection; for the chief Commander or Governour reſides in the Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tropolitan City, whom all inferiour Officers obey. This man, maintains alwaies a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleat Army, which he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands to march, when he hears of any riſings. Every City has alſo their own proper Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, with a competent number of Souldiers, but thoſe for the moſt part are <hi>Tartars,</hi> and theſe are <hi>Chines.</hi> But all this Politi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal, and well-eſtabliſhed Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment could not defend them
<pb n="154" facs="tcp:119887:83"/> from Traitors amongſt them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves. The firſt man that did revolt from them was one <hi>Kinus</hi> Governour of the Province of <hi>Kiangſi.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Kinus</hi> Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of a Province rebelleth.</note> This man was born in <hi>Leaotung,</hi> and becauſe it is a Country that borders upon <hi>Tar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary,</hi> the King commonly moſt confides in the Natives of that Province. It happened, I know not how, that this Governour, by reaſon of ſome corruptions, and Avarice of the Viſitor of the Country,<note place="margin">The ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt the two Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſturbs the Country of <hi>Kianſi.</hi>
               </note> had ſome difficul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties with him, which grew by little and little to open hatred; and although they both diſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled their private malice, as uſually they do in <hi>China,</hi> yet at length the flame broke out to the ruin of the Country; for being the one was Governour of the Arms, and the other of juſtice, there was a neceſſity of oft
<pb n="155" facs="tcp:119887:83"/> meetings, &amp; feaſtings alſo. It hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened once that whilſt they were feaſted with a ſumptuous Ban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quet, they were alſo intertained by a pleaſant Comedy; in which the Actors were attired with the habits of <hi>China,</hi> which were more comely and fairer than thoſe which the <hi>Tartars</hi> uſe; upon which occaſion <hi>Kinus</hi> tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning himſelf to the Viſitor ſaid, <hi>Is not this habit better, &amp; graver, than ours?</hi> This innocent ſpeech was interpreted by his corrival Judge, as if he had contemned the Edict about changing of Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bits, and expreſſed too much love to the <hi>Chines</hi> Garments, before thoſe of the <hi>Tartars;</hi> and of this he ſent and Expreſs to advertiſe the Emperour.</p>
            <p>But the Governour <hi>Kinus,</hi> had a corrupted Secretary, which ſerved the Lord Chief Juſtice,
<pb n="156" facs="tcp:119887:84"/> who gave him intelligence of all that paſſed in word or deed in his Maſters Houſe. And as ſoon as he had notice that this Letter was ſent to the Court, he pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently diſpatched thoſe who in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tercepted the Packet, which the Governour having read, went preſently armed to the Judges Palace, whom he ſuddainly killed. Then preſently he with the whole Province revolted from the <hi>Tartars,</hi> and with the great applauſe of all the <hi>Chine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes,</hi> he ſubmitted himſelf to <hi>Jug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ley</hi> the new elected Emperour. One onely City called <hi>Cancheu,</hi> which was governed by an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corrupted <hi>Tartar,</hi> refuſed to ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit, which was the whole, and onely cauſe, that the <hi>Tartars</hi> did recover the two Provinces <hi>Ki<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anſi</hi> and <hi>Quamtung;</hi> both which Provinces revolted at the ſame
<pb n="157" facs="tcp:119887:84"/> time with their Commanders, and both ſubmitted alſo to the new elected Emperour.<note place="margin">Many pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces revolt from the <hi>Tartar.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Lihu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus</hi> was Governour of <hi>Quamtung</hi> at that time, who reſolved to joyn his Forces with <hi>Kinus,</hi> and ſo to caſt the <hi>Tartars</hi> out of the Empire; which it is believed they might have affected, if the Governour of <hi>Cancheu,</hi> which is the Key and entrance into four Provinces, had not cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ningly undermined all their deſigns and intentions. But this man hearing that <hi>Lihuzus</hi> had revolted, and marched to joyn his Army with <hi>Kinus,</hi> diſpatched to him this deceitful Letter.<note place="margin">The de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceipt of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernour of <hi>Cancheu.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>I have not hitherto ſubmitted to</hi> Kinus, <hi>becauſe I knew his forces were not equal, nor able, to reſiſt the</hi> Tartars: <hi>But ſeeing thou my moſt renowned and valiant Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, begins alſo to march againſt
<pb n="158" facs="tcp:119887:85"/> them, my hopes are at an end. I am thine, and imbrace thy cauſe; whenſoever thou ſhalt come, or ſend, I will render my City to thee or thine.</hi> But in the mean time he ſent to all the Governours in <hi>Fokien,</hi> to ſend him ſecretly all the poſſible ſuccour they could raiſe altogether. <hi>Lihuzus</hi> having received the Letter marched to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards him, as cheerfully, and as confidently; But though hee found the Gates of the City o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen, yet he was furiouſly repel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led by the <hi>Tartarians</hi> oppoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; which unexpected accident ſo aſtoniſhed his Souldiers, as many of them periſhed, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the reſt it is thought himſelf was killed, for he was never heard of after.</p>
            <p>This reverſe and croſs for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune did much diſturb the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſs of the Emperour <hi>Jung<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ley's</hi>
               <pb n="159" facs="tcp:119887:85"/> affairs, though <hi>Kinus</hi> in the mean time had many ſingular victories over the <hi>Tartars;</hi> for when the chief Governour of all the Weſtern parts of <hi>China,</hi> who had placed his chief Seat in <hi>Nankuing,</hi> had gathered great Forces to repreſs this aſpiring mind, yet he was ſeveral times routed and overthrown by him, and if <hi>Kinus</hi> had purſued the courſe of his victories, he might have come to the very Walls of <hi>Nankuing;</hi> but he was ſollici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tous of the City of <hi>Cancheu,</hi> which obliged him to a retreit; for neither was it ſafe for him to leave an enemy behind him, nor could he receive victuals from the Emperour <hi>Jungley,</hi> but by <hi>Cancheu,</hi> which is the natural deſcent of the River, and therefore when he heard of <hi>Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>huzu</hi>'s defeat, he preſently be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſieged
<pb n="160" facs="tcp:119887:86"/> that City with his whole Army; But whilſt he was be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſieging this City, their came, unfortunately, a new Army of <hi>Tartars</hi> from the Emperial Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of <hi>Peking,</hi> which had order to recover this Province of <hi>Kiang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſi;</hi> and therefore <hi>Kinus</hi> was forced to raiſe his Siege to op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe their entrance by the Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thern parts of the Country; And at firſt having a vaſt Army, and uſed to the <hi>Tartarian</hi> warfare, he fought both valiantly and happily; but not being able to ſuſtain any longer their redou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled violent aſſaults, he was for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced to retire for his ſecurity to the <hi>Nanchang,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Kinus</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſieged by the <hi>Tar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tars.</hi>
               </note> the chief City of that Country; which City the <hi>Tartars</hi> durſt not venture to take by force, but reſolved to reduce it by a long Siege; for which end they gathered together a
<pb n="161" facs="tcp:119887:86"/> Company of Country Clowns to make a large and ſpacious Trench round about the City to the River, and there they placed Ships, ſo as no Proviſion could poſſibly enter. This City of <hi>Nanchang</hi> is great and extreme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly full of inhabitants, beſides the multitude of Souldiers which defended it at that time; ſo as although <hi>Kinus</hi> had made great Proviſion for a Siege, yet after ſome months he came to great want and penury; and yet he held it out though many dyed, expecting ſtill ſome ſuccours from the Emperour <hi>Jungley,</hi> which could not be ſent; becauſe the Souldiers of <hi>Quamgtung</hi> could never ſubdue the City of <hi>Chancheu,</hi> by which his ſuccour was to paſs; wherefore <hi>Kinus</hi> being brought to great extre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity, expreſſed his mind to his
<pb n="162" facs="tcp:119887:87"/> Souldiers in theſe words, <hi>There is no further hope, (my faithful Companions) but in our own va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour and ſtrength, we muſt force our way through the</hi> Tartarian <hi>Army by dint of Sword; be cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragious, and follow my example.</hi> And having ordered all affairs,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Kinus</hi> breaks out of the Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty.</note> he ſuddainly made a Sally out of the Town upon their Tren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, where, though he found a vigorous oppoſition, yet with great difficulty he paſſed and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced their Trenches, by which means he ſaved himſelf and his Army, having killed many <hi>Tartars;</hi> for it is conſtantly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported that <hi>Kinus</hi> with his Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my lives in the Mountains, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecting there ſome good occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion to renew the War.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The City of <hi>Nan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chang</hi> is deſtroyed.</note>He being thus eſcaped, the <hi>Tartars</hi> Pillaged the City, and put all the Citizens to the ſword;
<pb n="163" facs="tcp:119887:87"/> for it is the <hi>Tartars</hi> cuſtom to ſpare all Cities which ſubmit to them, and to thoſe which have made reſiſtance before they were taken they are more trouble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome, but they never ſpare or pardon thoſe Cities which revolt after they have once been taken. In this Slaughter they killed the two Prieſts which aſſiſted the Chriſtians, and their antient and fair Church was burned in the City. After this the <hi>Tartars</hi> eaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly recovered the whole Country, and having appeaſed all, and left new Garriſons in all places, the Army returned victorious to the Royal City of <hi>Peking.</hi> In the mean time this Court pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared new Armies to reduce <hi>Quamgtung</hi> with the other. Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinces which acknowledged <hi>Jungley</hi> for the Emperour of <hi>China;</hi> for the Tutor to the
<pb n="164" facs="tcp:119887:88"/> young King of <hi>Tartary</hi> finding the defections and rebellions in the Southern parts to be very frequent; reſolved to give thoſe Quarters over to ſome Tribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary Royolets,<note place="margin">Three Kings created with as many Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <hi>Jungley</hi> the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour of <hi>China.</hi>
               </note> the better to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain thoſe Countries in their duties; wherefore in the year MDCXLIX. he ſent three Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, conſiſting partly of <hi>Tar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tars,</hi> and partly of <hi>Chineſes,</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der three Tributary Princes, to govern theſe Provinces with ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolute power and Dominion; one of theſe was King of <hi>Fokien,</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother of <hi>Quamgtung,</hi> and the third of the Province of <hi>Quang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſi;</hi> but with this condition, that firſt of all they ſhould joyn their Forces to recover the Country of <hi>Quamgtung</hi> and drive away the Emperour <hi>Jungley.</hi> But we ſhall ſay more of this hereafter; now having ſeen the Rebelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons
<pb n="165" facs="tcp:119887:88"/> of the South, let us look a little back on the Rebellions in the North againſt the <hi>Tartars</hi> alſo.</p>
            <p>In theſe Northern parts the <hi>Chineſes</hi> ſhewed their deſire of Liberty as much as they had done in the South; where the Commanders though over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thrown, yet not taken, retired into the abrupt and precipitious Mountains, where they held Counſel, how they might ſhake off the <hi>Tartars</hi> Dominion; three of theſe heads inhabited the thickeſt and higheſt places of that mountanous Country; the chiefeſt of which was called <hi>Hous;</hi> this man being ſtrong in men, invited the reſt to joyn with him, to deliver his Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try from this miſerable thral<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome; one of them conſented, the other could not come, but
<pb n="166" facs="tcp:119887:89"/> ſent him two thouſand men to aſſiſt him;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Hous</hi> ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the <hi>Tartars.</hi>
               </note> ſo as <hi>Hous</hi> marched out with five and twenty thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand men, which was no con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temptible Army if they had been as couragious, as numerous: He put out a Proclamation, in which he challenged the <hi>Tartars,</hi> and threatned them all extremi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, and to the <hi>Chineſes,</hi> he pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed all liberty and freedom; and upon theſe hopes, many Towns and Cities admitted him very willingly. <hi>Sigan,</hi> the Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tropolitan of the Country, was the only place able to reſiſt him, having in its Walls three thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand <hi>Tartars,</hi> and two thouſand ſelected men of <hi>China,</hi> who ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved the <hi>Tartar.</hi> The Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of this Town hearing of <hi>Hous</hi> his motion, gathered all things neceſſary for a long Siege, till a new ſupply of <hi>Tartarian</hi>
               <pb n="167" facs="tcp:119887:89"/> Forces could be ſent him. But when he heard that all the Towns and Cities in the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try did voluntarily ſubmit them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to <hi>Hous,</hi>
               <note place="margin">The bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barous re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution of a <hi>Tartari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an</hi> Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour.</note> to prevent the like effect in his own City, he reſolved to murder all the Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tizens moſt barbarouſly; nor would he ever be removed from this unhumane ſentence, till the Vice-Roy commanding and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwading, and the Citizens pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſing all faithful ſervice, at length he changed this Tyranni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Counſel. But he comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded under pain of death, that whereas hitherto the <hi>Chineſes,</hi> who loved ſo much their Hair, that they only cut a little of it away, about their Temples, ſhould hereafter ſhave it off who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and totally, that ſo he might diſtinguiſh the Citizens from any others if perchance they en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred:
<pb n="168" facs="tcp:119887:90"/> he ordained beſides, that if any ſpoke more than two to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, they ſhould all be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently killed; he forbad all men to walk upon the Walls, or to walk in the Streets by night, or to keep a Fire or Candle in his Houſe by night, and finally diſarmed all; declaring it death to infringe any of theſe or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders.</p>
            <p>Theſe things being thus or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered,<note place="margin">The chief City cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>Sigan</hi> is beſieged.</note> he ſent out ſome Scouts to diſcover the enemies ſtrength, who were partly killed, and part<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly came flying back to the Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty; but this <hi>Tartarian</hi> Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, as well to make an often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of his ſtrength, as of his ſecurity, commanded the City Gates to be leſt open, nor would he permit the Draw Bridge to be raiſed or pulled up, to ſhew he feared nothing. But for all
<pb n="169" facs="tcp:119887:90"/> this the Commander <hi>Hous</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſieges this City a far off, which was three Leagues compaſs, and out of the reach of their Artil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lery; and to the end he might make a ſhew of greater forces than indeed he had, he joyned to his Army a Company of dull headed Clowns, by which means he made up a Body of thirty thouſand men. The Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernour of the City ſeeing ſuch an Army as appeared, believed them all to be Souldiers, and leſt his Citizens ſhould joyn with them, he thought again of cut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting all their throats; but his friends ever diverted him from this outragious cruelty; and therefore to divert himſelf from ſuch horrid projects, he uſed to walk upon the Walls, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>create himſelf in ſeeing the <hi>Chi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſes</hi> under his colours fight ſo
<pb n="170" facs="tcp:119887:91"/> valiantly againſt <hi>Hous;</hi> for when he ſaw this, he uſed to cry out in their Language, <hi>Hoo Manzu,</hi> (as much as to ſay) <hi>O good Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barians;</hi> for ſo the <hi>Tartars</hi> call the <hi>Chinaes,</hi> as conquering Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions uſe to expoſe the conque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to ſcorn and deriſion; and he crowned this ſcoff with theſe words <hi>Mauzuxa Manzu,</hi> as much as to ſay, let the barbarous kill the barbarous; yet notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding when they returned victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious, he did not onely praiſe them, but gave them Mony, and other pretious rewards, which were expoſed to publick view upon the Walls to animate them to high and generous exploits; ſo as <hi>Hous</hi> finding no Body ſtir in the City, as he expected, could do nothing; beſides their came new ſuccours to the <hi>Tartarian</hi> Army, which when <hi>Hous</hi> under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood
<pb n="171" facs="tcp:119887:91"/> by his ſpys, he preſently retired. But yet this flight did not ſerve his turn, nor could he wholy eſcape the <hi>Tartars</hi> hands, for the Horſemen purſuing them fell upon the rear, and killed many, carrying away great ſtore of Riches, which the Commander diſtributed in ſuch proportion, as he gave moſt to ſuch as were wounded; what became of <hi>Hous</hi> after this action, is unknown, and therefore I conclude that theſe Northern revolts produ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced no other effect, but the ſpoyl, Rapin and Plunder of all thoſe Quarters, as it had produced the like in the Southern parts. The <hi>Tartars</hi> having happily over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come all difficulties hitherto,<note place="margin">The <hi>Tar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tars</hi> inſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lencies produced great dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers.</note> fell into another by their own inſolency; from the yeare MDCXLIX. the Emperour of the <hi>Tartars,</hi> being now grown
<pb n="172" facs="tcp:119887:92"/> up to mans Eſtate, deſired to Marry the Daughter of the King of <hi>Tayngu,</hi> who is Prince of the Weſtern <hi>Tartars,</hi> hoping by this match, to conſerve the friendſhip of him, whoſe Forces he feared; for this end he ſent his Uncle to him, who was King of <hi>Pauang.</hi> This Prince paſſed by the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pregnable City of <hi>Taitung;</hi> which as it is the laſt City towards the North, ſo alſo it is the Key and Bulwork of the Province of <hi>Xanſi</hi> againſt the irruption of the Weſtern <hi>Tartars;</hi> for it com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands all the Souldiers which keep the many Fortifications of thoſe Quarters, where a fair Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vel down extending it ſelf be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond that famous Wall, I mentio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned heretofore, gives a fit occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on for the incurſion of the <hi>Tar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tars.</hi> The Women of this City are
<pb n="173" facs="tcp:119887:92"/> held the moſt beautiful of all <hi>China;</hi> and therefore it happe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, that ſome of the Embaſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dours followers did raviſh ſome of them, and alſo carried away by a Rape, a Perſon of quality, as ſhe was carried home to her Spouſe, which was a thing ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver heard of heretofore amongſt the <hi>Chineſe.</hi> The people had re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe for theſe injuries to <hi>Kian<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gus,</hi> who governed thoſe Quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters for the <hi>Tartars;</hi> who hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of this groſs abuſe, ſent to that petty Prince <hi>Pauang,</hi> to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand the new Married Lady to be reſtored, and to deſire him to prevent future diſorders in that nature; but he gave a very ſlight Ear to ſuch complants, and therefore <hi>Kiangus</hi> himſelf went unto him, who was not only ſlighted, but even caſt out of the Palace. His anger was quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="174" facs="tcp:119887:93"/> turned into rage;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Kiangus</hi> riſeth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the <hi>Tartars.</hi>
               </note> which made him reſolve to revenge that in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jury by the <hi>Tartars</hi> bloud; he therefore Muſters his Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers, and preſently falls on the <hi>Tartars,</hi> kils all he could encoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter; the Embaſſadour himſelf being let down by the Walls of the Town, hardly eſcaped by ſwift Horſes. Then <hi>Kiangus</hi> diſplayed a Banner, wherein he declared himſelf a Subject to the Empire of <hi>China,</hi> but na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med no Emperour in particular, becauſe perchance he had heard nothing of the Emperour <hi>Jung<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ley,</hi> by reaſon of ſo vaſt a di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Kiangus</hi> gathers great For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces.</note> But, however, he invi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted all the <hi>Chineſes</hi> to the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence of their Country, and to expell the <hi>Tartars;</hi> and many Captains as well as Souldiers, came in to him; yea even the very Weſtern <hi>Tartars</hi> againſt
<pb n="175" facs="tcp:119887:93"/> whom he had ever Born Arms, being promiſed great rewards, ſent him the Forces which he demanded. This accident ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tremely troubled the Court; for they knew well that the Weſtern <hi>Tartars</hi> did both aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire to the Empire of <hi>China,</hi> and alſo were envious at their proſperous courſe of fortune; they alſo knew that they were more abundant Men and Hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes than they were; for from hence it is they bought all their beſt Horſes, and they feared that now they ſhould have no more; and therefore they reſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved to ſend preſently a good ſtrong Army againſt him, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he ſhould gather a greater ſtrength. But <hi>Kiangus</hi> who was as valiant as crafty, and one who by long experience knew how to deal with the <hi>Tartars,</hi> firſt
<pb n="176" facs="tcp:119887:94"/> feigned to fly with his Army; But in the rear he placed very many Carts and Wagons, which were all covered very carefully as if they had carried the richeſt Treaſures they poſſeſſed, but in real truth they carried nothing but many great, and leſſer pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of Artillery, with their mouths turned upon the Enemy: all which the <hi>Tartars</hi> perceiving preſently purſue, they fight with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any order, and fall upon the prey with great Avidity; but thoſe that accompanied the Wagons,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Kiangus</hi> over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throws the <hi>Tartars</hi> by a ſtrata<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gem.</note> firing the Artillery, took off the greateſt part of the Army, and withall <hi>Kiangus</hi> wheeling about came up upon them, and made a ſtrange carnage amongſt them; and after this he ſhewed himſelf no leſs admirable in Stratagems than in fortitude and courage,<note place="margin">He beats the <hi>Tartars</hi> again.</note> when he fought a ſet pitched
<pb n="177" facs="tcp:119887:94"/> field with a new recruited Army of the <hi>Tartars,</hi> in which he ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained ſo noble, and renowned a victory, that he filled all the Court at <hi>Peking</hi> with fear and trembling; for by this means victorious <hi>Kiangus</hi> had gathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red ſo vaſt an Army, as he coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted no leſs then a hundred and forty thouſand Horſe, and four hundred thouſand foot, all men having recourſe to him, to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend their Country againſt the <hi>Tartarian</hi> Army; And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>Amavangus,</hi> Tutor to the Emperour, thinking it not fit to commit this buſineſs to any but to himſelf, reſolved himſelf to go againſt <hi>Kiangus,</hi> and try the laſt turn of fortune for the <hi>Tartars;</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Amavan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gus</hi> him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf goes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <hi>Ki<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>angus</hi>
               </note> he therefore drew out all the eight Colours, that is, the whole Forces that were then in <hi>Peking;</hi> for under theſe eight
<pb n="178" facs="tcp:119887:95"/> colours are comprehended all the Forces of the Kingdom of <hi>Chi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na,</hi> whether they be Natives or <hi>Tartars;</hi> the firſt of which is White, called the Imperial Ban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner; the ſecond is Red, the third is Black, the fourth is Yellow; and theſe three laſt are gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned and Commanded by the Uncle of the Emperour, but the firſt is immediatly ſubject to the Emperour; of theſe four colours by ſeveral mixtures, they frame four more, ſo as every Souldier knows his own colours, and to what part of the City to repair, where they have ever their Arms and Horſes ready for any expedition;<note place="margin">The <hi>Tar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tars</hi> Ban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners.</note> ſo as in one half hour they all are ready; for they blow a Horn juſt in the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhion of that, which we appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priate uſually to our Tritons, and by the manner of winding
<pb n="179" facs="tcp:119887:95"/> it, they preſently know, what Companies and Captains muſt march, ſo as they are ready in a moment to follow their En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign, which a Horſe-man carries tyed behind him, though com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly none but the Comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der and Enſign knows whether they go: this profound ſecrecy in their exerciſe of War, has of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten aſtoniſhed the <hi>Chineſes;</hi> for many times, when they thought to oppoſe them in one part, they preſently heard they were in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother Quarter; and it is no wonder they are ſo quick, for they never carry with them any Baggage, nor do they take care for Proviſion; for they fill themſelves with what they find, yet commonly they eat Fleſh, though half roſted, or half boy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led; if they find none then they devour their Horſes, or Camels;
<pb n="180" facs="tcp:119887:96"/> but ever when they have leaſure, they go a hunting all manner of wild Beaſts, either by ſome ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent Dogs and Vultures, which they bring up for that end, or elſe by incompaſſing a whole Mountain,<note place="margin">The <hi>Tar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tars</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light in hunting.</note> or large Field, they beat up all the wild Beaſts into a Circle, and drive them into ſo narrow a Compaſs, as that they can take as many as they pleaſe, and diſmiſs the reſt. The earth covered with their Horſe-cloath is their Bed; for they care not for Houſes, and Chambers; but if they be forced to dwell in Houſes, their Horſes muſt lodge with them, and they muſt have many holes beaten in the Walls; but yet their Tents are moſt beautiful, which they fix and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>move with ſuch Art and dexte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, as they never retard the ſpeedy march of an Army. Thus
<pb n="181" facs="tcp:119887:96"/> the <hi>Tartars</hi> train their Souldiers to hardneſs for War.</p>
            <p>Out of all theſe Enſigns <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mavangus</hi> choſe the choiceſt men to accompany his perſon. And beſides, he took part of thoſe which he had deputed to follow the three Royalets which he diſpatched to the South, or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering them to take as ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny out of the ſeveral Garriſons through which they paſſed, as might ſupply this defect. But yet although <hi>Amavangus</hi> had ſo gallant, and ſuch a flouriſhing Army, yet he never durſt give Battail to <hi>Kiangus,</hi> leſt he might ſeem to expoſe the whole Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire of the <hi>Tartars</hi> to the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune of one Battail;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Amavan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gus</hi> durſt not fight with <hi>Ki<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>angus.</hi>
               </note> So that al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though <hi>Kiangus</hi> did frequently offer him Battail; yet he ever refuſed to fight, expecting ſtill to hear what reply the Weſtern
<pb n="182" facs="tcp:119887:97"/> 
               <hi>Tartars</hi> would make to his Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition of his Nephews Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage; for he had ſent a Legate to that <hi>Tartarian</hi> King with pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious gifts, as well to demand his Daughter for the Emperour of <hi>China,</hi> as to deſire him to afford no ſuccour to the Rebel <hi>Kian<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gus.</hi> The pretious gifts of Gold, of Silk, of Silver, and of Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, obtained whatſoever he demanded; and therefore <hi>Ki<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>angus</hi> ſeeing himſelf deſerted of the <hi>Tartars,</hi> that he might pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vide as well as he could for his own affairs, he returned to the City <hi>Taitung,</hi> of which he ſoon repented himſelf, when it was too late; for <hi>Amavangus</hi> calling in an innnumerable number of Pezants, in the ſpace of three days, with an incredible dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence, caſt up a Trench of ten Leagues co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>paſs, which he ſo for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tified
<pb n="183" facs="tcp:119887:97"/> with Bulworks and Ram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parts, that in a trice he blocked up that City. Then did <hi>Ki<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>angus</hi> ſee his errour in gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting them leaſure to draw their Trench, which he knew would debar him from all manner of Proviſion. And therefore being inraged with anger, as he was a man full of metal, and a great Souldier, turning himſelf to his Souldiers, he ſaid, <hi>If I muſt dye, I had rather dye by the Sword, than by Famin;</hi> and upon this marched out preſently to the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies Trench with his whole Army. Here it was that both the parties fought moſt obſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nately, the one to ſeek his paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage, the other to hinder his ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance; ſo as the fortune was va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious, and the victory doubtful, untill an unlucky Arrow tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peirc'd <hi>Kiangus,</hi> and in him all
<pb n="184" facs="tcp:119887:98"/> the hope of <hi>China</hi> periſhed.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Kiangus</hi> is killed.</note> His Souldiers ſeeing him dead, part<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly run away, and partly ſubmit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to the <hi>Tartars,</hi> who recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved them with all courteſy and humanity; for they had cauſe enough of joy, to ſee they had eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caped the danger of loſing the Empire, and that they had con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quered ſo formidable a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mander. But yet they Plunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red the City <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aitung,</hi> and bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned the City of <hi>Pucheu,</hi> where the Church of the Chriſtians alſo periſhed. From hence the <hi>Tartars</hi> returned to <hi>Peking,</hi> where I ſaw them enter over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loaden with Riches and trium<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phant Laurels; But <hi>Amavan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gus</hi> purſued his journey to the Weſtern <hi>Tartars,</hi> where he ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tified his Nephew <hi>Xunchius</hi> his Marriage,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Xunchius</hi> the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour Marrys.</note> and brought back with him an infinit Company of
<pb n="185" facs="tcp:119887:98"/> Horſe from the <hi>Tartars</hi> of the Kingdom of <hi>Tanyu.</hi> In the mean time, the three Royalets which went to the Southern King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms, to pacify thoſe unquiet Provinces, paſſed their journey by the deſcent of the River <hi>Guei,</hi> and when they paſſed through that Province, which the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour had given the <hi>Tartars</hi> to inhabit, and cultivate, after he had expelled the <hi>Chineſes</hi> for their Rebellion; moſt of theſe Pezants, being wholy ignorant of tilling and manuring the ground, as having never been uſed to mannage a Spade or a Plough, but their Swords, theſe men I ſay, deſired earneſtly theſe Princes, that they might accompany them in theſe Wars, and in their expeditions; Two of theſe Princes rejected their Petitions, but the third called
<pb n="186" facs="tcp:119887:99"/> 
               <hi>Kengus</hi> without any conſent or order from the Emperour, liſted them amongſt his own Troups; upon which they joyfully chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged their ruſtical inſtruments in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to weapons for War; when the Emperour heard of this procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, he ſent word to <hi>Kengus</hi> to diſmiſs them, but he pretended various excuſes, and did neglect the Emperours orders. He there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore commanded the ſupreme Governour of all the Southern Quarters, who reſides ever at <hi>Nanking,</hi> to take <hi>Kengus</hi> either a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>live or produce him dead. He preſently caſt about how to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſs the Emperours command with all ſecrecy, and received the three Royolets with all ſorts of divertiſements, of Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medies, Banquets, and the like pleaſures, as if he had received no diſtaſtfull order from the
<pb n="187" facs="tcp:119887:99"/> Emperour. And when the day was come that they reſolved to proſecute their journey by the great River of <hi>Kiang,</hi> the ſaid Governour contrived his buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs ſo, as he met them again in the River, and under pretence of taking his laſt farewell, he intertained them nobly with a Royal feaſt, and in as Royal a Junck, which in <hi>China</hi> are ſo magnificent, as they reſemble rather ſome gilded Palaces than floating Veſſels. In this Prince<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Ship he entertained theſe Princes in all jollity and mirth, untill their Army had advanced a good way before, and then he declared to <hi>Kengus</hi> the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perours order; who preſently promiſed all ſubmiſſion, and to return to <hi>Nanking</hi> with him, if he would onely permit him to go to his Ship, which expected
<pb n="188" facs="tcp:119887:100"/> him in the River, to order ſome little affairs of his own; which being granted, he no ſooner got into his Ship, but knowing he could not avoid death by ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther mans hand,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Kengus</hi> hangs himſelf.</note> he choſe rather to be his own executioner, and hanged himſelf. Yet for all this, the ſupreme Governour in the Emperours name, granted to this Mans Son the ſame Dignity and Province which had been conferred upon the Father; and thus the three Royalets joyning again, having paſſed <hi>Nanking</hi> and <hi>Kiangſi,</hi> came at length into the Province of <hi>Quamgtung,</hi> to carry on the War againſt the Emperour <hi>Jungley;</hi> and at their firſt entrance, they took many Cities, which were loath to op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe the ſtrength of their Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies; onely, the City of <hi>Quang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheu</hi> reſolved to try its fortune and ſtrength.</p>
            <pb n="189" facs="tcp:119887:100"/>
            <p>This City of <hi>Quangcheu</hi> is a moſt rich and beautiful place, environed with large waters, and is the onely Southern Port within the Land, to which Boats may have acceſs; In this Town was the Son of the Captive <hi>I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quon</hi> whom I mentioned before; beſides, there was a ſtrong Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſon to defend it, and amongſt others many fugitives from <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cao,</hi> who were content to ſerve the Emperour <hi>Jungly</hi> for great ſtipends; and by reaſon the <hi>Tar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tars</hi> had neither Ships, nor skill to govern them, and that the Town had both the one and the other, it is no wonder if they endured almoſt a whole years Siege, having the Sea open for their relief, But they made many aſſaults, in which they loſt many men, and were ever bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten
<pb n="190" facs="tcp:119887:101"/> back, and vigorouſly repel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led. This courage of theirs, made the <hi>Tartars</hi> fall upon a reſolution of beating down the Town Walls, by their great Canon, which took ſuch ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect, as in fine they took it the 24. of <hi>November</hi> MDCL. and becauſe it was remarked that they gave to one of the Prefects of the Town, the ſame Office he had before, it was ſuſpected it was delivered by Treaſon.<note place="margin">The City of <hi>Quang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheu</hi> is ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken and Pillaged.</note> The next day after, they began to Plunder the City, and the ſac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kage endured from the 24. of <hi>November</hi> till the 5. of <hi>Decem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber,</hi> in which they never ſpared Man, Woman or Child, but all whoſoever were cruelly put to the Sword; nor was their heard any other Speech, But, <hi>Kill, Kill theſe barbarous Rebels;</hi> yet they ſpared ſome artificers to
<pb n="191" facs="tcp:119887:101"/> conſerve the neceſſary Arts, as alſo ſome ſtrong and luſty men, ſuch as they ſaw able to carry away the Pillage of the City; but finally the 6. day of <hi>Decem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber</hi> came out an Edict, which forbad all further vexation, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter they had killed a hundred thouſand men, beſides all thoſe that periſhed ſeverall ways du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the Siege. After this bloo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy Tragedy, all the Neighbou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring Provinces ſent voluntarily their Legats to ſubmit, deman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding onely mercy, which they obtained by the many rich pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſents which were offered. Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter this the Royalet marched with his Army, againſt the City <hi>Chaoking,</hi> where the Emperour <hi>Jungley</hi> held his Court; but he knowing himſelf far inferiour in Forces, and unable to reſiſt, fled away with his whole Army
<pb n="192" facs="tcp:119887:102"/> and Family,<note place="margin">The Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour <hi>Jungly</hi> fly<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> leaving the City to the <hi>Tartars</hi> mercy. But whither this Emperour fled, is yet who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly unknown to me, for at this time I took Shipping in <hi>Fokien</hi> to the <hi>Philippines,</hi> and from thence I was commanded to go for <hi>Europe,</hi> by thoſe to whom I conſecrate my ſelf, and all my labours. But I make no doubt, but the Emperour retired into the adjoyning Province called <hi>Quangſi.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now to give the Reader a little touch how the <hi>Tartars</hi> ſtand affected to Chriſtianity, it deſerves to be reflected on, that in the Metropolitan City of <hi>Quangcheu,</hi> which as I now re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated was utterly deſtroyed, there was a venerable perſon, who had the care and ſuperin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendency of all the Chriſtians, whoſe name was <hi>Alvarus Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medo</hi>
               <pb n="193" facs="tcp:119887:102"/> a Jeſuit; this Man they took and tyed hand and foot, for many days, and threatned to kill him every hower, unleſs he would deliver the Chriſtians Treaſures; but the poor Man had no Treaſure to produce; ſo as he ſuffered much, till at length the King hearing of his caſe, took pitty of his venerable gray Heirs and comely perſon, and gave him not onely his life and liberty, but a Bible, and Breviary,<note place="margin">The <hi>Tar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tars</hi> offer a Church to Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans.</note> which is their Prayer Book, together with a good ſum of Mony for an Alms, and finally a Houſe to build a Church for Chriſtians; and this is leſs to be wondred at from him, who heretofore was a Souldier under that famous <hi>Sun Ignatius,</hi> whom I mentioned before, where he knew what belonged to Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianity, and alſo had ſeen the Jeſuits
<pb n="194" facs="tcp:119887:103"/> in the Camp, from whence he fled to the <hi>Tartars.</hi> Nor is it onely this <hi>Tartar</hi> that loves us Chriſtians, but in a manner all the reſt do love, honour, and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteem thoſe Fathers,<note place="margin">The <hi>Tar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tars</hi> em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans.</note> and many have imbraced our Religion, nor do we doubt but many more would follow their example, if we could enter <hi>Tartary,</hi> as now it is projecting, where doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs many great things might be performed, for the reducing of that Nation to the Faith of Chriſt; and perchance God has opened away to the <hi>Tartars</hi> to enter <hi>China,</hi> to give Chriſtiani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty a paſſage into <hi>Tartary,</hi> which hitherto to us have been un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>known and inacceſſible.</p>
            <p>About this time alſo they made War againſt the Kingdom of <hi>Corea;</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Corea</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volted from the <hi>Tartars.</hi>
               </note> for of late years they became alſo Tributary to the
<pb n="195" facs="tcp:119887:103"/> 
               <hi>Tartars,</hi> upon condition that they ſhould ſtill conſerve their Hair and habits: but now the <hi>Tar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tars</hi> would needs conſtrain them to conform themſelves to the <hi>Tartarian</hi> faſhion; and therefore all that Kingdom revolted from the <hi>Tartars;</hi> but my departure hindred me from knowing ſince what has paſſed.</p>
            <p>But all theſe glorious victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries were much Eclipſed,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Amavan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gus</hi> dyeth.</note> by the ſorrowful death of <hi>Amavangus,</hi> which happened in the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of the year MDCLI. He was a Man to whom the <hi>Tar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tars</hi> owe their Empire in <hi>China,</hi> and ſuch an one as whom both <hi>Tartars</hi> and <hi>Chineſes</hi> loved and feared, for his prudence, Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice, humanity, and skill in Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial affairs. The death of this Potentate did much trouble the Court; for the Brother to this
<pb n="196" facs="tcp:119887:104"/> Man called <hi>Quingtus,</hi> would needs pretend to the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Empire, and of the young Emperour <hi>Xunchius,</hi> but both the <hi>Tartars</hi> and the <hi>Chine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes</hi> reſiſted his clame, alleging, that, being of ſixteen year old, he was able to govern the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom himſelf, and in conformity to this opinion, all the Preſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents depoſed the Enſigns of their Offices, refuſing ever to receive them from any, but from the young inſtalld Emperour <hi>Xunchius.</hi> To which Conſtancy the King <hi>Kuintus,</hi> Uncle to the Emperour, prudently yielded, leſt he ſhould exaſperate the minds of many, and raiſe grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter troubles in the Empire than would advance his Family.</p>
            <p>But I cannot doubt, but the death of <hi>Amavangus,</hi> muſt needs trouble the <hi>Tartarian</hi> Empire,
<pb n="197" facs="tcp:119887:104"/> and bring all their affairs into great diſturbance; for they will hardly find a Man ſo beloved, feared, and expert in all Military Diſcipline and Government as he in effect ſhewed himſelf to be; but time will teach us, what will become of all, for ſince his death we have no certainty of any relation; now let us turn the threed of our diſcourſe as I promiſed here above, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider the fortune and ſucceſs of the other Great Brigand cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>Changhienchungus,</hi> to let the Reader underſtand how the <hi>Tartars</hi> did invade not onely the Mediterranean and Oriental parts, but alſo the Occidental Quarters of that vaſt Kingdom.</p>
            <p>But before I begin to ſpeak of this monſter of nature,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Changhien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chungus</hi> a cruel Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant.</note> I muſt ingenuouſly confeſs, I am both aſhamed, and alſo touched with
<pb n="198" facs="tcp:119887:105"/> a kind of horrour, to declare his villanies, both in reſpect they ſeem to exceed all belief, and therefore I may perchance be held to write Fables, as alſo it is not handſome to make reflecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons on ſuch Subjects; yet I may ſincerely proteſt, that I have in my hands a long relation of all his Acts, written by two Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious perſons, who were then in the Province of <hi>Suchuen</hi> to exerciſe their Functions, which Country was the Theater of all his Brutalities which I ſhall relate; and becauſe I judge theſe two perſons to be of an incor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted a Faith, I judge therefore that a mortal Man might arrive to this pitch of wickedneſs and inhuman Cruelty. I therefore gathered out of that relation, what I here relate, which is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing elſe but a vaſt Maſs of
<pb n="199" facs="tcp:119887:105"/> ſuch abhominable Cruelty, as I doubt not even the moſt mildeſt Reader will take the Authour to be no Man but ſome horrid wild Beaſt, or rather if no more exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crable name occurs, ſome De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill tranſveſted in our humane Nature.</p>
            <p>This monſter like a wild Bear entred into divers Provinces, filling all with Rapin, Death, Fire and Sword, with all other imaginable miſeries; for he had a mind to deſtroy all, that ſo he might have no enemies, or leave any alive that might revolt from him, but onely content himſelf with his own Souldiers, and of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten times he ſpared not theſe. But the Province of <hi>Suchuen,</hi> where he uſurped the Title of a King was the chief Theater of his barbarous Cruelty; for af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter he had afflicted and vexed
<pb n="200" facs="tcp:119887:106"/> the Provinces of <hi>Huquang</hi> and <hi>Honan,</hi> and part of that of <hi>Nan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king</hi> and <hi>Kiangſi,</hi> he entred the Province of <hi>Suchuen</hi> in the year MDCXLIV, and having taken the principal City called <hi>Ching<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tu,</hi> in the heat of his fury he killed a King of the <hi>Tamingian</hi> race, which here had eſtabliſhed his Court; as he hath done alſo to ſeve<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> other Grandees of the ſame Family.<note place="margin">He kils divers Princes.</note> Theſe were the Preludes of the Tragical Acts, whoſe Scenſes I go about briefly to deſcribe, that ſo <hi>Europe</hi> may ſee, what a horrid and execra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble thing an unbridled and ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med cruelty appears to be, when it furiouſly rageth in the dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of Infidelity.</p>
            <p>This Brigand had certain vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent and ſuddain buttads of fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious cruelty, and maxims drawn from the very bowels of ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance
<pb n="201" facs="tcp:119887:106"/> it ſelf; for if he were never ſo little offended by another, or ſuſpected another to be offended with him, he preſently comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded ſuch to be maſſacred; and having nothing in his mouth but murder and death, he often for one ſingle Mans fault deſtroy'd all the Family, reſpecting nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Children,<note place="margin">For one offending he puts to death.</note> nor Women with Child; nay many times he cut off the whole Street where the offender dwelled, involving in the Slaughter, as well the inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cents as nocents. It happened once he ſent a Man Poſt into the Country of <hi>Xenſi,</hi> who being glad he was got out of the Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rants hands, would not return; to revenge this imaginary in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jury, he deſtroyed all the Quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of the City in which he dwelt, and thought he much bridled his fierceneſs, that he did
<pb n="202" facs="tcp:119887:107"/> not wholy extinguiſh all the Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty. To this I adde another un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>humane Act about his Hang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, whom it ſeems he loved above the reſt, becauſe he was Crueller than the reſt; when this Man was dead of his Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſe, he cauſed the Phyſician who had given him Phyſick to be killed; and not content with this, he Sacrifiſed one hundred more of that Profeſſion to the Ghoſt of his deceaſed Officer.</p>
            <p>He was affable and ſweet to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards his Souldiers; he played, banquetted, and feaſted with them, converſing familiarly with them; and when they had per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed any Military Action, with honour and valour, he gave them precious gifts of Silks and moneys; but yet many times he commanded ſome of them to be cruelly put to death before him;
<pb n="203" facs="tcp:119887:107"/> eſpecially ſuch as were of the Province of <hi>Suchuen</hi> where he reigned, whom he intirely ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted them, becauſe he thought they did not rejoyce in his Roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al dignity. Inſomuch as he hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ever did any publick Action,<note place="margin">His ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred to the people of <hi>Suchuen.</hi>
               </note> which though it begun like a Comedy, yet had not in fine, the ſad Cataſtrophie of a Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gedy; for if walking out he did but eſpie a Souldier ill clad, or whoſe manner of Gate or walking was not ſo vigorous or Maſculine as he deſired, he pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently commanded him to be killed. He once gave a Souldier a piece of Silk, who complained to his fellows of the pooreneſs of the piece, and being over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heard by a ſpye, (of which he had a great number) who pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently acquainted him with what was ſaid, he preſently comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded
<pb n="204" facs="tcp:119887:108"/> him,<note place="margin">He cuts off a Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion for one Mans fault.</note> and this whole Legion which were of two thouſand Men, to be all Maſſacred.</p>
            <p>He had in his Royal City ſome ſix hundred Prefects, or Judges,<note place="margin">He kils many City Officers.</note> and men belonging to the Law, and ſuch as managed the principal Offices; and in three years ſpace there was hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly twenty left, having put all the reſt to ſeveral deaths for very ſlight cauſes; He cauſed a Sergeant Major which the <hi>Chi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſes</hi> call <hi>Pingpu,</hi> to be flead a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>live, for having granted leave to a <hi>China</hi> Philoſopher, without ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cial order, to retire a little to his Country Houſe. And where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as he had five hundred Eunuchs taken from the Princes of the <hi>Tamingean</hi> Family,<note place="margin">And he killed alſo the Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuchs.</note> after he had put their Lords to death; he commanded all theſe to be cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elly put to death; onely becauſe
<pb n="205" facs="tcp:119887:108"/> one of them had preſumed to ſtile him, not by the Title of a King, but by the bare name of the Theef <hi>Changhienchungus,</hi> as if he then were no Theef.</p>
            <p>Nor did he ſpare the Heathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh Prieſts, who ſacrifiſed to their Idols. Theſe ſort of men, before he came into this Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, having feigned many crimes againſt the Prieſts, which Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched the Faith of Chriſt, had raiſed a bitter perſecution a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them; which God of his goodneſs did turn ſo much to their good, as they had permiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion to teach and Preach pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lickly the Law of Chriſt. But after this Tyrant came into the Country, the chief of theſe Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theniſh Prieſts was apprehended for ſome words let fall againſt him, and in the preſence of the Fathers, who by accident were
<pb n="206" facs="tcp:119887:109"/> then at audience with the Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant, he was beheaded; And al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though they had learned of Chriſt to do good for evill, yet knowing the phrenetical anger and fury of this monſter, who u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to puniſh thoſe that interce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, with the puniſhment of the offender, they durſt not make any motion for the leaſt favour. It is true, this cruel Beaſt loved theſe Fathers, and would often converſe with them, whom he experienced wiſe and learned, and he would often call them to the Palace to entertain him in diſcourſe; but they knowing well his precipitous anger, went ever prepared, and expecting death, and indeed they were thrice deputed to death, and the fourth time eſcaped by Gods particular providence, as we ſhall relate in time and place.
<pb n="207" facs="tcp:119887:109"/> But he was not contented with the death of one of theſe ſame Heatheniſh Prieſts, but having got together about twenty thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand of the ſame profeſſion,<note place="margin">For one Mans fault he kils twenty thouſand.</note> he ſent them all to Hell, to viſit their Maſters whom they had ſerved. And then he would ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaud himſelf as if he had done a very Heroical Action, ſaying to them, <hi>Theſe Men would have taken away your lives; but Thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>encheu,</hi> ſo they call God, which ſignifies the Lord of Heaven, <hi>has ſent me to revenge your cauſe, and inflict due puniſhment upon theſe wretches.</hi> He would often confer alſo with the Fathers of Chriſtian Religion, and that ſo properly as a man would take him for a Chriſtian. He praiſed, and highly extolled the Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion of Chriſtians, which he well underſtood, partly by the
<pb n="208" facs="tcp:119887:110"/> conferences which he frequently had with the Fathers, and partly by reading their Books, which for the Inſtruction of Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans they had writ in the <hi>China</hi> Language; and hath often pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed to build a Church to the God of Chriſtians, worthy of his magnificence, when he once came to be Emperour of <hi>China;</hi> and indeed all the works he ere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted were very ſplendid and magnificent; but he polluted them all with the blood of the Workmen; for if he found they had but committed the leaſt er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour, or the leaſt imperfection, he preſently put them to death upon the place.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">He endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours to take <hi>Han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chung.</hi>
               </note>On the North part of the Cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try of <hi>Suchuen,</hi> where it confines with the Province of <hi>Xenſi,</hi> lyes the ſtrong City called <hi>Nanchung,</hi> which though it be ſeated in the
<pb n="209" facs="tcp:119887:110"/> County of <hi>Xenſi,</hi> yet in reſpect, it is both ſo ſtrong and of ſo great an extent, it is held to be the Key of both the two Provinces. The Tyrant endeavoured by all induſtry to make himſelf Maſter of this important place, as being a convenient paſſage to the reſt; wherefore in the year MDCXLV. he levied a vaſt Army, conſiſting of one hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred and fourſcore thouſand men, all Natives of the County of <hi>Suchuen,</hi> beſides thoſe of his own, which had alwaies fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed him. This numerous Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my beſieged the Town a long time, but found ſo rigorous re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtance, that they began to be weary, and about fourty thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand of thoſe Souldiers of <hi>Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chuen</hi> revolted to the Prefects which governed the beleagured City; by which means the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my
<pb n="210" facs="tcp:119887:111"/> was conſtrained to return to the Tyrant,<note place="margin">He kils 140000 men moſt cruelly.</note> without any me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morable Action: and he being enraged with anger to ſee them return, commanded all the reſt of the Souldiers of the Province of <hi>Suchuen,</hi> which were in num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber one hundred and forty thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand, to be all maſſacred by the reſt of the Army. This horrible Butchery laſted four days; in which ſlaughter he comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded many of them to have their skins pulled of, which he filling with ſtraw, and ſowing on the head, commanded to be carried publickly and viſibly into the Towns where they were Born, ſo to ſtrike more terrour into the hearts of the inhabitants; and after all this, yet he had ſuch a malitious hatred againſt this Country, that they did not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyce that he was King, as he
<pb n="211" facs="tcp:119887:111"/> never ceaſed to vex and torment it, even when it was in a man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner left deſolate. Many unex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pert perſons, without head or guide, did take Arms againſt him, but he quickly diſperſed them, being wholy unexperien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced in Military Diſcipline; o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers that were wiſer, leaving the City, retired into the Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains, which were in a manner the onely Men who eſcaped his fury.</p>
            <p>After this he called all the Students of the Country to be examined for their degrees,<note place="margin">He kils all the Stu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents.</note> promiſing to give thoſe honours, to whomſoever ſhould deſerve them beſt; and the <hi>Chineſes</hi> are ſo bewitched with the deſire of theſe dignities, that they did not conceive the perfidious Strata<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gem of the Tyrant. Their ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared therefore in the publick
<pb n="212" facs="tcp:119887:112"/> Hall deputed for that Ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny about eighteen thouſand per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons; all which he commanded his Souldiers to maſſacre moſt barbarouſly, ſaying, Theſe were the people who by their cavil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling ſophiſms, ſollicited the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple to rebellions.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">He kils the Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren and expoſes the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trons.</note>I have a horrour to relate ſo many unhumane ſlaughters, and yet I ſee my ſelf over-whel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med with new ones; for what an addition is it to all his related barbarities, to tell you, that he never ſpared Children, Boys, nor Girls, no nor Matrons with Child and ready to lye down? what an exceſs of all inhumani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to take the Prefects Wives, when their Husbands were con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned, but yet alive, and to expoſe theſe Women to all kind of villanies, and then to kill them? This was ſo ſenſible to
<pb n="213" facs="tcp:119887:112"/> many, as they rather choſe to kill themſelves, than to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>goe ſo infamous and publick an opprobry by their honeſty. I forbear to relate more of ſuch deteſtable and execrable exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, leſt I offend the ears and minds of the Reader by ſuch abhominations.</p>
            <p>Let us therefore ſuppreſs theſe impurities, and paſs to what hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened in the year MDCXLVI. when the <hi>Tartars</hi> entred into the Province of <hi>Xenſi</hi> to give him Battail, ſo as he was forced to go out to meet them. And, to the end he might leave the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try behind him with more ſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, he reſolved to cut off all the inhabitants, except thoſe which inhabited the North-Eaſt Quarters by which he was to paſs, and therefore muſt needs reſerve theſe Creatures to aſſiſt
<pb n="214" facs="tcp:119887:113"/> and furniſh his Army with all neceſſaries; and therefore he deferred their death to another time. He therefore commanded all the Citizens of what quality or condition ſoever they were, that did inhabit his Metropoli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan City of <hi>Chingtu</hi> to be bound hand and foot,<note place="margin">He kils 600000. in the Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty <hi>Chingtu.</hi>
               </note> which was done by a part of the Army, which he had called in; and then riding about them, which vaſt multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude is related to have been a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove ſix hundred thouſand Souls, he viewed them all with leſs compaſſion than the cruelſt Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger would have done; whilſt in the mean time, theſe poor victims with lamentable crys, which penetrated the very vault of Heaven, and might have mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved a heart compoſed of ſtone or Rock, holding up their hands, begged of this outragious Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant
<pb n="215" facs="tcp:119887:113"/> to ſpare the lives of his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent people. He ſtood a while Penſive, like an aſtoniſhed and amazed Creature, ſo as it ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med to be an imperfect <hi>Criſis,</hi> wherin humane nature ſtruggled a little with thoſe bowels, and that heart which was compoſed of all cruelty; but preſently re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turning to his beaſtly nature, <hi>Kill, Kill,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>and cut off all theſe Rebels,</hi> upon which words, they were all maſſacred in one day out of the City Wals, in the preſence of this bloody monſter. Thoſe Religious perſons which are there, the Fathers of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianity, reſolved to make their addreſſes for the Tyrant to ſave their innocent ſervants lives; and though all men judged it a deſperate attempt, yet they ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained the lives of thoſe they claimed. So as they diſtributed
<pb n="216" facs="tcp:119887:114"/> themſelves at the City Gates, and as their Clients paſſed bound to the Shambles, they mercifully unbound their Shakles, and reſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cued them from death. By which occaſion alſo they performed another acceptable Sacrifice to God, in Baptizing an infinit number of Children,<note place="margin">Many Children Baptized.</note> which the Souldiers willingly permitted, ſo as the horrid and execrable cruelty of this Tyrant proved as advantagious to theſe little Angels, as <hi>Herods</hi> ſlaughter did to the Bleſſed Innocents.</p>
            <p>They write, that in this maſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſacre their was ſo much blood ſpilt, as made the great River of <hi>Kiang,</hi> which runs by the City, to increaſe and ſwell viſibly; and the dead Corps being caſt into the River, and carried downwards to the other Cities, did denounce unto them, that
<pb n="217" facs="tcp:119887:114"/> they were to expect no better Treaty from this Tyrants hands. And it quickly proved true, for he diſpatched his Army to the reſt of the Cities, and killed all that he could lay hands on; and thus this Tyrant did bring that populous Province of <hi>Suchuen</hi> into a vaſt wilderneſs. After this, he muſtered all his Souldiers in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a Field, which in <hi>China</hi> is ever deputed for that end, and is called by the Natives <hi>Kioo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chang,</hi> in this place, he delivered himſelf thus unto them, <hi>I hope by your valour to obtain the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire of the world, when I have expelled the</hi> Tartars; <hi>but I deſire to ſee you yet quicker and nim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bler than hitherto you have been; you all know, to free you from all burdens and heavy luggage, how I ſunck threeſcore Ships full of Silver in the River of</hi> Kiang;
<pb n="218" facs="tcp:119887:115"/> 
               <hi>which I can eaſily recover, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward your pains and merits, when I ſhall once have obtained the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire;</hi> he had indeed ſunk the Ships, and killed the Ship-men, to conceal the place; <hi>but there remains yet a greater encum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance, which retards much our journy, and all our enterpriſes, which is your Wives, which are a heavy burden to you all; There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore put on a generous reſolution, There will not be wanting other exquiſit Women, when we are come to poſſeſs the Empire; and although as Emperour I ought to have ſome Prerogative, and make a difference betwixt you and my Royal perſon, yet I am content in this, to give you all a leading example, which may ſerve as a Preſident.</hi>
               <note place="margin">He kils all the Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers Wives.</note> After this Speach, of three hundred handſome and beautiful Maids, which he kept
<pb n="219" facs="tcp:119887:115"/> for his voluptuous pleaſures, he onely reſerved twenty to ſerve his three Queens, and comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded all the reſt to be killed upon the place. The Souldiers pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently followed the example and command of their cruell Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant, and cut off the heads of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>numerable innocent Women, as if they had been their mortal enemies.</p>
            <p>Having now no more men in the Province of <hi>Suchuen</hi> to put to death,<note place="margin">He burned his Palace in the Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of <hi>Ching<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tu.</hi>
               </note> he turned his fury and hatred againſt Cities, Houſes and Palaces: for whereas he had built himſelf a very ſtately and magnificent Palace in the City of <hi>Chingtu,</hi> he conſumed that, and with it, a great part of that noble City with fire; beſides he cut down all Trees and Woods, that they might profit no man. And thus (as he ſaid)
<pb n="220" facs="tcp:119887:116"/> having purged his Army, he marched on into the Province of <hi>Xenſi</hi> to meet the <hi>Tartars;</hi> but as he marched, if he found any man remaining alive, he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded him to be killed. And not content with all this, if he eſpied any Souldier which mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched either too far before, or too far behind, though the fault were never ſo little, he killed him preſently. He killed all his ſick or weak Souldiers, that they might be delivered (as he ſaid) out of ſo miſerable and ruined a Country. I ſuppreſs many more paſſages of his cruelty, becauſe I will haſten to the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taſtrophe of this Tragedy.</p>
            <p>He was no ſooner entred in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Province of <hi>Xenſi,</hi> but one of the Emperours Uncles meets him with five thouſand <hi>Tartars,</hi> and the Body of the Army mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched
<pb n="221" facs="tcp:119887:116"/> after him; five Horſemen run before the Army as uſually they do amongſt the <hi>Tartars;</hi> who if they be well received of the enemy, they retire, and take it as a ſign of Peace and ſubmiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion; but if they receive any Act of hoſtility, then they march up to fight. Theſe Horſemen were eſpied by the Tyrants Scouts, who preſently brought him ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings of their approach. But he laughed at the news, and jeſting<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly asked them, If the <hi>Tartars</hi> had learned to fly. He had at that time many perſons tyed before him, which he intended to maſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſacre, and amongſt the reſt two of the Jeſuits, for asking leave to return into <hi>Suchuen,</hi> which was the Country they had un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertaken to convert to Chriſtia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity. But the ſuddain death of this Archbrigand delivered them
<pb n="222" facs="tcp:119887:117"/> all, from the imminent danger; for at the ſame time came in his chief Commanders, aſſuring him the <hi>Tartar</hi> was upon him; upon which news, he being of a bold and couragious humour, burſt out of his Tent, and without ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther head-piece or breſt-Plate, ſnatched up a Lance, went out with a few, to view the enemy. The <hi>Tartars</hi> preſently aſſaulted the Tyrant; and the firſt diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charged Arrow, which was as happy to the <hi>Tartars,</hi>
               <note place="margin">The Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant is ſlain.</note> as it was to many others, peirced the heart of that monſter of Cruelty, kil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling that Man, who had an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention to make an end of all Men; and who from the baſe condition of a raskally Theef, preſumed to take the Sacred Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle of King and Emperour. The head being down, the <hi>Tartars</hi> eaſily ſeized on the body of his
<pb n="223" facs="tcp:119887:117"/> Army; but many of the Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers ſubmitted to them, others were killed, others run away; and the poor inhabitants of the Province of <hi>Suchuen</hi> received the <hi>Tartars</hi> as their Saviours.<note place="margin">The Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince of <hi>Suchuen</hi> is made ſubject to the <hi>Tar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tars.</hi>
               </note> By which means this Province, which is the moſt Weſtern in <hi>China,</hi> and borders upon the Kingdom of <hi>Tibet,</hi> became ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject to the <hi>Tartarian</hi> Empire.</p>
            <p>When they had eſtabliſhed Garriſons, and all their other affairs in that Country, they prepared to return to the Royal City of <hi>Peking;</hi> leading with them the two Captive Prieſts, which they had found in Chains, as a preſent moſt acceptable to the <hi>Tartarian</hi> Emperour, there I ſaw then, and left them in great veneration and honour in the year MDCL.</p>
            <p>But this victorious Conque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour
<pb n="224" facs="tcp:119887:118"/> returning crowned with Laurels,<note place="margin">One of the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perours Uncles is ill recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved.</note> was ill received and worſe recompenſed, by his Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the great <hi>Amavangus,</hi> who was the Emperours Tutor; and inſtead of a deſerved tryumph, he received an unworthy death; for being to make a march of many Months, to undergo much labour, and many troubles, it happened ſo, as he loſt more Men in marching than in fight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; he was accuſed of great negligence in governing his Army; and being of a generous nature, he thought he deſerved high praiſe, but no blame, and therefore he took his <hi>Tartarian</hi> Cap, and ſcornfully trampled it upon the ground, which is the greateſt ſign of indignation, which they can expreſs; upon which fact he was committed to a Priſon proper to thoſe of the
<pb n="225" facs="tcp:119887:118"/> blood Royal which he accuſed of any Crime; But he ſcorned to be the firſt of the <hi>Tartarian</hi> Family, which ſhould ſuffer this firſt opprobry in <hi>China;</hi> and therefore before he was carried to this Priſon called by the <hi>Chi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſe Coaciang,</hi> he hung himſelf miſerably in his own Palace.<note place="margin">He hangs himſelf.</note> A Gallant Prince, and worthy of a better fortune. Many think this diſgrace to have grown from <hi>Amavangus</hi> his eldeſts Brothers emulation; but I think that <hi>Amavangus</hi> was affraid that this Man wanting neither courage, nor wit, would quickly ruin the <hi>Tartarian</hi> affairs, by his raſh proceedings. And here I will put a period, rather then an end, to this brief Narration of the <hi>Tartars</hi> War to the year MDCLI. in which year I was ſent to <hi>Europe,</hi> by thoſe that
<pb n="226" facs="tcp:119887:119"/> may command me. In which relation if there be nothing elſe worthy of admiration, yet it ſeems admirable to conſider, that in ſeven years ſpace, they conquered more ground in Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gitude and Latitude, then an Army could have walked in that ſpace of time; for they over-run twelve vaſt Provinces of <hi>China;</hi> beſides the immenſe extents of <hi>Leaotung,</hi> and the Kingdom of <hi>Corea.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>VVhat ſince has paſt in ſuch viciſſitude of fortune, I know not; but as ſoon as God ſhall bleſs me with a proſperous re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn into my beloved <hi>China;</hi> or that my friends acquaint me with any new Occurrances by Letters; I will procure all <hi>Europe</hi> ſhall underſtand the Iſſue of theſe prodigious revolutions.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="addendum">
            <pb n="227" facs="tcp:119887:119"/>
            <head>An Addition to the former Hiſtory, taken out of the laſt Letters from <hi>China,</hi> Written in the years 1651. 52. and 53.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Fter the Printing of this our Hiſtory of the <hi>Tartarian</hi> Wars, returning to <hi>Bruſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels</hi> from <hi>Amſterdam</hi> (where I uſed all poſſible expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition to bring my <hi>Atlas Sinieus</hi> to the Preſs) I there, received my long deſired Letters from <hi>China,</hi> ſent by my friends from <hi>Rome;</hi> ſome of which being da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the 14. of <hi>November</hi> 1651. were writ by a <hi>Sicilian</hi> called Father <hi>Francis Brancatus,</hi> who ſojurns in the City of <hi>Xanchai</hi> in the Province of <hi>Nanking;</hi> and
<pb n="228" facs="tcp:119887:120"/> reflecting, that happily it would not be ungrateful to our <hi>Euro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peans,</hi> if I made a private rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of publick uſe; I reſolved to draw out this little enſuing Narration from thoſe Letters written in ſeverall years.</p>
            <p>The Empire of <hi>China</hi> is now grown to a more fixed and ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led Eſtate,<note place="margin">See fol. 165.</note> ſince the death of <hi>Amavangus</hi> Uncle to the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour: who as he was the firſt Man that ſuggeſted to the <hi>Tar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tars</hi> the Emperours invaſion, ſo alſo, it is to his care and vigilan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy they owe the happy ſucceſs of all, and its conſervation.</p>
            <p>But yet, the opinion framed of him after his death, was far different from the authority and power he carried in his life; for no ſooner was the power of reigning by his death devolved into the hands of his Nephew called <hi>Xunchi;</hi> but that this Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour,
<pb n="229" facs="tcp:119887:120"/> though a youth in years, began his reign by the approba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of all eſtates and orders, with ſuch maturity of judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and Councel, as he ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med to ſurpaſs the gray and hory heads of his wiſeſt Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellors. He was no ſooner in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throned, then he expreſſed a ſtrange ripeneſs of judgement and Juſtice joyned together in the ſame Action;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Amavan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gus</hi> ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected and puni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed after his death.</note> for having diſcovered his Uncles wicked Councels and Deſigns, and tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced the obſcure track of his ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hominable vices, which were hid during his life: he did ſo much reſent thoſe deteſtable Acts, as he commanded his bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to be digged up, and his mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nificent Sepulcher to be beaten down;<note place="margin">The vene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of dead mens tombs; a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the <hi>Chi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſes.</hi>
               </note> which kind of puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment amongſt the <hi>Chineſes</hi> it held to be the greateſt that can be inflicted; being taught by
<pb n="230" facs="tcp:119887:121"/> their Religion to carry all ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration and reſpect to the tombs of dead perſons. The Carcaſs being dragged out, they firſt beat it with Clubs, then they ſcour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged it with Rods; and finally cutting off the head, they made it a ſpectacle to all Criminal op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probies. Thus the ſplendour of his Tomb, was brought to duſt; and fortune payed him after his death, the turn, ſhe owed him in his life. He puniſhed alſo all the Officers and Prefects, which were privy to his Councels; putting ſome to death, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priving others of their digni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties. Amongſt all which I find the fortune of General <hi>Fung</hi> to have been very various: who though he be no Chriſtian, yet being a ſingular friend, prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor of my order, and particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly known to my ſelf, I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not but rejoyce to hear him re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtored
<pb n="231" facs="tcp:119887:121"/> to his place and dignity, after his diſcovered innocency. In the mean time the Emperour <hi>Xunchius,</hi>
               <note place="margin">The Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour of the <hi>Tar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tars</hi> Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage and their cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoms.</note> growing up to Mans eſtate, and ſollicitous to propa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gate his Auguſt off-ſpring, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved to accompliſh his long intended Marriage with the Daughter to the Emperour of the Occidental <hi>Tartars:</hi> In which action the <hi>Tartars</hi> imitate the <hi>European</hi> cuſtom; for they take a Lady of ſome illuſtrious blood or deſcent; But the Emperours of <hi>China</hi> ſeem little to value the nobility of blood, but ſelect the primeſt beauty; nor will they refuſe a perſon of a mean for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune, if ſhe be but graced with beauty; In ſo much, as the Wife to the late Emperour of <hi>China,</hi> was Daughter to a Man, that got his living by making ſtraw Shoos. So King <hi>Ahaſuerus</hi> raiſed a poor Captive Maid to be Confort with him in his Royal
<pb n="232" facs="tcp:119887:122"/> Throne: which kind of cuſtom happily the <hi>Chineſes,</hi> drew from the <hi>Perſians,</hi> or elſe the <hi>Perſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans</hi> had it from them. But to return to the ſubject that cauſed this little digreſſion. The Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perours VVedding was perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med with a Pomp and ſplendor proportionable to ſuch an Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire: nor was there any magni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficence wanting on the Spouſes part; for according to the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhion of the Nation, ſhe came accompanied with whole Armies of Men, and ſo many Troops of Horſe, as they ſeemed innu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merable; nature ſeeming to have framed the riches of the <hi>Tartars</hi> more for warlike affairs, than for pleaſure. Nor is this infinit multitude of Horſe incredible, for I my ſelf have ſeen eighty thouſand Horſe, all at one time, ſent as a preſent from the Occi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dental <hi>Tartars</hi> to the King of <hi>China.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="233" facs="tcp:119887:122"/>
            <p>Which boundleſs power of the <hi>Tartars,</hi>
               <note place="margin">The <hi>Tar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tars</hi> ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>due the reſt of <hi>China.</hi>
               </note> as it cannot be contained within any limits, ſo alſo it broke out into the Province of <hi>Quam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tung,</hi> which they wholy ſubdued; and out of that, like an impetu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Torrent, they ran into the Province of <hi>Quangſi;</hi> which they likewiſe conquered to their Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire. So as the King of <hi>China</hi> called <hi>Jungley,</hi> with his chief favourit the Eunuch, called <hi>Pang Achileus,</hi> who profeſſeth Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianity, were feign to fly to the confines of <hi>Tunking,</hi> being in a manner excluded the whole Empire. In ſo much as a friend of mine writes out of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince of <hi>Fokien,</hi> that the King <hi>Jungley</hi> fearing to fall into the <hi>Tartars</hi> hands, was feign to leave the Land, and fly to Sea. But upon what Coaſt that unmerciful Element may have caſt him, we know not, for we hear no news
<pb n="234" facs="tcp:119887:123"/> of our Father <hi>Andrew Xauerius Koffler</hi> who ever followed the Court of King <hi>Jungley,</hi> having had the happineſs to have Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized his Queen, his Son, and his Mother with many others of that diſtracted Court.</p>
            <p>In the mean time, whilſt one <hi>Cang,</hi> a Royolet amongſt the <hi>Tartars,</hi> ſubdued the Province of <hi>Quangſi,</hi> the Governour of the Country, whom they call <hi>Colaus,</hi> fell into the Enemies hands, and the <hi>Tartars</hi> hoping by rewards and promiſes of dignities, to ſoften the mind of this ſo gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lant a Man,<note place="margin">The great fidelity of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernour to his King.</note> and ſo eminent a Philſopher, abſtained three days from any cruelty, or ill uſage; But he ſcorned to prefer his life before his alleageance and fide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity to his King; and therefore loſt his head.</p>
            <p>But yet, this generous Action was admired and honoured by
<pb n="235" facs="tcp:119887:123"/> thoſe brutiſh Souls, who pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently erected a magnificent Tomb, in memory of ſo honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable an Act; for although the <hi>Tartars</hi> ſollicit the <hi>Chineſes</hi> to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volt from their Prince, yet they honour and praiſe ſuch as ſhew themſelves conſtant to him; And this memorial, I owe unto his memory, well for his ſingu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar friendſhip he was pleaſed to contract with me, as alſo to his eminent vertues, of which, I my ſelf and the whole Church of Chriſtians in <hi>China,</hi> were both Spectators and Admirers, for the ſpace of twenty years. And that his name may not pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh, nor his Country; he was Born in the Province of <hi>Nan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quin</hi> in the City <hi>Changcho;</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing called <hi>Kiu Thomas,</hi> a name worthy of eternal memory, in the Temple of vertue.</p>
            <p>During the ſaccage of theſe
<pb n="236" facs="tcp:119887:124"/> Provinces; news arrives from the Country of <hi>Suchuen,</hi> that the notorious Brigand called <hi>Changhienchungus,</hi> famous for his infamous cruelty and abho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minable villanies,<note place="margin">See fol. 197.</note> was broke out again, and waſted all that Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince with ſeverall tempeſts of War; for though he ſeemed to be quite vanquiſhed in the laſt Battails, yet he appeared again to trouble and vex the Empire with new Garboyls, and fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Deſigns of War.</p>
            <p>The Province of <hi>Fokien</hi> alſo began to grone under the ſame miſerable condition of VVar; for the Reverend Father <hi>Peter Canevari</hi> Native of <hi>Genua,</hi> writes out of the City <hi>Chang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheu</hi> which was beſieged the 30. of <hi>March</hi> 1652. that <hi>Queſingus</hi> having made a deſcent from his Ships into that Province had overrun the whole Country, ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken
<pb n="237" facs="tcp:119887:124"/> ſome Cities and Towns, and carried on the War with great terrour to the Inhabitants. Inſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much as the <hi>Tartarian</hi> Comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders kept themſelves, and their Army in their Forts, and other places of ſtrength, not daring to appear in the field to oppoſe them; but yet he ſayd they ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected new Forces and Succours from <hi>Peking;</hi> by which they doubt not, but quickly to ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>due him.</p>
            <p>This <hi>Queſingus,</hi> who now vexeth this Province of <hi>Fokien,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Queſingus</hi> the Pyrat.</note> is Son to the famous Pyrate <hi>I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quon</hi> or <hi>Chinchilungo</hi> whom the <hi>Tartars</hi> impriſoned by a ſlight, as I recounted to you in my for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer Hiſtory.</p>
            <p>And to let you know what I heard from ſome paſſengers of <hi>China,</hi> who in the month of <hi>Ja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuary</hi> 1653. were caſt, in a Ship of <hi>China,</hi> upon the Coaſts of an
<pb n="238" facs="tcp:119887:125"/> Iſland called <hi>new Holland;</hi> whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther I had been brought before by their Barks, and Souldiers as their Priſoner; Theſe Men related that a great Army of <hi>Tartars</hi> was arrived, to ſubdue <hi>Queſingus;</hi> whoſe Commander thought it fit to joyn art to his great Force, and therefore he commanded a handfull of Men to charge the <hi>Tartarian</hi> Army, and preſently by feigning flights to retire to more advantagious and ſurer places. But in the mean time, he had placed a number of Horſe in a deep valley behind a Mountain, towards which Quarters the fugitive Troops re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tired. This flight gave courage to the <hi>Tartars,</hi> and the deſire of victory, made them venture ſo far from the River <hi>Chang,</hi> where their Ships lay at Anchor, as they found themſelves enviro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by the <hi>Tartars</hi> Army. This
<pb n="239" facs="tcp:119887:125"/> deſperate condition which ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded the <hi>Chineſes,</hi> from retur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning to their Ships, cauſed a ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſad, and bloody Battail, in which there periſhed above 8000 of the <hi>Chineſes</hi> Army;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Queſingus</hi> defeated.</note> whilſt <hi>Queſingus</hi> a ſpectator of this ſad accident from the Maſt of his Ships, and as they relate, was heard to ſay, that he would once more try his fortune againſt the <hi>Tartars;</hi> but if ſhe proved a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain adverſe unto him, he then would ſubmit, and ſhave his Hair, like a <hi>Tartar.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Having briefly related the State of the Temporality in this Kingdom, it remains I ſhould touch a little of the State of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianity, ſince theſe great revolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions.</p>
            <p>In which ſubject, I can onely ſay, that being at <hi>Bruſels</hi> this laſt <hi>June</hi> in the year 1654. I recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved Letters from <hi>China,</hi> in which
<pb n="240" facs="tcp:119887:126"/> they gave me notice that the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Jeſuits, were very favou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rably treated by the <hi>Tartars;</hi> yea better than before, for they permitted free exerciſe of the Chriſtian Catholick Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, through an their King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms, granting them leave not onely to enjoy their antient Churches, but did alſo liberally contribute to build new ones; So by the goodneſs of God, that which endamaged others, proved gain to them. But I reſerve all particulars to a larger relation in a greater volumn, which ſhall continue, <hi>Trigautius</hi> his Hiſtory <hi>of the miſſions diſpatched into China;</hi> and conſidering he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cludes that Hiſtory in the year 1610. it ſhall be my endeavour to produce the reſt of thoſe me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morable Actions to theſe our preſent times.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:119887:126"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
